<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="tagDoc" id="tagDesc_timeline"><h2>&lt;timeline&gt; timeline</h2><h3>Description:</h3><p> Provides a set of ordered points in time to which musical elements can be linked in
      order to create a temporal alignment of those elements. The origin attribute designates
      the origin of the timeline, i.e., the time at which it begins. It must point to one of
      the when elements in its content. Units specifies the unit of time corresponding to the
      value of the interval attribute of the timeline or of its constituent points in time.
      The mediacontent attribute is provided in order to link the timeline to a particular
      external media file, such as an audio file. The medialength attribute specifies the
      length of the external media file in terms of the unit attribute. This element is
      modelled on an element in the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI). 
   </p><h3>May contain:</h3><p><a title="Show description of when-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/when">when</a></p><h3>May occur within:</h3><p><a title="Show description of scoredef-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/scoredef">scoredef</a></p><h3>Attributes:</h3><ul><li><p><span class="attributeName">mediacontent</span>, optional, xs:anyURI 
            <span class="description">holds the web-addressable location of the external
               digital media.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">medialength</span>, optional, xs:positiveInteger
            
            <span class="description">indicates the length of the external digital
               file.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">n</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">provides a label (name or number) for an element. While
               its value need not be unique, it is required to be a single token.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">origin</span>, required, xs:IDREF 
            <span class="description">designates the origin of the timeline, i.e. the time at
               which it begins.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">unit</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">indicates the units used for a measurement, usually
               using the standard symbol for the desired unit.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">xml:id</span>, optional, xs:ID 
            <span class="description">regularizes the naming of an element and thus
               facilitates building links between it and other resources. Each id attribute
               within a document must have a unique value.
            </span></p></li></ul><h3>Module:</h3><p> linkalign </p></div>