<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="tagDoc" id="tagDesc_mdiv"><h2>&lt;mdiv&gt; musical division</h2><h3>Description:</h3><p> The mdiv element may contain one or both of 2 possible views of the music. The score
      view is the traditional full and open score while the parts view contains each
      performer's view of the score; that is, his part. These 2 views are necessary because it
      is not always possible or desirable to generate one from the other. The score and parts
      elements are placed here and not directly within the body element because score and part
      characteristics may change from mdiv to mdiv. For example, the 2nd movement of a
      symphony may require different performing forces (and therefore different score and part
      layout) than the other movements. The mdiv element may be recursively nested in order to
      represent music which exhibits this kind of structure. For example, an opera is normally
      divided into acts, which are in turn divided into scenes. This may be represented by the
      following markup: &lt;mdiv&gt; &lt;- the opera &lt;mdiv&gt; &lt;- act I &lt;mdiv&gt;
      &lt;- scene i &lt;mdiv&gt; &lt;- scene ii &lt;/mdiv&gt; &lt;mdiv&gt; &lt;- act II
      &lt;mdiv&gt; &lt;- scene i &lt;mdiv&gt; &lt;- scene ii &lt;/mdiv&gt; &lt;/mdiv&gt; 
   </p><h3>May contain:</h3><p><a title="Show description of mdiv-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/mdiv">mdiv</a>, <a href="/documentation/tagLibrary/parts">parts</a>, <a title="Show description of score-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/score">score</a></p><h3>May occur within:</h3><p><a title="Show description of body-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/body">body</a>, <a href="/documentation/tagLibrary/mdiv">mdiv</a></p><h3>Attributes:</h3><ul><li><p><span class="attributeName">facs</span>, optional, xs:IDREFS 
            <span class="description">permits the current element to reference a facsimile
               image or image zone which corresponds to it.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">n</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">provides a label (name or number) for an element. While
               its value need not be unique, it is required to be a single token.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">subtype</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">provide any sub-classification for the element,
               additional to that given by its type attribute.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">type</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">characterizes the element in some sense, using any
               convenient classification scheme or typology.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">xml:id</span>, optional, xs:ID 
            <span class="description">regularizes the naming of an element and thus
               facilitates building links between it and other resources. Each id attribute
               within a document must have a unique value.
            </span></p></li></ul><h3>Module:</h3><p> shared </p></div>