<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="tagDoc" id="tagDesc_eventlist"><h2>&lt;eventlist&gt; event list</h2><h3>Description:</h3><p> Contains historical information given as a sequence of significant past events.
      &lt;eventlist&gt; contains &lt;event&gt; elements that contain a brief description of
      the associated event, including dates and locations where the event took place. An
      &lt;eventlist&gt; describes events associated with a work when it appears in the
      &lt;profiledesc&gt; element or events associated with the custodial history of a given
      copy of a source for the encoding when it appears within the &lt;source&gt; element. The
      type attribute may be used to distinguish between event lists with different functions,
      such as a list of events in the compositional process and a list of performance dates. 
   </p><h3>May contain:</h3><p><a title="Show description of event-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/event">event</a></p><h3>May occur within:</h3><p><a title="Show description of profiledesc-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/profiledesc">profiledesc</a>, <a title="Show description of provenance-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/provenance">provenance</a></p><h3>Attributes:</h3><ul><li><p><span class="attributeName">analog</span>, optional, CDATA 
            <span class="description">contains a reference to a field or element in another
               descriptive encoding system to which an MEI element is comparable. Mapping
               elements from one system to another may help a repository harvest selected
               data from the MEI file to build a basic catalog record. The encoding system
               from which fields are taken must be specified. When possible, subfields as
               well as fields should be specified, e.g., subfields within MARC
               fields.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">n</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">provides a label (name or number) for an element. While
               its value need not be unique, it is required to be a single token.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">subtype</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">provide any sub-classification for the element,
               additional to that given by its type attribute.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">type</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">characterizes the element in some sense, using any
               convenient classification scheme or typology.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">xml:id</span>, optional, xs:ID 
            <span class="description">regularizes the naming of an element and thus
               facilitates building links between it and other resources. Each id attribute
               within a document must have a unique value.
            </span></p></li></ul><h3>Module:</h3><p> header </p></div>