<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="tagDoc" id="tagDesc_part"><h2>&lt;part&gt; part</h2><h3>Description:</h3><p> An alternative visual rendition of the score from a particular performer's point of
      view. Part elements are not used in the score to indicate voice leading. Next attributes
      on event elements should be used for this purpose. Part elements are useful for encoding
      individual parts when there is no score, such as early music part books, when the music
      has non-aligning barlines, when different layout, such as page turns, are needed for the
      score and parts, or for accommodating software that requires part-by-part encoding. When
      assembly of the parts into a score is desired and there are non-aligning barlines,
      barlines which indicate points of alignment across all the parts may be marked as
      'controlling', while non-aligning ones may be marked as 'non-controlling'. 
   </p><h3>May contain:</h3><p><a title="Show description of ending-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/ending">ending</a>, <a title="Show description of section-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/section">section</a></p><h3>May occur within:</h3><p><a title="Show description of parts-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/parts">parts</a></p><h3>Attributes:</h3><ul><li><p><span class="attributeName">copyof</span>, optional, xs:IDREF 
            <span class="description">points to an element of which the current element is a
               copy.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">corresp</span>, optional, xs:IDREFS 
            <span class="description">used to point to other elements that correspond to this
               one in a generic fashion.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">n</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">provides a label (name or number) for an element. While
               its value need not be unique, it is required to be a single token.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">next</span>, optional, xs:IDREFS 
            <span class="description">used to point to the next event(s) in a user-defined
               collection.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">prev</span>, optional, xs:IDREFS 
            <span class="description">points to the previous event(s) in a user-defined
               collection.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">sameas</span>, optional, xs:IDREFS 
            <span class="description">points to an element that is the same as the current
               element but is not a literal copy of the current element.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">subtype</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">provide any sub-classification for the element,
               additional to that given by its type attribute.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">synch</span>, optional, xs:IDREFS 
            <span class="description">points to elements that are synchronous with the current
               element.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">type</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">characterizes the element in some sense, using any
               convenient classification scheme or typology.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">xml:id</span>, optional, xs:ID 
            <span class="description">regularizes the naming of an element and thus
               facilitates building links between it and other resources. Each id attribute
               within a document must have a unique value.
            </span></p></li></ul><h3>Module:</h3><p> shared </p></div>