<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" id="mainframe" class="oneColumn"><div id="content"><h1>History</h1><p>
            Seeing the need for a comprehensive markup language in the academic music community, in
            1999 Perry Roland of the University of Virginia set about creating an XML schema (DTD)
            for the representation of music notation. Eventually this DTD became known as MEI
            because it was influenced by the same principles that guided the creation of the Text
            Encoding Initiative (TEI). Mr. Roland first presented his work at the first
            International Symposium on Music Information Retrieval in 2000. Many presentations
            followed including:
        </p><ul><li>Musical Applications using XML (MAX) conference, Milan, 2002</li><li>MusicNetwork Notation Workshop, Leeds, 2003</li><li>ISMIR, Baltimore, 2003</li><li>Online Chopin Variorum Edition (OCVE) workshop, Philadelphia, 2004</li><li>Digital Humanities conference, Urbana-Champaign, 2007</li><li>TEI Members' Meeting, College Park, 2007</li></ul><p>
            In 2005 to help support these efforts the University of Virginia Library offered support
            for a 2-year pilot project to demonstrate the capability of MEI to faithfully represent
            a sample of music scores found in <em>Beyond MIDI: The Handbook of Music Codes</em>
            (Selfridge-Field, Eleanor, ed. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1997), to investigate methods
            for transforming MusicXML-encoded data into the MEI format, and finally, to ensure that
            the semantic information encoded in MEI could be rendered as traditional music
            notation.
        </p><p>
            In the summer of 2007, Mr. Roland was approached by representatives of the German markup
            community, regarding the integration of text markup and music markup. This led to a
            presentation on MEI to the Arbeitsgruppe Musikcodierung in der Akademie der
            Wissenschaften und Literatur in Mainz, in July, 2007 and collaboration with:
        </p><ul><li>Stefan Morent of the University of Tübingen to develop features within MEI for the
                representation of medieval notation; and</li><li>Johannes Kepper and Daniel Röwenstrunk, both from <a href="http://www.edirom.de/index.php?id=1&amp;L=1">Edirom</a>, to refine MEI
                handling of score facsimiles and editorial intervention.</li></ul><p>
            Initial results of these collaborations were demonstrated at the conference "Digitale
            Edition zwischen Experiment und Standardisierung", held in Paderborn, Germany in
            December, 2007. During a lecture on music editing, they wondered if digitized editorial
            reports might be easier to understand than those in print format. After receiving
            assistance from the <a href="http://www.dfg.de/en/index.jsp">German Research Foundation
                (DFG)</a>, a prototype for digital music editions was created. In 2005, this
            prototype, containing Carl Maria von Weber's Clarinet Quintet, op. 34, was published at
            no charge as an addition to the printed edition of the Weber-Gesamtausgabe (Complete
            Works). This was the first complete computer-based scholarly edition of a piece of music
            from the Common Western Notation period. Due to its wide approval among musicologists
            and editors, the DFG granted funds for five more years, beginning in 2006. Edirom
            employs MEI in its prototype-successor software.
        </p><p>
            During a one-week workshop on "<a href="http://www.dagstuhl.de/de/programm/kalender/semhp/?semnr=09051">Knowledge Representation for Intelligent Music Processing</a>"
            at the Leibnitz Center for Informatics at the Schloss Dagstuhl at the end of January
            2009, a small MEI study group was founded. One of the main topics during the Dagstuhl
            discussions was the question of data interchange between different encoding systems.
            Under the guidance of Andreas Kornstaedt (Hamburg), a list of features currently
            supported by existing formats was created, the so-called "Dagstuhl Core". This document
            was used in the discussions regarding the creation of a requirements list for encoding
            music notation as part of the meeting in Charlottesville mentioned below.
        </p><p>
            Collaboration between the research being performed in Germany and the development of the
            standard being conducted in the United States is currently supported by a <a href="http://www.neh.gov/grants/guidelines/DFG_BSW.html">DFG/NEH Bilateral Digital
                Humanities Program: Bilateral Symposia and Workshops grant</a>. This one-year grant (<a href="/downloads/MEI-final-proposal-workshop.pdf">proposal</a>)
            is providing much needed funding to address the lack of standardization plaguing the
            representation of music by supporting two workshops attended by an international group
            of scholars representing musicology, music theory, librarianship and technologists.
        </p><p>
            The first of the two workshops took place in Charlottesville, Virginia, July 29<sup>th</sup>-31<sup>st</sup>,
            2009. At this meeting it was decided that MEI held the most promise for an open-source,
            scholarly standard for music representation. Following this decision, the group quickly
            turned its attention to development work necessary for the growth of MEI. A list of
            potential users and uses for the standard was recorded. A functional requirements
            document was drafted and is currently being revised. Based on the functional
            requirements, a work plan for the technologists has been developed which includes the
            revision of the schema and the creation of a tag library. Following the revision of the
            schema, sample scores selected by the workgroup that illustrate problems in successful
            music encoding will be encoded in MEI. Perceived by all participants as a great success,
            this workshop marked the beginning of MEI development as an international community
            driven effort. Our progress can be monitored at www.mei-c.org.
        </p><p>
            The second DFG/NEH funded meeting was held in Detmold Germany in March 2010. At this
            meeting, the group reviewed the finished examples, schema and tag library. In addition,
            a plan for continued development and dissemination of the results of our efforts was
            created and will be submitted to the DFG and NEH and implemented by the current MEI
            Advisory Board. Also at the meeting was a series of reports by people and groups
            currently working with MEI.
        </p></div></div>