<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" id="mainframe" class="oneColumn"><div id="content"><h1>Introduction</h1><p>   
            The Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) is a community-driven effort to create a
            commonly-accepted, digital, symbolic representation of music notation documents. We
            strive to establish the design principles and the technological and representational
            requirements that will enable the discipline of musicology to take full advantage of
            digital technologies. We are working to provide guidelines and tools that can be widely
            used by libraries, museums, and individual scholars to encode musical scores for
            research, teaching, and preservation activities.
        </p><p><img class="block" alt="Scope of MEI" title="Scope of MEI" src="/pix/images/scopeMEI.png" style="width: 400px; height: 259px;"/>
            The MEI schema is a set of rules for recording the intellectual and physical
            characteristics of music notation documents so that the information contained in them
            may be searched, retrieved, displayed, and exchanged in a predictable and
            platform-independent manner. Because of its emphasis on comprehensibility and software
            independence, the data format defined by the schema may also serve an archival function.
        </p><p><a href="http://neh.gov/"><img class="floatLeft" alt="National Endowment for the Humanities" title="National Endowment for the Humanities" src="/pix/images/hzonlineart.png" style="width: 86px; height: 85px;"/></a><a href="http://www.dfg.de/en/index.jsp"><img class="floatRight" alt="Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft" title="Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft" src="/pix/images/dfg_logo_schwarz.png" style="width: 86px; height: 30px;"/></a>
            This project is supported jointly by the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Deutsche 
            Forschungsgemeinschaft. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in this 
            publication do not necessarily reflect those of the National Endowment for the Humanities or the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft.
        </p>
        <!--<p>
            The Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) schema is a set of rules for recording the
            intellectual and physical characteristics of music notation documents so that the
            information contained in them may be searched, retrieved, displayed, and exchanged in a
            predictable and platform-independent manner. The MEI rules are expressed in the form of
            a RelaxNG (RNG) schema.
        </p>
        <p>
            The MEI is a community driven effort striving to make possible for music the same kinds
            of operations that are commonly performed on electronic texts such as compiling musical
            corpora, data interchange, and comparative analysis. Also, because music research
            routinely combines the study of manuscript sources, printed music editions and
            time-based media, the group is developing an encoding mechanism that facilitates the
            creation and management of relationships between components of digital versions of these
            materials.
        </p>--></div></div>