<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" id="mainframe" class="oneColumn"><div id="content"><h1>Projects</h1><p>
            On this page you will find short reports about several ongoing projects using MEI for different purposes.
            There are other projects as well, and it is intended to introduce them at this site successively.           
        </p><ul class="headedEntriesList"><li><h1>MEI editor</h1><div class="subTitle">Julian Dabbert, Detmold</div><p>
                    The MEI editor currently in development aims to enable the users to view
                    and graphically edit MEI-encoded music documents in CWN (Common Western
                    Notation). The supported function set is only a subset of the features
                    contained in MEI, excluding more exotic features such as medieval neumes
                    and features that are graphically complex to implement. This reduction in
                    scope strives to enable the realization within the framing <a href="http://www.textgrid.de">TextGrid</a>
                    project's runtime ending in summer 2012. Work on the featured component
                    MEI editor begun in December 2009 and is scheduled to deliver a working
                    prototype by fall 2011.
                </p></li><li><h1>Case Study Report: Debussy's Syrinx (La Flûte de Pan)</h1><div class="subTitle">Raffaele Viglianti, London</div><p>
                    Syrinx (La Flûte de Pan) by Claude Debussy (1862 - 1918) is a short piece
                    for flute solo originally composed as a theatrical interlude called La
                    Flûte de Pan. Comparing the first edition (published posthumously in
                    1927), a manuscript discovered in 1991, a 1996 edition, and a 1922 Music
                    and Letters article by the first performer of La Flûte de Pan, this report
                    investigates the potential of digital representation and presentation of
                    comparative editions of music using MEI.
                </p></li><li><h1>Haydn by Hand</h1><div class="subTitle">Christine Siegert, Bayreuth</div><p>
                    One of the editors of the new edition of <a href="http://www.haydn-institut.de/">Haydn's complete works</a>, reports
                    on the possibilities that MEI offers for scholarly music editions, using
                    partial encodings of two aria arrangements made by Joseph Haydn for the
                    Esterházy court. The first aria, "Non per parlar d'amore", is taken from
                    Niccolò Piccinni's opera L'avaro. The second example is Haydn's
                    arrangement of the aria "Vorrei punirti, indegno" from Pasquale Anfossi's
                    opera La finta giardiniera.
                </p></li><li><h1>Cataloguing with MEI</h1><div class="subTitle">Axel Teich Geertinger, Copenhagen</div><p>
                    The <a href="http://www.kb.dk/da/kb/nb/mta/dcm">Danish Centre for Music Publication</a> (DCM) was searching for a data
                    format suitable for the preparation, flexible presentation and long-term
                    storage of its future editions. The Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) seemed
                    to be by far the most promising approach for this purpose, providing not
                    only the desired flexibility and accessibility inherent to XML in general,
                    but also explicitly addressing the needs of scholarly editions of music
                    such as variant encoding, annotation, and detailed source description. On
                    this background, DCM decided to build an infrastructure based on an MEI
                    file repository. A database serves as a file table for the XML file
                    repository, while the metadata editor itself, implemented in XHTML, uses
                    XForms to read in the MEI XML model, populate it, add or modify elements
                    and attributes, and store it.
                </p></li></ul></div></div>