<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
  NOTICE: Copyright (c) by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Board (formerly known as "MEI Council").

  Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
  not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License
  at https://opensource.org/licenses/ECL-2.0.
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
  OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language
  governing permissions and limitations under the License.
  
  This is a derivative work based on earlier versions of the schema © 2001-2006 Perry Roland
  and the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia; licensed under the Educational
  Community License version 1.0.
  
  CONTACT: info@music-encoding.org
-->
<?xml-model href="../validation/mei_odds.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../validation/mei_odds.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
     xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     version="5.0"
     rend="book"
     xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">The Music Encoding Initiative Guidelines</title>
            <title level="a">Lyrics and Performance Directions</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Edited by</resp>
               <!-- tbd -->
               <name role="edt">tbd</name>
               <note>The editors listed here are responsible for the contents of this very chapter of the MEI Guidelines.</note>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>With contributions by</resp>
               <!--TODO: To be filled automatically via GitHub API-->
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/bwbohl">Benjamin W. Bohl</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/BruxDDay">BruxDDay</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/ndubo">Norbert Dubowy</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/fujinaga">Ichiro Fujinaga</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/axgeertinger">Axel Geertinger</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/ahankinson">Andrew Hankinson</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/irmlindcapelle">irmlindcapelle</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/frakel">franz kelnreiter</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/kepper">kepper</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/zolaemil">Zoltan Komives</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/DDMAL-LabManager">DDMAL LabManager</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/uliska">Urs Liska</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/elsinhadl">Elsa De Luca</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/napulen">Néstor Nápoles López</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/MajaHartwig">MajaHartwig</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/musicEnfanthen">Stefan Münnich</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/pe-ro">pe-ro</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/lpugin">Laurent Pugin</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/JRegimbal">Juliette Regimbal</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/rettinghaus">Klaus Rettinghaus</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/aseipelt">Agnes Seipelt</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/martha-thomae">Martha E. Thomae</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/raffazizzi">Raffaele Viglianti</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/vigliensoni">Gabriel Vigliensoni</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/th-we">Thomas Weber</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/musicog">David M. Weigl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Board</distributor>
            <availability>
               <p>
                  <hi>Music Encoding Initiative (MEI)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>NOTICE: Copyright (c) by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Board (formerly known as "MEI Council").</p>
               <p>Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
                                            not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the
                                            License at <ref target="http://opensource.org/licenses/ECL-2.0">http://opensource.org/licenses/ECL-2.0</ref>.</p>
               <p>Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under
                                            the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
                                            KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language governing
                                            permissions and limitations under the License.</p>
               <p>This is a derivative work based on earlier versions of the schema copyright (c)
                                            2001-2006 Perry Roland and the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia;
                                            licensed under the Educational Community License version 1.0.</p>
               <p>CONTACT: contact@music-encoding.org </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital: No previous source exists.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="lyricsperfdir" type="div1">
            <head>Lyrics and Performance Directions</head>
            <p>This chapter describes how to encode words and syllables in vocal notation. This text is typically written under a staff to indicate the text to be vocally performed. As such, this text should not be confused with other text on the score, for which see chapter <ptr target="#textencoding"/>.</p>
            <div xml:id="lyricsDesc" type="div2">
               <head>Vocal Text</head>
               <p>These guidelines suggest two methods for encoding text in vocal notation: encoding syllables as <ptr target="#lyricsInEvents"/> and encoding performed text as <ptr target="#lyricsAfterEvents"/> after the notes (and other staff events) either within <gi scheme="MEI">layer</gi> elements or within <gi scheme="MEI">measure</gi> elements when available (for example in a Common Music Notation context). Each method may be more convenient depending on the source text and on the textual phenomena that the encoding intends to record.</p>
               <p>Both methods eventually rely on the <gi scheme="MEI">syl</gi> element, which is part of the ‘shared’ module and is therefore available in all MEI files. The following sections will begin by introducing the general use of <gi scheme="MEI">syl</gi> and then show in detail the two different encoding methods.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="lyricsSyl" type="div2">
               <head>Lyric Syllables</head>
               <p>By ‘lyric syllable’, these guidelines mean a word or portion of a word that is to be performed vocally. Each syllable is encoded with the <gi scheme="MEI">syl</gi> element, with which it is also possible to specify the position of the syllable in a word, the type of connectors between syllables, alignment adjustments, and the formatting for each syllable. These are the key components:</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="syl"/>
                     <specDesc key="att.syl.log" atts="wordpos con"/>
                     <specDesc key="att.horizontalAlign" atts="halign"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p>The attribute <att>wordpos</att> is used to specify the position of the marked-up lyric syllable in a word. It allows the following values:</p>
               <list type="gloss">
                  <label>i</label>
                  <item>Indicates that the current syllable’s position is initial; that is, at the beginning of a word;</item>
                  <label>m</label>
                  <item>Indicates that the current syllable is in the middle of a word;</item>
                  <label>t</label>
                  <item>Indicates that the syllable’s position is terminal; that is, at the end of a word.</item>
               </list>
               <p>When a syllable is at the beginning or in the middle of a word (in which case it will have the <att>wordpos</att> attribute set to ‘i’ or ‘m’), it is recommended to specify the type of connector written between the current and the following syllable. This is expressed with the <att>con</att> attribute, which takes the following values:</p>
               <list type="gloss">
                  <label>s</label>
                  <item>A space is used as a connector between syllables;</item>
                  <label>d</label>
                  <item>A dash is used as a connector between syllables;</item>
                  <label>u</label>
                  <item>An underscore sign (indicating prolongation of the syllable) is used as a connector between syllables;</item>
                  <label>t</label>
                  <item>A tilde is used to indicate elision with the following syllable. This is typically rendered as a small curved line between the syllables.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Occasionally, a word or a final syllable needs to be extended across multiple notes. In this case an ‘extender’ is provided. An extender is a continuous line drawn at the text’s baseline from the end of the syllable associated with the first note until the last note to be sung with the syllable.</p>
               <p>The use of <gi scheme="MEI">syl</gi> described in this section is common to CMN and other notation systems, such as mensural notation. Other uses specific to certain types of notation and repertoires are addressed in other chapters. See for example <ptr target="#neumes"/>.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="lyricsInEvents" type="div2">
               <head>Vocally Performed Text Encoded Within Notes</head>
               <p>Each lyric syllable can be encoded directly within an associated note, either by using the <att>syl</att> attribute on <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi> or the <gi scheme="MEI">verse</gi> element.</p>
               <p>Using the <att>syl</att> attribute on notes is the simplest way of encoding vocally performed text and is recommended only for simple situations or for those encodings which do not focus on vocally performed text.</p>
               <p>The following example from <name ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Frideric_Handel">Handel’s</name> <hi rend="italic">Messiah</hi> (HWV 56) shows the use of <att>syl</att>:</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Handel, Messiah HWV 56, Hallelujah</head>
                     <graphic url="../images/modules/lyrics/ex_syl_att.png"/>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head/>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/lyricsDesc/lyricsDesc-sample280.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>When there are multiple lines of vocally performed text, or the encoder wishes to be more specific about connectors, etc., the use of <gi scheme="MEI">verse</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">syl</gi> is recommended.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="verse"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p>The following example from <name ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Frideric_Handel">Handel’s</name> <hi rend="italic">Messiah</hi> (HWV 56) shows the use of <gi scheme="MEI">verse</gi>:</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head/>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/lyricsDesc/lyricsDesc-sample281.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>As it is common practice in written text, it is assumed that a space separates words. Many vocal texts, however, introduce elisions and connect two syllables into one unit. For example, the vocal text from Mozart’s <hi rend="italic">Don Giovanni</hi> sung by Don Giovanni in Finale II, <quote>Ho fermo il core in petto</quote> introduces an elision between the word fermo and il and between core and in. An elision can be indicated by placing both syllables within the same <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi> and setting the <gi scheme="MEI">syl</gi> element’s <att>con</att> attribute value to 't':</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head/>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/lyricsDesc/lyricsDesc-sample282.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>When there is more than one line of text, more than one <gi scheme="MEI">verse</gi> element can be used. The following example from a piano reduction of Wagner’s <hi rend="italic">Rheingold</hi> has two lines of text, with an English translation on the second line. Note the use of the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute to differentiate the two languages:</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Example from Wagner’s Rheingold with translated text.</head>
                     <graphic url="../images/modules/lyrics/ex_verse_m.png"/>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head/>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve" valid="feasible"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/lyricsDesc/lyricsDesc-sample283.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Optionally, it is possible to include an <gi scheme="MEI">lb</gi> element within <gi scheme="MEI">verse</gi> to explicitly encode line and line group beginnings. This is specifically meant to facilitate karaoke applications.</p>
               <p>Finally, the <att>rhythm</att> attribute on <gi scheme="MEI">l</gi> can be used to specify a rhythm for the syllable that differs from that of the notes on the staff (see <ptr target="#lyricsAfterEvents"/>).</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="lyricsAfterEvents" type="div2">
               <head>Vocally Performed Text Encoded Separately</head>
               <p>Vocally performed text may also be encoded separately from the notes with the <gi scheme="MEI">lg</gi> element. These are the main components:</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="lg"/>
                     <specDesc key="l"/>
                     <specDesc key="att.staffIdent" atts="staff"/>
                     <specDesc key="att.layerIdent" atts="layer"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p>Since this element is separated from the encoding of the notes, it must be associated with a staff that will provide rhythm information when required for automated processing. The <att>staff</att> attribute gives the associated staff and if there is more than one layer on that staff, the <att>layer</att> attribute may be used to indicate the layer from which the rhythm should be taken. If there is any divergence between the rhythm of the vocally performed text and the notes, the <att>rhythm</att> attribute on <gi scheme="MEI">l</gi> may be used to specify the text’s rhythm.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head/>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve" valid="feasible">
                        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/lyricsDesc/lyricsDesc-sample284.txt" parse="text"/>
                     </egXML>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="drama" type="div2">
               <head>Drama</head>
               <p>This section is supposed to explain stage directions and speeches in MEI drama.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
