<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
  NOTICE: Copyright (c) by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Board (formerly known as "MEI Council").

  Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
  not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License
  at https://opensource.org/licenses/ECL-2.0.
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
  OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language
  governing permissions and limitations under the License.
  
  This is a derivative work based on earlier versions of the schema © 2001-2006 Perry Roland
  and the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia; licensed under the Educational
  Community License version 1.0.
  
  CONTACT: info@music-encoding.org
-->
<?xml-model href="../validation/mei_odds.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../validation/mei_odds.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
     xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     version="5.0"
     rend="book"
     xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">The Music Encoding Initiative Guidelines</title>
            <title level="a">Linking Data</title>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Edited by</resp>
                <name role="edt">Stefan Münnich</name>
                <name role="edt">David M. Weigl</name>
                <note>The editors listed here are responsible for the contents of this very chapter of the MEI Guidelines.</note>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>With contributions by</resp>
               <!--TODO: To be filled automatically via GitHub API-->
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/bwbohl">Benjamin W. Bohl</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/BruxDDay">BruxDDay</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/ndubo">Norbert Dubowy</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/fujinaga">Ichiro Fujinaga</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/axgeertinger">Axel Geertinger</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/ahankinson">Andrew Hankinson</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/irmlindcapelle">irmlindcapelle</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/frakel">franz kelnreiter</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/kepper">kepper</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/zolaemil">Zoltan Komives</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/DDMAL-LabManager">DDMAL LabManager</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/uliska">Urs Liska</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/elsinhadl">Elsa De Luca</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/napulen">Néstor Nápoles López</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/MajaHartwig">MajaHartwig</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/musicEnfanthen">Stefan Münnich</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/pe-ro">pe-ro</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/lpugin">Laurent Pugin</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/JRegimbal">Juliette Regimbal</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/rettinghaus">Klaus Rettinghaus</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/aseipelt">Agnes Seipelt</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/martha-thomae">Martha E. Thomae</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/raffazizzi">Raffaele Viglianti</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/vigliensoni">Gabriel Vigliensoni</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/th-we">Thomas Weber</name>
               <name ref="https://api.github.com/users/musicog">David M. Weigl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Board</distributor>
            <availability>
               <p>
                  <hi>Music Encoding Initiative (MEI)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>NOTICE: Copyright (c) by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Board (formerly known as "MEI Council").</p>
               <p>Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
                                            not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the
                                            License at <ref target="http://opensource.org/licenses/ECL-2.0">http://opensource.org/licenses/ECL-2.0</ref>.</p>
               <p>Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under
                                            the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
                                            KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language governing
                                            permissions and limitations under the License.</p>
               <p>This is a derivative work based on earlier versions of the schema copyright (c)
                                            2001-2006 Perry Roland and the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia;
                                            licensed under the Educational Community License version 1.0.</p>
               <p>CONTACT: contact@music-encoding.org </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital: No previous source exists.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="linkingdata" type="div1">
            <head>Linking Data</head>
            <p>This chapter describes the use of elements in MEI for linking and referencing. This includes the elements, models, and attributes that are part of the 'MEI.ptrref' module. This module contains declarations, techniques and approaches to establish references within a single MEI document, or to link out from one MEI document to another or to other external sources. This chapter also addresses possibilities to link into an MEI document from external sources which makes MEI highly interoperable and serviceable in the context of Linked (Open) Data approaches.</p>
            <div xml:id="links" type="div2">
               <head>Links</head>
               <p>An element is a ‘link’ when it has an attribute whose value is a reference to the ID of one or more other elements (cross-reference). These link elements indicate an association between themselves (or one of their ancestors) and one or more other entities, either inside the same document or elsewhere. An association between two elements in the same document is said to be an ‘internal’ link, while an association that involves an entity outside the current document is called an ‘external’ link. However, either of the elements discussed in the following section can be used for either purpose.</p>
                <div xml:id="linkingDescribingRelationships" type="div3">
                    <head>General Relationships Between Elements</head>
                    <p>MEI offers several attributes in the <ident type="class">att.linking</ident> class for the description of basic relationships:</p>
                    <p>
                        <specList>
                            <specDesc key="att.linking"
                                atts="copyof sameas corresp next prev precedes follows synch"/>
                        </specList>
                    </p>
                    <p>The <ident type="class">att.alignment</ident> class contains an attribute for describing temporal relationships:</p>
                    <p>
                        <specList>
                            <specDesc key="att.alignment" atts="when"/>
                        </specList>
                    </p>
                    <p>The <ident type="class">att.dataPointing</ident> class provides an attribute for pointing from the header into the music content:</p>
                    <p>
                        <specList>
                            <specDesc key="att.dataPointing" atts="data"/>
                        </specList>
                    </p>
                    <p>To reference images, the <ident type="class">att.facsimile</ident> class provides an attribute for pointing to <gi scheme="MEI">surface</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">zone</gi> elements:</p>
                    <p>
                        <specList>
                            <specDesc key="att.facsimile" atts="facs"/>
                        </specList>
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>These attributes accommodate the encoding of linkages between the element carrying the attribute and one or more other elements. All of them use URIs to establish the connection. While the examples below illustrate relationships between musical events, the use of the aforementioned attributes is not restricted to musical events. On the contrary, these attributes can be used to capture information about relations between any elements.</p>
                    <p>Using the attributes above makes it possible to create relationships between events, which are often widely-spaced in both encoded order and time. The attributes allow a large number of connections, enhancing the informational content, and therefore the potential usefulness, of the encoding.</p>
                    <p>The <att>copyof</att> attribute points to an element of which the current element is a copy. It can be used to repeat a note, for example, without encoding the whole <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi> element again. The copy is a ‘deep’ one; that is, the <att>copyof</att> attribute copies all attributes and child elements which belong to the copied element, such as the <att>dur</att> and <att>oct</att> attributes of a copied <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi>. The value of the <att>copyof</att> attribute must be a URI, which usually refers to an element in the current document. The following example demonstrates use of the <att>copyof</att> attribute:</p>
                    <p>
                        <figure>
                            <head/>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example017.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    <p>In this example, the <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi> in the second measure has exactly the same characteristics as the <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi> in the first <gi scheme="MEI">measure</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Using <att>copyof</att> is not limited to copying events. The <att>copyof</att> attribute can also be used to copy an entire <gi scheme="MEI">measure</gi> or <gi scheme="MEI">staff</gi>. When there are many repeated features, the use of the <att>copyof</att> greatly reduces encoding effort. The image and the following encoding of the beginning of Schubert’s <hi rend="italic">Erlkönig</hi> illustrates the benefit of using the <att>copyof</att> attribute.</p>
                    <p>
                        <figure>
                            <head>First measure of Schubert’s Erlkönig</head>
                            <graphic url="../images/modules/analysis/schubert_erlkonig_op1_m1.png"/>
                        </figure>
                        <figure>
                            <head/>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example018.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    <p>This example can be reduced further by using <att>copyof</att> inside the initial tuplet to represent the repeated chords:</p>
                    <p>
                        <figure>
                            <head/>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example019.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    <p>While <att>copyof</att> signifies a duplicate copy of an element, the <att>sameas</att> indicates that the current element represents exactly the same entity as the one referenced in <att>sameas</att>. Use of <att>sameas</att> is used for describing the same entity from multiple perspectives, <abbr>e.g.</abbr>, the same event in two layers.</p>
                    <p>While <att>copyof</att> and <att>sameas</att> have defined semantics, the <att>corresp</att> may be used to create user-defined relationships between elements. The example below demonstrates the encoding of a relationship between the third note and the fermata, even though the fermata is not placed directly above the note.</p>
                    <p>
                        <figure>
                            <head/>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example020.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    <p>The <att>corresp</att> attribute only marks the correspondence between the current element and one or more other entities. To describe the nature of the correspondence, one must use <gi scheme="MEI">annot</gi>.</p>
                    <p>One possible usage of <att>corresp</att> is to link related editorial markup. Because of the hierarchical nature of XML it may be necessary to split related editorial markup into multiple elements. In the following example, <att>corresp</att> is used to encode the relationship between those elements.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head/>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="verovio code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/verovio/att-corresp.mei" parse="text"/></egXML>
                    </figure>
                    <p>A one-to-many relationship between the current element and the entities being referred to can be expressed by using a list of space-separated URIs in <att>corresp</att>.</p>
                    <p>The <att>next</att> and <att>prev</att> attributes point to elements which follow or precede the current element in some fashion other than that indicated by encoding order. The use of these attributes helps to avoid confusion in the sequence of events, for example, in voice leading across layers or staves, when the encoding reflects the physical arrangement of voices. In the second measure of the following example, the target of the next attribute occurs after the pointing element in time, but before it in encoding order:</p>
                    <p>
                        <figure>
                            <head>Bach Chorale, Ach Gott, vom Himmel sieh' darein, m. 6-7</head>
                            <graphic url="../images/modules/analysis/chor003_m6-7.png"/>
                        </figure>
                        <figure>
                            <head/>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example021.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    <p>The <att>next</att> and <att>prev</att> attributes may also be useful to clarify a sequence of entities which occurs across some form of interruption, in this case, notes before and after a new system or page beginning where there is no custos or direct in the source:</p>
                    <p>
                        <figure>
                            <head/>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example022.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    <p>The <att>synch</att> attribute points to an element that is synchronous with; that is, begins at the same moment in time, as the current element. It is useful when the encoding order differs from the order in which entities occur in time.</p>
                    <p>The <att>when</att> attribute may be used to indicate the point of occurrence of the feature bearing this attribute along a time line. Its value must be the ID of a <gi scheme="MEI">when</gi> element. For more detailed information regarding the use of <att>when</att>, please see <ptr target="#performances"/>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="linkFromMei" type="div2">
               <head>Linking from MEI</head>
               <p>This section describes techniques and approaches to establish references within a single MEI document, or to link out from one MEI document to another or to other external sources.</p>
                <div xml:id="ptrRef" type="div3">
                    <head>Pointers and References</head>
                    <p>The link elements discussed in this section are the <gi scheme="MEI">ptr</gi> and the <gi scheme="MEI">ref</gi> elements which are declared in the MEI.ptrref module.</p>
                    <p>
                        <specList>
                            <specDesc key="ptr"/>
                            <specDesc key="ref"/>
                        </specList>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The <gi scheme="MEI">ptr</gi> element is a traversible pointer to another location. It is an empty linking element that uses only attributes to describe its link destination. It cannot contain text or sub-elements to describe the referenced object. The next example shows the use of the <gi scheme="MEI">ptr</gi> element to target a certain identifier (here <abbr>e.g.</abbr>, a page number, or more precisely, page beginning elements, <gi scheme="MEI">pb</gi>, bearing these identifiers) from within a <gi scheme="MEI">list</gi> of item descriptions:
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <figure>
                            <head/>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example001.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The <gi scheme="MEI">ref</gi> element defines a traversible reference to another location. While <gi scheme="MEI">ptr</gi> cannot contain other markup, the <gi scheme="MEI">ref</gi> element can include text or sub-elements that further specify the link destination:
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <figure>
                            <head/>
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example002.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="ptrrefModule" type="div3">
                    <head>Specifying Link Elements</head>
                    <p>
                        In addition to the common linking attributes provided by the <ident type="class">att.linking</ident> class (see <ptr target="#linkingDescribingRelationships"/>), the <gi scheme="MEI">ptr</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">ref</gi> elements inherit another set of common attributes from the <ident type="class">att.pointing</ident> class (a more detailed explanation is provided below):
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <specList>
                            <specDesc key="att.pointing" atts="target targettype xlink:actuate xlink:show xlink:role"/>
                        </specList>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Furthermore, the <att>mimetype</att> attribute from the <ident type="class">att.internetMedia</ident> class is also available on <gi scheme="MEI">ptr</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">ref</gi> (a more detailed explanation is provided below):
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <specList>
                            <specDesc key="att.internetMedia" atts="mimetype"/>
                        </specList>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Additionally, the following attributes are also available on <gi scheme="MEI">ptr</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">ref</gi>:
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Via the <ident type="class">att.metadataPointing</ident> class:
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <specList>
                            <specDesc key="att.metadataPointing" atts="decls"/>
                        </specList>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Via the <ident type="class">att.classed</ident> class:
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <specList>
                            <specDesc key="att.classed" atts="class"/>
                        </specList>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Via the <ident type="class">att.responsibility</ident> class:
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <specList>
                            <specDesc key="att.responsibility" atts="resp"/>
                        </specList>
                    </p>
                    <div xml:id="ptrRefTarget" type="div4">
                        <head>Define the link element’s target (XPointer mechanism)</head>
                        <p>
                            The <att>target</att> attribute specifies the destination of a pointer or reference using a method standardized by the W3C consortium, known as the XPointer mechanism. The XPointer framework is described at <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xptr-framework/">http://www.w3.org/TR/xptr-framework/</ref>. This mechanism permits a range of complexity, from the very simple (a reference to the value of the target element’s <att>xml:id</att> attribute) to the more complex usage of a full URI with embedded XPointers:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head/>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example003.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head/>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example004.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head/>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example005.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head/>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example006.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head/>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example007.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            A <att>target</att> attribute is not required in order to mark the textual content as a cross-reference, as demonstrated in the example below; however, without this attribute the reference will not be resolvable.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head/>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example008.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="ptrRefTargettype" type="div4">
                        <head>Define the type of a link element’s target</head>
                        <p>
                            The <att>targettype</att> attribute allows the target resource to be characterized using any convenient classification scheme or typology. This is often useful when the target requires special processing, <abbr>e.g.</abbr>, for display purposes. The pointers in the examples below may be formatted differently, <abbr>e.g.</abbr>, the bibliographic citation may result in special typography while the pointer to the audio file may be used to embed an audio player:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head/>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example009.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head/>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example010.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="ptrRefMimetype" type="div4">
                        <head>Define the mimetype of a link element’s target</head>
                        <p>
                            The function of the <att>mimetype</att> attribute is similar to that of <att>targettype</att> in that they both allow classification of the destination. Unlike <att>targettype</att>, however, <att>mimetype</att> explicitly defines the destination type using a standard taxonomy. Its value should be a valid MIME (Multimedia Internet Mail Extension) type as defined by the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) in RFC 2046, available at <ref target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2046.txt">http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2046.txt</ref>. The following are all valid mimetype values:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head/>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example011.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            As shown above, the <gi scheme="MEI">ptr</gi> element can be used to ‘point to’ a digital image (<code>target="my.png"</code>). However, when the intention is to <hi rend="italic">display</hi> a digital image as part of the rendering of an MEI file, the <gi scheme="MEI">graphic</gi> element provides a convenient and recommended alternative:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head/>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example012.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            The <att>mimetype</att> attribute is particularly useful for documenting the nature of the destination when the value of <att>target</att> does not provide a filename extension or when the destination is a non-standard file type:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head/>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example013.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="ptrRefXlinkActuateShow" type="div4">
                        <head>Determine the link element’s behaviour</head>
                        <p>
                            The <att>xlink:actuate</att> and <att>xlink:show</att> attributes are used in conjunction to determine the link’s behavior.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            The <att>xlink:actuate</att> attribute defines whether the resolution of a link occurs automatically or must be requested by the user.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            The following values are allowed for the <att>xlink:actuate</att> attribute:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <list type="gloss">
                                <label>‘onLoad’</label>
                                <item>load the target resource(s) immediately</item>
                                <label>‘onRequest’</label>
                                <item>load the target resource(s) upon user request, <abbr>e.g.</abbr>, after a mouse click</item>
                                <label>‘none’</label>
                                <item>do not permit loading of the target resource(s); no other markup is provided to determine appropriate behavior</item>
                                <label>‘other’</label>
                                <item>behavior other than permitted by the other values of this attribute; application should look for other markup to determine appropriate behavior</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            The value <val>none</val> may be used to indicate that the link is un-traversable and no other markup is provided to determine appropriate behavior; it may or may not render the link invisible to the user. When the value of <att>xlink:actuate</att> is <val>other</val>, an application must base a determination of appropriate behavior on factors other than the value of <att>xlink:actuate</att>.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            The <att>xlink:show</att> attribute defines how a remote resource is to be rendered. The following values are permitted:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <list type="gloss">
                                <label>‘new’</label>
                                <item>target of the link appears in a new window</item>
                                <label>‘replace’</label>
                                <item>target of the link replaces the current resource in the same window</item>
                                <label>‘embed’</label>
                                <item>the content of the target appears at the point of the link</item>
                                <label>‘none’</label>
                                <item>do not permit traversal to the target resource(s); no other markup is provided to determine appropriate behavior</item>
                                <label>‘other’</label>
                                <item>behavior other than permitted by the other values of this attribute; application should look for other markup to determine appropriate behavior</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            The value <val>none</val> may be used to indicate a link that is not displayed or is not displayable and no other markup is provided to determine appropriate behavior. When the value of <att>xlink:show</att> is <val>other</val>, an application must base a determination of appropriate behavior on factors other than the value of <att>xlink:show</att>.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            The following example illustrates a pointer that results in the automatic creation of a new window with the content of the target loaded in it:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head/>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example014.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="ptrRefXlinkRole" type="div4">
                        <head>Determine the link element’s role</head>
                        <p>
                            The <att>xlink:role</att> attribute describes the meaning of resources within the context of a link. It is used to label or describe a link or resource in a human- and machine-readable fashion. The value of <att>xlink:role</att> must be an absolute URI (Uniform Resource Identifier) reference as defined by the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) in RFC 3986, available at <ref target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3986">http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3986</ref>. The URI reference identifies a resource that describes the intended property. When no value is supplied, no particular role value is to be inferred.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head/>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example015.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head/>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="code" xml:space="preserve"><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../examples/linkalign/linkalign-example016.txt" parse="text"/></egXML>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            In the preceding examples, the value of the <att>xlink:role</att> attribute may be used to specify the value of the link target’s role.
                        </p>
                    </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="linkAlign" type="div2">
               <head>Linking and Alignment</head>
               <p>The linkAlign module has been deprecated in MEI v3.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
