<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  © 2010 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs Unported License, 
  Version 3.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/.
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="analysis" n="0">
    <head>Analytical Information</head>
    <p>This chapter describes the use of attributes for describing several analytical issues, e.g.
        in a harmonic analysis. The phrase "musical analysis" embraces a large number of diverse
        activities, so this chapter of the guidelines recommend the use of elements and attributes
        offered in MEI. The module contains attributes indicating relations between <gi>notes</gi>,
            <gi>chords</gi>, intervals and melodies in an analytical context. To describe analytical
        information within a <gi>note</gi> or other elements, the model offers a various range of
        attributes which can be used for several analytical interpretations. That makes available
        individual application of users and offers different results, depending on the purpose of an
        analysis. The guidelines recommend commonly accepted realizations and encodings of different
        practices in analysis, such as a "Functional analysis", "Schenkerian analysis" or other
        methods. For further information of musical analysis, please read the Grove Music Online,
        article: analysis, May 2012 <ref
            target="http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/subscriber/article/grove/music/41862pg1#S41862.1"
        /></p>
    <div type="div2" xml:id="analysisOverview">
        <head>Overview of the analysis Module</head>
        <p>The analysis module contains common analytical attributes but no further elements.</p>
        <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:</p>
        <div type="div3" xml:id="analysisElements">
            <head>Elements</head>
            <p>No elements are defined in this module.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="div3" xml:id="analysisAttributeClasses">
            <head>Attribute Classes</head>
            <p>The following attribute classes are defined in this module.</p>
            <p>
                <specList>
                    <specDesc key="att.common.anl"/>
                    <specDesc key="att.harmonicfunction"/>
                    <specDesc key="att.intervalharmonic"/>
                    <specDesc key="att.intervallicdesc"/>
                    <specDesc key="att.melodicfunction"/>
                    <specDesc key="att.pitchclass"/>
                    <specDesc key="att.solfa"/>
                </specList>
            </p>
            <div type="div3">
                <head>Describing relationships between elements</head>
                <p>The relationships between elements make the structure of a musical work and the
                    attributes ensure a closed network of these relations. The following paragraph
                    describes the attributes, as part of the analysis module, which are particularly
                    used for linking elements.</p>
                <p>In MEI, the so called common analytical attributes provide the opportunity to
                    encode certain issues in a generic fashion. The analysis module offers six
                    optional attributes beside the basic parameters of the <ref target="#shared"
                        >Shared Module</ref> in the att.common.anl class. These are the
                        <att>copyof</att>, <att>sameas</att>, <att>next</att>, <att>corresp</att>
                    <att>prev</att> and <att>synch</att>. These attributes work as a special tool to
                    refer to several elements. All of them act with xml:id´s and URI´s to link to
                    each other. In the context of a Formal analysis for instance, the attributes
                    presented here, might be useful to get information about the structure of a
                    musical work. As well, another method needing several data about coherence
                    within a musical work might be the Transformational Theory, focussing the
                    relationships between musical objects.</p>
                <p>The <att>copyof</att> attribute points to an element of which the current element
                    is a copy. It is used to repeat e.g. a note without encoding the whole
                        <gi>note</gi> element again (reduplication). The <att>copyof</att> copies
                    any other attributes, which belong to the note, like the <att>dur</att>,
                        <att>oct</att> and so on. By definition, the value of the
                    <att>copyof</att>-attribute must be an URI, which refers to a previous
                        <gi>note</gi>. The following example demonstrates the <att>copyof</att>
                    within a two-measure level.<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <measure n="1">
                            <staff n="1">
                                <layer>
                                    <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="4" xml:id="note1"/>
                                </layer>
                            </staff>
                        </measure>
                        <measure n="2">
                            <staff n="1">
                                <layer>
                                    <note copyOf="#note1"/>
                                </layer>
                            </staff>
                        </measure>
                    </egXML> In the small example the <gi>note</gi> of the second measure would have
                    exactly the same characteristics as the <gi>note</gi> in the first
                        <gi>measure</gi>. Certainly the <att>copyof</att> can also be used to copy a
                    whole <gi>staff</gi> or <gi>measure</gi>. In some cases the use of the
                        <att>copyof</att> facilitates the effort in a vastly way. The image and the
                    following encoding of the beginning of Schuberts "Erlkönig" illustrates the
                    benefit of using the <att>copyof</att> without loosing musical content. <figure>
                        <head>First measure of Schuberts Erlkönig</head>
                        <figDesc/>
                        <graphic url=""/>
                    </figure><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <measure>
                            <staff n="1">
                                <layer>
                                    <mRest/>
                                </layer>
                            </staff>
                            <staff n="2">
                                <layer>
                                    <tuplet xml:id="tuplet1" num="3" num.visible="true">
                                        <chord dur="8">
                                            <note pname="g" oct="3"/>
                                            <note pname="g" oct="4"/>
                                        </chord>
                                    </tuplet>
                                    <tuplet xml:id="tuplet2" copyof="#tuplet1">
                                        <chord/>
                                    </tuplet>
                                    <tuplet xml:id="tuplet3" copyof="#tuplet1">
                                        <chord/>
                                    </tuplet>
                                    <tuplet xml:id="tuplet4" copyof="#tuplet1">
                                        <chord/>
                                    </tuplet>
                                </layer>
                            </staff>
                            <staff n="3">
                                <layer>
                                    <mRest/>
                                </layer>
                            </staff>
                        </measure></egXML>
                </p>
                <p> Opposed to this the <att>sameas</att>is not a literal copy of an element, but
                    the same as the current element. The element containing the <att>sameas</att>
                    can have additional attributes and is commonly used for describing the same
                    thing in two perspectives, e.g. the same event in two layers as the following
                    example shows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <measure>
                            <staff n="1">
                                <layer n="1">
                                    <note pname="a" oct="4" dur="2" stem.dir="up" xml:id="note1"/>
                                    <layer n="2">
                                        <note xml:id="456" sameas="#note1" stem.dir="down"/>
                                    </layer>
                                </layer>
                            </staff>
                        </measure>
                    </egXML> The same event has different stem directions but they share the same
                    headshape. The <att>sameas</att>is allowed on a huge number of elements and it
                    is to be used like the <att>copyOf</att> with an URI, which refers to another
                    element. The case shown in the example occurs often in chorales. The image
                    illustrates the function of <att>sameas</att> by an extract of a Bach-Chorale,
                    where the first and the second voice are sharing one notehead. <figure>
                        <head>Bach Chorale</head>
                        <figDesc/>
                        <graphic url=""/>
                    </figure> It is recommended to use the <att>sameas</att> to avoid duplication of
                    an encoded note, chord or other element.</p>
                <p>The <att>corresp</att>is used to point to other elements, which are defined
                    elsewhere in the document. That might be be a large number of elements in a
                    generic fashion. The <att>corresp</att> offers the opportunity to encode an
                    element with its own characteristics but still corresponding to another element.
                    The <att>corresp</att> is used to make a semantic relation beween elements, even
                    if a graphic pictures something different. The use of <att>corresp</att> is
                    allowed on many elements, working with ID´s/URI´s, as suggested in the following
                        example.<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <measure n="1" right="end">
                            <staff n="1">
                                <layer n="1">
                                    <note pname="c" oct="4" dur="4" xml:id="note1"/>
                                    <note pname="d" oct="4" dur="4" xml:id="note2"/>
                                    <note pname="e" oct="4" dur="2" xml:id="note3"/>
                                </layer>
                            </staff>
                            <fermata place="above" tstamp="4.75" corresp="#note3"/>
                        </measure>
                    </egXML> The example demonstrates the relationship between note3 and the
                    fermata, although the fermata is not placed directly above the note. It is also
                    possible to indicate more than one URI separated by whitespace.</p>
                <p>The <att>prev</att> and the <att>next</att> point to previous or respectively
                    next events in a user-defined collection. The URI is used to mark the preceding
                    or following event, which can be a note, chord, rest or several elements. It
                    enables to link abreast to events directly and avoids confusion in the sequence
                    of events. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <measure n="1">
                            <staff n="1">
                                <layer>
                                    <note pname="f" oct="4" dur="4" stem.dir="up" xml:id="m1s1e1"
                                        next="m1s1e2"/>
                                    <sb/>
                                    <pb/>
                                    <note pname="b" oct="3" dur="8" stem.dir="up" xml:id="m1s1e2"
                                        prev="m1s1e1" next="m1s1e3"/>
                                    <note pname="c" oct="4" dur="8" stem.dir="up" xml:id="m1s1e3"
                                        prev="m1s1e2"/>
                                </layer>
                            </staff>
                        </measure>
                    </egXML> It is useful to encode notes with the <att>next</att> before a
                        <gi>sb</gi> or <gi>pb</gi> for example. The <att>prev</att> enables to get
                    an impression which events occured before.</p>
                <p> The <att>synch</att> points to an element that is synchronous to the current
                    element. This attribute can be used to describe, that at least two events happen
                    at the same time. The <att>synch</att> marks the sound of a pitch in a first
                    layer, while the second layer has a rest at the same time. It also can be used
                    to link the notes of a score to the notes of a solo part, to facilitate the
                    reading of content, that belongs together. The following encoded feature is a
                    small example for using the <att>synch</att> within one measure, combining two
                    notes and one rest, which occur on the same time and sound simultanously. <egXML
                        xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <measure>
                            <staff n="1">
                                <layer>
                                    <note pname="d" oct="5" dur="2" xml:id="note1"/>
                                </layer>
                            </staff>
                            <staff n="2">
                                <layer>
                                    <rest dur="2" synch="note1 note2" xml:id="rest1"/>
                                </layer>
                            </staff>
                            <staff n="3">
                                <layer>
                                    <note pname="b" oct="4" dur="2" xml:id="note2"
                                        synch="#rest1 #note1"/>
                                </layer>
                            </staff>
                        </measure>
                    </egXML>
                </p>
                <p>The described attributes have similar intentions, but with different results.
                    Their intention is to provide the opportunity to refer to other events by the
                    use of ID´s and URI´s. Using these attributes offer the possibility to create a
                    relationship between different events in diverse levels and to facilitate
                    encoding of several events which are related. The result depends on the
                    attributes, which have to be used for the described tasks. The attributes allow
                    a vast number of connecting elements within a file, which can enhance the
                    structure of the encoding. For the analytical point of view, it can be quite
                    beneficial to know which notes for example correspond to which chord, or which
                    note follows on the current event perhaps for indicating it as a passing
                    note.</p>
                <div type="div3">
                    <head>Harmonic function</head>
                    <p>The current schema allows several attributes within certain elements. This
                        paragraph is intended to make recommendations how to use the
                            <att>hfunc</att> and the <att>mfunc</att>. For a future version of the
                        MEI release, a reconfiguration of these attributes is planned.</p>
                    <p>This part of the chapter addresses the explanation of the harmonical context
                        of a note. Actually the <att>hfunc</att>is only permitted within the
                            <gi>note</gi>, <gi>uneume</gi> and <gi>ineume</gi>. The various
                        opportunities of using the <att>hfunc</att> depends on the musical context
                        and the intention of the encoder. There are many techniques to analyze
                        music. In the european tradition, the functional harmony is the most common
                        practice for analyzing musical works. The term derives from Hugo Riemann
                        with roots back to Jean-Philippe Rameau. Basic parameters are the labels of
                        functions which any tone of a seven-tone scale can have. For example the
                        tonic and the common abbreviation T. Functional harmony is a basic
                        discipline in the western world, though different labels are used. In the US
                        e.g. the <soCalled>Schenkerian analysis</soCalled> is a more common practice
                        than in Europe. The basic component of this type of analysis is the harmonic
                        scale degree ("Stufe") and is represented by roman numerals. For further
                        information about methods and techniques in analysis please read the New
                        Grove Online, article: analysis, §I: General. Moreover, Forte, A. (1959)
                        "Schenker´s Conception of Musical Structure." Journal of Music Theory
                        3(1):1-30 and "SchenkerGuide: A brief Handbook and a website for Schenkerian
                        Analysis" - by Tom Pankhurst. In: Music analysis vol. 28 (2009), p. 145-151 </p>
                    <p>For describing the harmonic function of a note the <att>hfunc</att> provides
                        an open value, because it allows to describe harmonic function in any
                        convenient typology. Using the <att>hfunc</att>offers several options for
                        the encoder, depending on his intention, but it is recommended to use the
                            <att>hfunc</att>in a consistent way within a file. The first example
                        demonstrates the <att>hfunc</att> within a <gi>note</gi>. <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <measure>
                                <staff n="1">
                                    <layer n="1">
                                        <note pname="a" oct="4" dur="8"/>
                                    </layer>
                                    <layer n="2">
                                        <note pname="f" accid="s" oct="4" dur="8"/>
                                    </layer>
                                </staff>
                                <staff n="2">
                                    <layer n="2">
                                        <note pname="d" oct="4" dur="8" hfunc="keynote"/>
                                    </layer>
                                </staff>
                            </measure>
                        </egXML> The <gi>note</gi> element of the second staff contains some
                        attributes describing the pitchname, note value and so on. In the context of
                        the basic key of this chorale, which is described in the previous
                            <gi>scoreDef</gi>, and the other notes occurring in the first staff, it
                        is possible to determine the function of the bass note using the
                            <att>hfunc</att>. </p>
                    <p>Chord labels, like "Cm7", or indications of harmonic functionality like "ii7"
                        belong in <gi>harm</gi>, so for describing harmonic function of chords, it
                        is recommended to use the <gi>harm</gi>element.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="div3">
                    <head>Interval harmonic</head>
                    <p> The <att>inth</att> is used to encode the harmonic interval between the
                        current note and other pitches occuring at the same time for example within
                        a chord or within different staffs and layers on the same timestamp. It is
                        determined to encode numbers for describing halfsteps above the root. <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <measure>
                                <staff>
                                    <layer n="1">
                                        <note xml:id="e1" pname="c" oct="4" dur="4" inth="0"/>
                                    </layer>
                                    <layer n="2">
                                        <note xml:id="e2" pname="e" oct="4" dur="4" inth="3"/>
                                    </layer>
                                </staff>
                                <staff n="2">
                                    <layer n="3">
                                        <note xml:id="e3" pname="g" oct="4" dur="4" inth="5"/>
                                    </layer>
                                </staff>
                            </measure>
                        </egXML> By using the <att>inth</att>the encoding gives detailed information
                        about every note and its function in a relation to the other occuring notes
                        and hence about the harmonic of the musical work. An interval is always the
                        combination of two notes and can be described in a vertical or horizontal
                        way. To describe the horizontal way of intervals between notes, it is
                        recommended to use the <att>intm</att>, which is explained in the next
                        paragraph.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="div3">
                    <head>Interval description</head>
                    <p> The<att>intm</att>is used to encode the melodic interval coming from the
                        previous pitch using a decimal number or the Parson´s Code (d/u/s). The
                        attribute is only permitted on the <gi>note</gi> and the <gi>uneueme</gi>.
                        The decimal numbers allow the description of the interval in a very precise
                        way, so that is also possible to encode minute intervals. At first an
                        example which shows a simple melody with intervals represented by numbers
                        (halfsteps). <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <measure>
                                <staff>
                                    <layer>
                                        <note pname="c" oct="4" dur="4"/>
                                        <note pname="d" oct="4" dur="4" intm="1"/>
                                        <note pname="d" oct="5" dur="4" intm="8"/>
                                    </layer>
                                </staff>
                            </measure>
                        </egXML> In a diatonic melodoy it is quite sufficient to use the Parsons
                        Code. The shortcuts are intended to give the direction of the notes/ melody
                        (up, down or the same). For more information about the Parsons Code please
                        read the "The Directory of Tunes and MusicalThemes" by Denys Parsons (2002).
                        The next example shows the encoded beginning of a melody including the
                        Parsons Code.<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <measure n="1">
                                <staff n="1">
                                    <layer>
                                        <note pname="c" oct="4" dur="4"/>
                                        <note pname="d" oct="4" dur="4" intm="u"/>
                                        <note pname="e" oct="4" dur="4" intm="u"/>
                                        <note pname="f" oct="4" dur="4" intm="u"/>
                                        <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="2" intm="u"/>
                                        <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="2" intm="s"/>
                                        <note pname="f" oct="4" dur="4" intm="d"/>
                                    </layer>
                                </staff>
                            </measure>
                        </egXML> The use of the The Parsons Code is helpful to find songs and
                        musical works, so in an analytical way, the use of the <att>intm</att> could
                        be beneficial to analize the relation between successive notes and may help
                        to identify motifs. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="div3">
                    <head>Melodic function</head>
                    <p>The <att>mfunc</att> describes melodic function in any convenient typology.
                        The values of this attribute could be a name or a number. However, the
                            <att>mfunc</att> should be used for describing passing notes or passing
                        chords for a better distinction and assignment of notes. Currently the
                            <att>mfunc</att> is allowed on notes and chords. The following example
                        illustrates the <att>mfunc</att> on a chord and on a note, indicating the
                        first chord as a tonic, the following note as a passing note and the second
                        chord as a dominant. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <measure n="2">
                                <staff n="1">
                                    <layer>
                                        <chord dur="4" stem.dir="up" xml:id="chord1"
                                            mfunc="start_as_I">
                                            <note pname="f" oct="4" dur="4" xml:id="m2e1"/>
                                            <note pname="a" oct="4" dur="4" xml:id="m2e2"/>
                                            <note pname="c" oct="5" dur="4" xml:id="m2e3"/>
                                        </chord>
                                        <note pname="b" oct="4" dur="4" stem.dir="down"
                                            xml:id="m2e4" accid="f" mfunc="passing-note"/>
                                    </layer>
                                </staff>
                                <staff n="2">
                                    <layer>
                                        <chord dur="4" stem.dir="up" xml:id="chord2"
                                            mfunc="leads_to_I">
                                            <note pname="c" oct="4" dur="4" xml:id="m2e5"/>
                                            <note pname="e" oct="4" dur="4" xml:id="m2e6"/>
                                            <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="4" xml:id="m2e7"/>
                                        </chord>
                                    </layer>
                                </staff>
                            </measure>
                        </egXML> Even the description of motifs is possible, e.g. if some sequenced
                        notes are part of a motif, all about in the combination with the
                            <att>intm</att>. The attribute is still allowed on a chord so another
                        example shows a part of an encoding including a chord, which might be
                        identified as the "Tristan-chord". <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <measure n="5">
                                <staff n="1">
                                    <layer>
                                        <chord n="1" mfunc="Tristan_chord">
                                            <note pname="f" oct="4" dur="2" dots="1"/>
                                            <note pname="b" oct="4" dur="2" dots="1"/>
                                            <note pname="d" accid="s" oct="3" dur="2" dots="1"/>
                                            <note pname="g" accid="s" dur="2" dots="1"/>
                                        </chord>
                                    </layer>
                                </staff>
                            </measure></egXML></p>
                </div>
                <div type="div3">
                    <head>Pitch class</head>
                    <p>The <att>pclass</att> attribute is used to encode information about the pitch
                        class. The value must be an integer less than or equal to 11. It is only
                        allowed on the <gi>note</gi> element. Background of this attribute is the
                        "musical set theory" eloborated first by Howard Hanson and Allen Forte as a
                        new method for organizing tones at the beginning of the 20th. It provides a
                        concept for categorizing musical objects (notes) and describing their
                        relationships. It is a kind of grouping and combining, mostly developed in
                        connection with atonal music. But the concepts of set theory are general and
                        can be applied also to tonal music. A pitch class means the summary of every
                        pitch with specific characteristics that means a pitch class set is an
                        unordered collection of pitches, e.g. every pitches with the name c. A pitch
                        class may contain a large number of pitches, because the notation, as
                        different octaves and enharmonical quotation of pitch, makes no difference.
                        The notes C, E, and G would be 0, 4 and 7 in pitch classes for example. For
                        further information find a brief introduction to the Pitch-Class Set
                        analysis on <ref
                            target="http://www.mta.ca/faculty/arts-letters/music/pc-set_project/pc-set_new/pages/introduction/toc.html"
                        />. Otherwise please read the "Analyzing Atonal Music: Pitch Class Set
                        Theory and its contexts" by Michael Schuijler (2008). <!-- Cohen, Allen Laurence (2004) Howard Hanson in Theory and Practice-->
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <note pname="d" oct="4" dur="4" pclass="2"/>
                            <note pname="d" oct="5" dur="2" pclass="2"/>
                            <note pname="c" accid="ss" dur="4" pclass="2"/>
                            <note pname="e" accid="ff" dur="1" pclass="2"/>
                        </egXML> The example illustrates four different notes, but all are part of
                        the same pitch class. A collection of examples can be found on <ref
                            target="http://kern.ccarh.org/"/></p>
                </div>
                <div type="div3">
                    <head>Solfa</head>
                    <p>The solmization is a system to associate a syllable to each note of a musical
                        scale. There are various forms of solmization all over the world and which
                        developed over the years. In Europe and North America, the solfège is the
                        most common practice. The seven syllables for a major scale are called do,
                        re, mi, fa, so, la and ti. The attribute is only allowed on <gi>note</gi>
                        and <gi>uneme</gi> with an open value, that ensures the opportunity to
                        encode different values for several typs of solmization. <egXML
                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <measure>
                                <staff n="1">
                                    <layer>
                                        <note pname="c" oct="4" dur="4" psolfa="do"/>
                                        <note pname="d" oct="4" dur="4" psolfa="re"/>
                                        <note pname="e" oct="4" dur="4" psolfa="mi"/>
                                        <note pname="f" oct="4" dur="4" psolfa="fa"/>
                                    </layer>
                                </staff>
                            </measure>
                        </egXML>The <att>psolfa</att> might be particularly helpful for describing
                        and analyzing musical works from the Middle Age.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
        <div type="div3" xml:id="analysisModelClasses">
            <head>Model Classes</head>
            <p>No model classes are defined in this module.</p>
        </div>
    </div>

</div>
