<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
  © 2015 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI).
  Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
  not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License
  at http://opensource.org/licenses/ECL-2.0.
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
  OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language
  governing permissions and limitations under the License.
  
  This is a derivative work based on earlier versions of the schema © 2001-2006 Perry Roland
  and the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia; licensed under the Educational
  Community License version 1.0.
  
  CONTACT: info@music-encoding.org
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="cmn" n="0">
  <head>Common Music Notation</head>
  <p>The module described in this chapter offers the means to describe music in so-called
      <soCalled>Common Music Notation</soCalled> (<term>CMN</term>, sometimes referred to as
      <soCalled>Common Western Music Notation</soCalled>). For this purpose, it provides a number of
    special elements and adds several attribute classes to elements from the <ref target="#shared"
      >Shared</ref> module.</p>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="cmnBasics">
    <head>Basic Elements of CMN</head>
    <p>This section describes the use of basic features of MEI important for encoding CMN material.
      Most of the elements discussed here are defined in chapter <ptr target="#shared"/> of these
      Guidelines, but are used in music from the CMN repertoire in specialized ways.</p>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnMeasures">
      <head>The Role of the Measure Element</head>
      <p>Arguably, the most important element of the CMN module is the <gi scheme="MEI">measure</gi>
        element. It is used as a structural unit inside <gi scheme="MEI">section</gi> elements and
        acts as a container for <soCalled>events</soCalled> from the <ident type="class"
          >model.eventLike</ident> class, such as notes, chords and rests as well as
          <soCalled>control events</soCalled> from the <ident type="class"
          >model.controleventLike</ident> class, such as slurs and indications of dynamics.</p>
      <p>The following example demonstrates the use of the <gi scheme="MEI">measure</gi>
        element:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<section>
  <measure n="1">
    <staff n="1">
      <layer>
        <chord dur="1">
          <note pname="c" oct="5"/>
          <note pname="g" oct="4"/>
          <note pname="e" oct="4"/>
        </chord>
      </layer>
    </staff>
    <staff n="2">
      <layer>
        <note pname="c" oct="3" dur="1"/>
      </layer>
    </staff>
  </measure>
</section>
      </egXML>

      <p>A <gi scheme="MEI">measure</gi> slices the flow of a score or part into chunks that
        normally comply with a duration determined by the meter defined within a preceding <gi
          scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi> or <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> element. Each staff in the
        source material is represented by a <gi scheme="MEI">staff</gi> element. As the order of the
        staff elements in the file does not have to reflect their order in the original document, to
        eliminate confusion they should always refer to a <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> element,
        using either an <att>n</att> or <att>def</att> attribute. Whereas the <att>def</att>
        attribute uses the <term>xs:anyURI</term> datatype, the <att>n</att> value refers to the
        closest preceding <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> or <gi scheme="MEI">layerDef</gi> with the
        same value in its <att>n</att> attribute.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<staffDef xml:id="cmn_staffDef1" n="3"/>
<!-- later in the file: -->
<staff def="#cmn_staffDef1">
  <!-- @def refers to staffDef with this identifier -->
  <!-- staff content -->
</staff>
<!-- or: -->
<staff n="3">
  <!-- @n refers to staffDef with this numeric label -->
  <!-- staff content -->
</staff>
      </egXML>

      <p>Each <gi scheme="MEI">staff</gi> may hold a number of <gi scheme="MEI">layer</gi> elements
        to reflect multiple <soCalled>voices</soCalled>. Just as with <gi scheme="MEI">staff</gi>,
        the order of the <gi scheme="MEI">layer</gi> elements in the file does not have to reflect
        their original order in the document, so they also possess <att>n</att> and <att>def</att>
        attributes for association with the appropriate layer definition.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<staffDef xml:id="cmn_staffDef1" n="3">
  <layerDef xml:id="cmn_layerDef1" n="1"/>
</staffDef>
<!-- later in the file: -->
<staff def="#cmn_staffDef1">
  <layer def="#cmn_layerDef1">
    <!-- layer content -->
  </layer>
</staff>
<!-- OR: -->
<staff n="3">
  <layer n="1">
    <!-- layer content -->
  </layer>
</staff>
      </egXML>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnDefs">
      <head>Defining Score Parameters for CMN</head>
      <p>When encoding a score in CMN, MEI relies on the following elements from the <ref
          target="#shared">Shared</ref> module:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="scoreDef"/>
          <specDesc key="staffGrp"/>
          <specDesc key="staffDef"/>
          <specDesc key="layerDef"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>A <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi> element is used to specify the common parameters of a
        score, e.g., key and meter. The most important attributes for this purpose are:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="att.meterSigDefault.log" atts="meter.count meter.unit"/>
          <specDesc key="att.meterSigDefault.vis" atts="meter.sym"/>
          <specDesc key="att.keySigDefault.log" atts="key.pname key.accid key.mode key.sig"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The following example describes a score in common time with 3 flats:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<scoreDef meter.count="4" meter.unit="4" meter.sym="common" key.sig="3f"/>
      </egXML>

      <p>Other attributes allow the description of default page and system margins and fonts for
        text and music:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="scoreDef"
            atts="page.width page.height page.leftmar page.topmar
            page.rightmar page.bottommar system.leftmar system.topmar system.rightmar
            text.name text.fam text.size music.name music.size lyric.name lyric.fam
            lyric.size"
          />
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>There are other attributes that allow the specification of many further details of a score.
        These are available from the element definitions accessible at <gi scheme="MEI"
          >scoreDef</gi>, <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi>, <gi scheme="MEI">staffGrp</gi> and <gi
          scheme="MEI">layerDef</gi>.</p>

      <p>When content is provided for <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi>, it must contain a <gi
          scheme="MEI">staffGrp</gi> element. This element is used to gather individual staves and
        other staff groups. This is useful for collecting instrumental or vocal groups in a large
        score, such as woodwinds, brasses, etc., and for assigning a shared label to the group,
        using the <att>label</att> and <att>label.abbr</att> attributes. The <gi scheme="MEI"
          >staffGrp</gi> element is also used for the two staves of a grand staff. The
          <att>barthru</att> attribute on <gi scheme="MEI">staffGrp</gi> allows one to specify
        whether barlines are drawn across the space between staves of that group or only on the
        staves themselves.</p>
      <p>A <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> element is used to describe an individual staff of a <gi
          scheme="MEI">score</gi> or performer <gi scheme="MEI">part</gi>. It bears most of the
        attributes described above, including <att>label</att> and <att>label.abbr</att> for
        providing staff labels for the first and subsequent pages.</p>
      <p>Every <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> must have an <att>n</att> attribute with an integer as
        its value. The first occurence of a <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> with a given number must
        also indicate the number of staff lines via the <att>lines</att> attribute.</p>
      <p>The order of <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> elements within <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi>
        follows the order of staves in the source document or planned rendering. The individual <gi
          scheme="MEI">staff</gi> elements within a <gi scheme="MEI">measure</gi> refer to these <gi
          scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> declarations using their own <att>n</att> attribute values.
        Therefore, the encoding order of staves within a measure does not have to mimic the order of
        the <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> elements with <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi>.</p>
      <p>In addition to the parameters inherited from <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi>, the following
        attributes are important for <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> elements:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="att.cleffing.log" atts="clef.line clef.shape clef.dis clef.dis.place"/>
        </specList>
      </p>

      <p>A staff with a tenor clef is encoded as in the following example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<staffDef clef.shape="G" clef.line="2" clef.dis="8" clef.dis.place="below"/>
      </egXML>

      <p>In the case of transposing instruments, the key-related attributes described above may be
        used to override the written key expressed in the <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi> element. As
        a basic principle, MEI always captures written pitches, so the <att>trans.diat</att> and
          <att>trans.semi</att> attributes may be used to indicate the number of diatonic steps and
        semitones to calculate sounded pitch from written pitch. The piccolo and E♭ clarinet staves
        in the example below utilize these attributes:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<scoreDef meter.count="6" meter.unit="8">
  <staffGrp>
    <!-- Piccolo sounds 12 semitones higher than written (and encoded in MEI). -->
    <staffDef n="1" xml:id="cmn.P1" label="Piccolo" label.abbr="Picc." lines="5" clef.line="2" clef.shape="G" key.sig="4f" key.mode="major" trans.semi="12" trans.diat="0"/>
    <staffDef n="2" xml:id="cmn.P2" label="Flute" label.abbr="Fl." lines="5" clef.line="2" clef.shape="G" key.sig="4f" key.mode="major"/>
    <staffDef n="3" xml:id="cmn.P3" label="Oboe" label.abbr="Ob." lines="5" clef.line="2" clef.shape="G" key.sig="4f" key.mode="major"/>
    <staffDef n="4" xml:id="cmn.P4" label="Bassoon" label.abbr="Bsn." lines="5" clef.line="4" clef.shape="F" key.sig="4f" key.mode="major"/>
    <!-- Clarinet sounds a minor third (two diatonic steps or three semitones) higher than written.  -->
    <staffDef n="5" xml:id="cmn.P5" label="Clarinet in E♭" label.abbr="E♭ Cl." lines="5" clef.line="2" clef.shape="G" key.sig="1f" key.mode="major" trans.semi="3" trans.diat="2"/>
  </staffGrp>
</scoreDef>
      </egXML>

      <p>There are a number of additional elements that can be used as children of <gi scheme="MEI"
          >staffDef</gi> in order to describe additional features of the staff, such as the color of
        a clef or a key signature added in a different hand. These elements include:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="clef"/>
          <specDesc key="clefGrp"/>
          <specDesc key="keySig"/>
          <specDesc key="keyAccid"/>
          <specDesc key="label"/>
          <specDesc key="meterSig"/>
          <specDesc key="meterSigGrp"/>
        </specList>
      </p>

      <p>With the exception of <gi scheme="MEI">label</gi>, these elements may also occur within the
        flow of musical events captured in a <gi scheme="MEI">layer</gi>, since they are members of
          <ident type="class">model.eventLike</ident>. In the layer context they function as
        milestones and affect all following content assigned to the layer (even in subsequent
        measures) until their information is again overridden either by the same element bearing
        different information or a <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> or <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi>.
        In this context, it is also possible to combine them with the elements described in chapters
          <ptr target="#critApp"/> and <ptr target="#editTrans"/> of these Guidelines.</p>
      <p>Such flexibility as this may require close inspection of an encoding to retrieve the
        correct definitions for a given staff. As a general rule, the closest preceding and most
        specific element provides this information: For example, a <gi scheme="MEI">keySig</gi> in
        the preceding measure is more relevant than a <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> at the
        beginning of the section, which is more relevant than a <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi> at
        the beginning of the score. However, a section-specific <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi> that
        provides only information about the meter does not override the more specific information
        about key signature gathered from a <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> for a transposing
        instrument.</p>
      <p>Every <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> may contain a number of <gi scheme="MEI">layerDef</gi>
        elements, which may be used to establish default values for the distinct layers sharing one
        staff. MEI does not use the term <soCalled>voice</soCalled> to describe these
          <soCalled>musical threads</soCalled> because that term implies continuity across measure
        boundaries. Given the sometimes arbitrary relationships between these threads from measure
        to measure as well as across staves, MEI uses the more neutral term
          <soCalled>layer</soCalled>.</p>
      <!-- TODO: Address voice-leading here -->
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnReDef">
      <!-- scoreDef and staffDef within score, section, etc. -->
      <head>Redefinition of Score Parameters</head>
      <p>Sometimes it is necessary to provide the parameters of a score or a staff with new values.
        For example. a score may change keys, gain or lose staves, use different layout settings at
        any point, etc. Likewise, a staff may change its clef, gain or lose layers, or become
        invisible, and so on. To accommodate these circumstances, in CMN <gi scheme="MEI"
          >staffDef</gi> is allowed to occur in the following locations:</p>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>within the description of staff groups; that is, in <gi scheme="MEI"
          >staffGrp</gi>,</item>
        <item>within the content of a <gi scheme="MEI">measure</gi>,</item>
        <item>between measures; that is, directly within <gi scheme="MEI">section</gi> and <gi
            scheme="MEI">ending</gi> elements, and</item>
        <item>between sections and endings; that is, directly within a <gi scheme="MEI">score</gi>
          or <gi scheme="MEI">part</gi> element.</item>
      </list>

      <p>In addition, <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi> is allowed to occur:</p>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>within sections and endings; that is, inside <gi scheme="MEI">section</gi> and <gi
            scheme="MEI">ending</gi> elements; and </item>
        <item>between sections and endings; that is, directly within a <gi scheme="MEI">score</gi>
          or <gi scheme="MEI">part</gi>.</item>
      </list>

      <p>The possibility also exists to include <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI"
          >staffDef</gi> in staves and layers when the mei-all schema is in use; however, this
        practice is not recommended for the CMN repertoire.</p>

    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnNotesChords">
      <head>Notes, Chords and Rests in CMN</head>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="cmnNotes">
        <head>Notes</head>
        <p>Undoubtedly, the most important element for any music notation representation is the <gi
            scheme="MEI">note</gi> element, which is defined in section <ptr
            target="#sharedBasicEvents"/>. This section describes the usage of <gi scheme="MEI"
            >note</gi> in the CMN repertoire as well as CMN-specific additions to the basic
          definition in the shared module.</p>
        <div type="div5" xml:id="cmnNotesBasic">
          <head>Basic Usage of Notes in CMN</head>
          <p>In CMN, notes are determined by three basic parameters:</p>
          <list>
            <item>pitch name (using <att>pname</att>)</item>
            <item>octave (using <att>oct</att>)</item>
            <item>duration (using <att>dur</att>)</item>
          </list>
          <p>A typical note, in this case a quarter note C4, is therefore encoded like so:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<note pname="c" oct="4" dur="4"/>
          </egXML>
          <p>Because these attributes may not be required in all situations (such as <att>dur</att>
            for the notes of a chord), processing software should anticipate retrieving the
            information that would have been provided by missing attributes from a preceding note or
              <gi scheme="MEI">chord</gi> parent in the same <gi scheme="MEI">layer</gi>. Only
            information from <att>pname</att>, <att>oct</att> and <att>dur</att> attributes can be
            gathered in this fashion. No other attributes can be treated this way.</p>

          <p>The usual CMN-specific values for <att>dur</att> are:</p>
          <list type="gloss">
            <label>1</label>
            <item> - whole note</item>
            <label>2</label>
            <item> - half note</item>
            <label>4</label>
            <item> - quarter note</item>
            <label>8</label>
            <item> - eighth note</item>
            <label>16</label>
            <item> - sixteenth note</item>
            <label>…</label>
            <item/>
            <label>2048</label>
            <item> - 2048th note</item>
          </list>
          <p>Additionally, the following two values borrowed from mensural notation are allowed, as
            they sometimes also appear in CMN:</p>
          <list type="gloss">
            <label>breve</label>
            <item> - double whole</item>
            <label>long</label>
            <item> - quadruple whole</item>
          </list>
          <p>Please note that their mensural counterparts bear different names in order to clearly
            distinguish between repertoires.</p>
          <p>Dotted durational values are accommodated by the <att>dots</att> attribute, which
            records the number of written augmentation dots. Thus, a dotted quarter note may is
            represented:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<note pname="c" oct="4" dur="4" dots="1"/>
          </egXML>
        </div>
        <div type="div5" xml:id="cmnNotesGrace">
          <head>Grace Notes</head>
          <p>The CMN module adds two optional attributes, <att>grace</att> and
            <att>grace.time</att>, to <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">chord</gi>.
            The presence of the <att>grace</att> attribute indicates a grace note.</p>
          <figure>
            <head>Grace notes</head>
            <graphic url="Images/modules/cmn/grace-300.png" width="500px"/>
          </figure>
          <p>The encoding of the left-most example would look like this:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<beam>
  <note pname="d" oct="5" dur="8" stem.dir="down"/>
  <note pname="e" oct="5" dur="8" grace="acc" stem.dir="up"/>
  <note pname="d" oct="5" dur="8" stem.dir="down"/>
  <note pname="c" accid="s" oct="5" dur="8" grace="acc" stem.dir="up"/>
  <note pname="d" oct="5" dur="8" stem.dir="down"/>
  <note pname="b" oct="4" dur="8" stem.dir="down"/>
</beam>
          </egXML>

          <p>Grace notes are not counted when determining the measure's conformance to the current
            time signature. Therefore, the <att>dur</att> attribute records only the
              <emph>written</emph> rhythmic value of the grace note. The time necessary for the
            performance of grace notes can be unspecified, calculated based on taking time from
            other non-grace notes, or specified precisely using the <att>dur.ges</att>
            attribute.</p>
          <p>The values of <att>grace</att> indicate from which note time is
              <soCalled>borrowed</soCalled> to perform the grace note: The preceding note, in which
            case the value 'unacc' (unaccented) is used, or the following note, when the value 'acc'
            (accented) is appropriate. Technically, this value determines if the note following the
            grace will keep its original onset time or will be slightly delayed to allow the grace
            note itself to be accented. Sometimes it is not clear how to perform a grace; in these
            situations the value 'unknown' allows one to indicate a grace note while unambiguously
            stating that its performed duration remains unknown.</p>
          <p>The <att>grace.time</att> attribute is only to be used in combination with the
              <att>grace</att> attribute. It records the amount of time (as a percentage of the
            written duration) that the grace note should <soCalled>steal</soCalled> from the
            preceding note (when <att>grace</att>='unacc') or the following note (when
              <att>grace</att>='acc').</p>
          <p>More information about grace notes in the context of other CMN ornaments is available
            in chapter <ptr target="#cmnOrnaments"/>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="div5" xml:id="cmnNotesStems">
          <head>Stem Modifications</head>
          <p>The CMN module makes the <ident type="class">att.stemmed.cmn</ident> attribute class
            available, which adds the optional <att>stem.mod</att> and <att>stem.with</att>
            attributes to <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">chord</gi>.</p>
          <p>The <att>stem.mod</att> attribute accommodates various stem modifiers found in the CMN
            repertoire. These symbols are placed on a note or chord's stem and generally indicate
            different types of tremolo and <term>Sprechstimme</term>. The following values are
            allowed:</p>
          <list type="gloss">
            <label>1slash</label>
            <item> - 1 slash through stem</item>
            <label>2slash</label>
            <item> - 2 slashes through stem</item>
            <label>3slash</label>
            <item> - 3 slashes through stem</item>
            <label>4slash</label>
            <item> - 4 slashes through stem</item>
            <label>5slash</label>
            <item> - 5 slashes through stem</item>
            <label>6slash</label>
            <item> - 6 slashes through stem</item>
            <label>sprech</label>
            <item> - X placed on stem</item>
            <label>z</label>
            <item> - Z placed on stem</item>
          </list>
          <p>The <att>stem.mod</att> attibute is normally used in accordance with practices
            described in section <ptr target="#cmnTrem"/>.</p>
          <!-- TODO:
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
            <!-\- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -\->
          </egXML>-->

          <p>The attribute <att>stem.with</att> allows for the indication of a stem that joins notes
            on adjacent staves.</p>
          <figure>
            <head>Cross-staff chord</head>
            <graphic url="Images/modules/cmn/xchord-300.png" width="500px"/>
          </figure>
          <p>The following code snippet demonstrates one method of encoding the first chord in the
            last measure in the image above. The <att>stem.with</att> attribute must occur on all
            the notes or chords attached to the cross-staff stem.</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<staff n="1">
  <layer n="1">
    <note pname="d" oct="4" dur="2" stem.with="below"/>
  </layer>
</staff>
<staff n="2">
  <layer n="1">
    <chord dur="2" stem.with="above">
      <note pname="b" oct="3" accid="n"/>
      <note pname="f" oct="3"/>
    </chord>
  </layer>
</staff>
          </egXML>
          <p>Alternatively, the encoder may choose to treat the notes in the lower staff as
            logically belonging to the top staff and to <soCalled>displace</soCalled> them using the
              <att>staff</att> attribute on <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi>. Some use cases, however, may
            require filling the time that those notes would normally occupy using the <gi
              scheme="MEI">space</gi> element described in section <ptr target="#sharedNoteSpacing"
            />. Using this mechanism, the example above could also be encoded like so:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<staff n="1">
  <layer n="1">
    <chord dur="2">
      <note pname="d" oct="4"/>
      <note pname="b" oct="3" staff="2" accid="n"/>
      <note pname="f" oct="3" staff="2"/>
    </chord>
    <!-- following content -->
  </layer>
</staff>
<staff n="2">
  <layer n="1">
    <!-- the time used by the notes on staff 2 filled with non-sounding "space" -->
    <space dur="2"/>
    <!-- following content -->
  </layer>
</staff>
          </egXML>

          <p>The choice between these two methods of representing material that crosses staves is
            often software-dependent.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="cmnRests">
        <head>Rests</head>
        <p>The <att>dur</att> attribute on <gi scheme="MEI">rest</gi> captures the written duration
          of the rest and allows the same values as on <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi> and <gi
            scheme="MEI">chord</gi>. The CMN module also makes three more elements available for
          special forms of rest:</p>
        <p>
          <specList>
            <specDesc key="mRest"/>
            <specDesc key="multiRest"/>
            <specDesc key="mSpace"/>
          </specList>
        </p>
        <div type="div5" xml:id="cmnRestsMRest">
          <head>Measure Rests</head>
          <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">mRest</gi> (<expan>measure rest</expan>) element is used to
            indicate a complete measure rest, independent from the meter of the current <gi
              scheme="MEI">measure</gi>.</p>
          <p>The <att>cutout</att> attribute provides for the description of the rendition of the
              <gi scheme="MEI">mRest</gi>. If <att>cutout</att> is set to
              <soCalled>cutout</soCalled> (the only value allowed), then the complete staff
            including the staff lines will not be rendered for this measure.</p>
          <figure>
            <head>Measure rest</head>
            <!-- TODO: Add image here -->
          </figure>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<staff>
  <layer>
    <mRest cutout="cutout"/>
  </layer>
</staff>
          </egXML>

          <p>It is a semantic error to mix an <gi scheme="MEI">mRest</gi> with other events in the
            same <gi scheme="MEI">layer</gi>. However, other <soCalled>control events</soCalled>,
            such as <gi scheme="MEI">fermata</gi>, may be used at the same time as <gi scheme="MEI"
              >mRest</gi>.</p>
          <!-- TODO: use schematron to enforce this? -->
        </div>
        <div type="div5" xml:id="cmnRestsMultiRest">
          <head>Multiple-Measure Rests</head>
          <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">multiRest</gi> (<expan>multiple measure rest</expan>) element is
            used to encode multiple measures of rest. It is commonly used in performer parts, but
            due to the problem of synchronicity with other staves, it is never found in scores. A
            numeric value, stored in the <att>num</att> attribute, indicates the number of resting
            measures. The various visual forms displayed below are not captured by <gi scheme="MEI"
              >multiRest</gi>, but may be created by rendering software.</p>
          <figure>
            <head>Forms of multiple measure rests</head>
            <graphic url="Images/ExampleImages/multirest.png" width="500px"/>
          </figure>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<staff>
  <layer>
    <multiRest num="9"/>
  </layer>
</staff>
          </egXML>
        </div>
        <div type="div5" xml:id="cmnRestsMSpace">
          <head>Empty Measures</head>
          <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">mSpace</gi> (<expan>measure space</expan>) element is closely
            related to the <gi scheme="MEI">space</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">mRest</gi> elements. It
            is used to explicitly indicate that a layer has no content but that no information is
            missing from the encoding.</p>
          <figure>
            <head>Empty measure</head>
            <graphic url="Images/ExampleImages/mspace-300-20100514.png" width="500px"/>
          </figure>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure n="2">
  <staff>
    <layer>
      <mSpace/>
    </layer>
  </staff>
</measure>
          </egXML>

        </div>
      </div>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnTstamp">
      <head>Timestamps and Durations</head>
      <p>MEI offers multiple ways of defining onsets and offsets of timed musical events such as
        notes and slurs. The most common and most musician-friendly approach to this is through the
        use of a combination of the attributes <att>tstamp</att> and <att>dur</att>, which are made
        available by the attribute classes <ident type="class">att.timestamp.musical</ident>
        (inherited by <ident type="class">att.controlevent</ident>) and <ident type="class"
          >att.duration.musical</ident>, both from the shared module.</p>
      <p>The <term>timestamp</term> (<att>tstamp</att>) of a musical event is calculated in relation
        to the meter of the current measure and resembles the so-called <soCalled>beat</soCalled>.
        In a common time measure with four quarter notes, the timestamp of each quarter equals its
        beat position in the measure: The first quarter has a timestamp of 1, the second has a
        timestamp of 2, and so on. MEI defines the value of <att>tstamp</att> as a real number; the
        second eighth note position in a measure would thus be represented by the value of "1.5".
        The range of possible values is defined as starting with zero and ending with the number of
        metrical units in a measure (the <soCalled>numerator</soCalled> in a time signature) + 1.
        This allows the capture of all graphical positions starting from the left barline ('0') and
        ending with the right barline of the measure ('5', in the case of 4/4 time).</p>
      <p>For expressing durations, MEI offers the <att>dur</att> attribute. This attribute is
        described in section <ptr target="#cmnNotesBasic"/>.</p>
      <p>For <soCalled>spanning</soCalled> elements like slurs, which are members of the <ident
          type="class">model.controleventLike</ident> class, it is often more intuitive to record
        two timestamps – one for the onset of the event and one for its termination. Because the
        termination of the event may be in a succeeding measure, the second timestamp
          (<att>tstamp2</att>) has a slightly different datatype than the one marking the initiation
        of the event. Its datatype is constrained to values following the formula "<hi rend="italic"
          >x</hi>m+<hi rend="italic">y</hi>", where <hi rend="italic">x</hi> is the number of full
        measures that this particular feature lasts (or the number of bar lines crossed) and <hi
          rend="italic">y</hi> is the timestamp in the target measure where the feature ends. The
        timestamp is expressed using the same logic as described above. For example, a value of
        "0m+3" in 4/4 time indicates that the element bearing this attribute, a slur for example,
        ends on beat 3 of the same measure where it started. A value of "1m+1.5" would indicate an
        end on the second eighth note of the following measure. In 6/8 time, the value "2m+3" means
        that the feature ends two measures later on the third eighth note.</p>
    </div>
    <!--<div type="div3" xml:id="cmnIMT1to6datatype">
      <head>Spanning Features in Single-pass Encodings</head>
      <p><!-\- TODO: Cover imt[1-6] datatype here in a generic fashion -\->
        <!-\- This datatype must be restricted to a single staff. -\->
      </p>
    </div>-->
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="cmnAdditionalMeasureContent">
    <head>Advanced CMN Features</head>
    <p>Over time, in addition to the basic features of note, chord, and rest, many other symbols
      have been added to CMN. The following section describes some of these symbols and introduces
      their handling in MEI.</p>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnBeams">
      <head>Beams</head>
      <p>A very common feature of music from the CMN repertoire is the beaming of eighth or shorter
        notes. MEI provides two elements for the explicit encoding of features joined by beams.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="beam"/>
          <specDesc key="beamSpan"/>
        </specList>
      </p>

      <p>Use of the <gi scheme="MEI">beam</gi> element is straightforward. The beamed notes, rests,
        or chords are simply enclosed by the <gi scheme="MEI">beam</gi> element:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<layer>
  <beam>
    <note dur="8"/>
    <note dur="8"/>
  </beam>
</layer>
      </egXML>

      <p>Whereas in music notation every note value shorter than an eighth adds another beam
        (sometimes referred to as <soCalled>secondary beams</soCalled>), in MEI only one beam
        element is used, no matter the durations of the contained notes. The visual rendition of a
        set of beamed notes is presumed to be handled by rendering processes.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<layer>
  <!--...-->
  <beam>
    <note dur="16"/>
    <note dur="32"/>
    <note dur="32"/>
    <note dur="16" dots="1"/>
    <note dur="32"/>
  </beam>
  <!-- ...-->
</layer>
      </egXML>

      <p>From the 19th century onwards, it became quite common to break secondary beams to increase
        readability of longer beamed passages. The optional <att>breaksec</att> attribute on <gi
          scheme="MEI">note</gi>s and <gi scheme="MEI">chord</gi>s under the beam may be used to
        encode the breaking of secondary beams <emph>after</emph> the note or chord bearing the
        attribute. The value of <att>breaksec</att> indicates the number of continuous beams. For
        example:</p>
      <figure>
        <head>Primary and secondary beams</head>
        <graphic url="Images/ExampleImages/beam-a-20100510.png" width="500px"/>
      </figure>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<layer>
  <beam>
    <note dur="8" dots="1"/>
    <note dur="16"/>
  </beam>
  <beam>
    <note dur="32"/>
    <note dur="32"/>
    <note dur="16" breaksec="1"/>
    <note dur="32"/>
    <note dur="32"/>
    <note dur="32"/>
    <note dur="32"/>
  </beam>
</layer>
      </egXML>

      <p>In the music of the second half of the 20th century, it is quite common to indicate
        acceleration or deceleration using converging beams as in the image below:</p>

      <p>The encoding of such a beam is accomplished using the <att>rend</att> attribute of the
        beam, which allows the following values:</p>
      <list type="gloss">
        <label>acc</label>
        <item> - The secondary beams start in their usual position and gradually converge until they
          meet with the primary beam on the last note (or, the first eighth note under the beam). </item>
        <label>rit</label>
        <item> - The secondary beams gradually diverge until they reach their regular distance. </item>
        <label>mixed</label>
        <item> - The secondary beams diverge and converge arbitrarily.</item>
        <label>norm</label>
        <item> - The beam is rendered as usual (default). </item>
      </list>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<layer>
  <!-- … -->
  <beam rend="acc">
    <note dur="8"/>
    <note/>
    <note/>
    <note/>
    <note/>
    <note dur="32"/>
  </beam>
  <!-- … -->
</layer>
      </egXML>
      <p>The duration of notes, rests, or chords under a beam which carries the <att>rend</att>
        attribute with a value of 'acc', 'rit', or 'mixed' must be treated specially. The first and
        last contained elements must specify a duration which matches the number of beams displayed
        at the point of these events. In the case of a 'mixed' beam, each event at the point of
        change in the number of secondary beams must carry a <att>dur</att> attribute. Beams like
        this may be encoded thusly:</p>
      <figure>
        <head>Accelerando beams</head>
        <graphic url="Images/modules/cmn/beamAcc-Rit.png" width="500px"/>
      </figure>
      <p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<layer>
  <!-- … -->
  <beam rend="mixed">
    <note dur="8"/>
    <note dur="8"/>
    <note/>
    <note/>
    <note/>
    <note dur="32"/>
  </beam>
  <beam rend="mixed">
    <note dur="32"/>
    <note/>
    <note/>
    <note/>
    <note/>
    <note dur="8"/>
    <note dur="8"/>
  </beam>
  <!-- … -->
</layer>
        </egXML>
      </p>

      <!-- TODO: Cross-staff beaming using @beam.with -->
      <figure>
        <head>Cross-staff beam</head>
        <graphic url="Images/ExampleImages/beam-c-20100510.png" height="150px"/>
      </figure>

      <p>Beams that connect events on different staves may be encoded in two different ways. First,
        a single-layer approach may be taken that treats the events lying under the beam as
        logically belonging to the same layer as the initial event but visually
          <soCalled>displaced</soCalled> to an adjacent staff. In the example below, the last two
        notes under the beam carry a <att>staff</att> attribute value that contradicts the
          <soCalled>normal</soCalled> staff placement indicated by the <att>n</att> attribute on
        their ancestor <gi scheme="MEI">staff</gi>.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<staff n="2">
  <layer>
    <beam>
      <note pname="g" oct="3" dur="16"/>
      <note pname="b"/>
      <note pname="d" oct="4" staff="1"/>
      <note pname="f" staff="1"/>
    </beam>
  </layer>
</staff>
      </egXML>
      <p>Alternatively, a staff-by-staff methodology may be employed in which the notes are encoded
        according to the staff on which they appear. This encoding style requires that each <gi
          scheme="MEI">beam</gi> element account for the total time encompassed by the beam; that
        is, each <gi scheme="MEI">beam</gi> must use one or more <gi scheme="MEI">space</gi>
        elements to account for the time occupied by notes on the opposing staff. For example, the
        time used by the first two notes of the beam must be represented on staff number 1 and the
        time taken by the last two notes of the beam must be filled on staff number 2.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure>
  <staff n="1">
    <layer>
      <beam beam.with="below">
        <space dur="8"/>
        <note pname="d" oct="4"/>
        <note pname="f"/>
      </beam>
    </layer>    
  </staff>
  <staff n="2">
    <layer>
      <beam beam.with="above">
        <note pname="g" oct="3" dur="16"/>
        <note pname="b"/>
        <space dur="8"/>
      </beam>
    </layer>
  </staff>
</measure>
      </egXML>
      <p>Downstream processing needs are the determining factor in the choice between the two
        alternative encoding methods.</p>

      <p>Due to the potential problem of overlapping hierarchies, the <gi scheme="MEI">beam</gi>
        element only allows the encoding of beams that do not cross barlines. When beams cross
        barlines, the use of the <gi scheme="MEI">beamSpan</gi> element is required. Unlike <gi
          scheme="MEI">beam</gi>, the <gi scheme="MEI">beamSpan</gi>element does not contain the
        beamed notes as its children. Instead, it references the <att>xml:id</att> values of all
        affected notes in its <att>plist</att> attribute and denotes the initial and terminal notes
        of the beam using <att>startid</att> and <att>endid</att> attributes. This configuration
        allows beams to cross measure boundaries. The following example demonstrates a typical
        example of such hierarchy-crossing beams:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<beamSpan startid="#note1" endid="#note4" plist="#note1 #note2 #note3 #note4"/>
      </egXML>

      <p>In addition to the explicit encoding of beams accommodated by the <gi scheme="MEI"
          >beam</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">beamSpan</gi> elements and the <att>beam</att> attribute,
        MEI allows for specification of default beaming behavior using the following attributes on
          <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi>, <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi>, and <gi scheme="MEI"
          >layerDef</gi>:</p>
      <list type="gloss">
        <label><att>beam.group</att></label>
        <item> - Provides an example of how automated beaming (including secondary beams) is to be
          performed.</item>
        <label><att>beam.rests</att></label>
        <item> - Indicates whether automatically-drawn beams should include rests shorter than a
          quarter note duration.</item>
      </list>

      <p>The <att>beam.group</att> attribute can be used to set a default beaming pattern to be used
        when no beaming is indicated at the layer level. It must contain a comma-separated list of
        time values that add up to a measure in the current meter, e.g., '4,4,4,4' in 4/4 time
        indicates that each quarter note worth of shorter notes should be beamed together.
        Parentheses can be used to indicate sub-groupings of secondary beams. For example,
        '(4.,4.,4.)' in 9/8 meter indicates one primary beam per measure with secondary beams broken
        at each dotted quarter duration, while '(4,4),(4,4)' in 4/4 will result in a measure of 16th
        notes being rendered with a primary beam covering all the notes and secondary beams for each
        group of four 16th notes.</p>
      <p>The <att>beam.group</att> attribute is available on <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi>, <gi
          scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi>, and <gi scheme="MEI">layerDef</gi> elements, making it
        possible to set different beaming patterns for each of these. Also, the beaming pattern can
        be changed anywhere score parameters may be changed, for example, at the start of sections.
        This beaming "directive" can be overridden by using <gi scheme="MEI">beam</gi>, <gi
          scheme="MEI">beamSpan</gi>, or <att>beam</att> attributes as described above. If none of
        these beaming specifications is used, then no beaming is implied. Default beaming can be
        explicitly 'turned off' by setting <att>beam.group</att> to an empty string.</p>

    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnSlurTies">
      <head>Ties, Slurs and Phrase Marks</head>
      <p>One of the most specific features of CMN is the use of <soCalled>curved lines</soCalled>
        which connect notes. These lines are used to indicate various musical features, depending on
        their context.</p>
      <p>A <term>tie</term> is a curved line connecting <hi rend="bold">two</hi> notes of the <hi
          rend="bold">same pitch</hi>. The purpose of a tie is to join the durations of both notes,
        so that the first note sounds for the combined duration. In other words, there is only one
        onset for both notes.</p>
      <p>In MEI, ties can be encoded in different ways, depending on the level of detail that the
        encoder wants to preserve. The simplest solution is to use the <att>tie</att> attribute
        found on <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">chord</gi>.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<note pname="f" oct="4" dur="2" tie="i"/>
<note pname="f" oct="4" dur="4" dots="1" tie="t"/>
      </egXML>

      <p>This attribute allows three values:</p>
      <list type="gloss">
        <label><emph>i</emph> (initial)</label>
        <item> - Marks the start of a tie</item>
        <label><emph>m</emph> (medial)</label>
        <item> - Marks a participant in a tie other than the first or last</item>
        <label><emph>t</emph> (terminal)</label>
        <item> - Marks the end of a tie</item>
      </list>

      <p>The scope of the <att>tie</att> attribute is the musical <gi scheme="MEI">layer</gi>; that
        is, a tie started in one layer may only be ended by a subsequent musical event with a
          <att>tie</att> attribute with an <emph>m</emph> or <emph>t</emph> value in the same layer.
        The tie-terminating event may lie in the following measure.</p>
      <figure>
        <head>Ties across barlines</head>
        <graphic url="Images/modules/cmn/finger-300.png" width="500px"/>
      </figure>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure n="1">
  <!-- staff 1 omitted -->
  <staff n="2">
    <layer n="1">
      <chord dur="16"/>
      <beam>
        <note pname="f" tie="i"/>
        <note pname="a" tie="i"/>
        <note pname="c" tie="i"/>
      </beam>
      <chord dur="4">
        <note pname="f" tie="i"/>
        <note pname="c" tie="m"/>
        <note pname="a" tie="m"/>
        <note pname="f" tie="m"/>
      </chord>
    </layer>
  </staff>
</measure>
<measure n="2">
  <!-- staff 1 omitted -->
  <staff n="2">
    <layer n="1">
      <chord dur="16">
        <note pname="f" tie="t"/>
        <note pname="c" tie="t"/>
        <note pname="a" tie="t"/>
        <note pname="f" tie="t"/>
      </chord>
      <!-- ... -->
    </layer>
  </staff>
</measure>
<!-- measures 3 and 4 omitted -->
      </egXML>

      <p>When <att>tie</att> is used on chords, it functions as a shorthand indication for multiple
        tie markings; that is, a separate tie is drawn for every pitch in the chord that remains
        unchanged in the succeeding chord.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<staff>
  <layer>
    <chord dur="4" tie="i">
      <note pname="f"/>
      <note pname="c"/>
      <note pname="a"/>
    </chord>
    <chord dur="4" tie="t">
      <note pname="f"/>
      <note pname="c"/>
      <note pname="a"/>
    </chord>
  </layer>
</staff>
      </egXML>

      <p>This is equivalent to the following, more verbose version:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<staff>
  <layer>
    <chord dur="4">
      <note pname="f" tie="i"/>
      <note pname="c" tie="i"/>
      <note pname="a" tie="i"/>
    </chord>
    <chord dur="4">
      <note pname="f" tie="t"/>
      <note pname="c" tie="t"/>
      <note pname="a" tie="t"/>
    </chord>
  </layer>
</staff>
      </egXML>

      <p>A <term>slur</term> is a curved line that connects a group of notes of different pitch. It
        normally indicates that an instrument-specific performance technique should be applied to
        the affected notes. For example, in notation for winds, the notes should be played in one
        breath, while a single bow is indicated for string instruments.</p>
      <figure>
        <head>Slurs</head>
        <graphic url="Images/ExampleImages/slur-300-20100514.png" height="100px"/>
      </figure>

      <p>In MEI, slurs may be encoded in a similar way to ties: <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi> and <gi
          scheme="MEI">chord</gi> bear a <att>slur</att> attribute that allows the commencement or
        ending of a slur at this element. The allowed values, however, are slightly different: The
          <emph>i</emph>, <emph>m</emph> or <emph>t</emph> are followed by a single digit in the
        range 1 to 6, as in the following example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<layer>
  <note pname="f" oct="4" dur="4" accid="s" slur="i1"/>
  <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="4" slur="m1"/>
  <note pname="a" oct="4" dur="4" slur="t1"/>
</layer>
      </egXML>

      <p>The reason for this difference is that slurs, unlike ties, may overlap, so that a second
        slur may start while the first slur is still ongoing. The digit indicates the level of
        nesting of slurs on the note; '1' indicates no nesting, while '2' indicates the existence of
        2 slurs in which this note participates, and so on. In the example below, the second and
        third quarter notes lie under 2 slurs. The second note is covered by the slur that begins on
        the preceding note and by the one that it starts. The third note is affected by the slur
        that begins on note one and by the one that starts on note two.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<staff>
  <layer>
    <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="2" slur="i1"/>
    <note pname="a" oct="4" dur="8" slur="i2"/>
    <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="8" slur="t2"/>
    <note pname="f" oct="4" dur="4" accid="s" slur="t1"/>
  </layer>
  <layer>
    <note pname="b" oct="3" dur="2" dots="1" slur="i1"/>
    <note pname="d" oct="4" dur="4" slur="t1"/>
  </layer>
</staff>
      </egXML>

      <!--  Perhaps this should only be permitted when the analysis module is enabled. Hmmm ... -->
      <p>To support analytical operations, <att>slur</att> may take on more than one value. For
        example, the example above may be more explicitly encoded as:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<staff>
  <layer>
    <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="2" slur="i1"/>
    <note pname="a" oct="4" dur="8" slur="m1 i2"/>
    <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="8" slur="m1 t2"/>
    <note pname="f" oct="4" dur="4" accid="s" slur="t1"/>
  </layer>
  <layer>
    <note pname="b" oct="3" dur="2" dots="1" slur="i1"/>
    <note pname="d" oct="4" dur="4" slur="t1"/>
  </layer>
</staff>
      </egXML>
      <p>In this encoding, the notes in the beamed group are marked as participating in two slurs –
        one connecting just the beamed notes and one connecting the first and last notes of the
        layer. In <soCalled>nested</soCalled> slurs like this, the function of the slurs is usually
        different. Here, the slur connecting the 8th notes indicates <term>legato</term>
        performance, while the longer slur functions as a phrase mark.</p>

      <p>While ties are not normally allowed to cross layers or staves, slurs may. The following
        example demonstrates how cross-staff slurs may be encoded using the <att>slur</att>
        attribute:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure>
  <staff>
    <layer>
      <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="4" slur="i1"/>
      <note pname="a" oct="4" dur="8" slur="m1"/>
      <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="8" slur="m1"/>
      <note pname="f" oct="4" dur="4" accid="s" slur="m1"/>
    </layer>
  </staff>
  <staff>
    <layer>
      <note pname="b" oct="3" dur="2" dots="1"/>
      <note pname="d" oct="4" dur="4" slur="t1"/>
    </layer>
  </staff>
</measure>
      </egXML>

      <p>Slurs and ties that cross system or page breaks are often split into two separate symbols
        for rendering. One slur or tie ends at the last barline, another one starts at the beginning
        of the new system. MEI expects this to be the default rendering behaviour, so that in
        situations like these, the regular <att>tie</att> or <att>slur</att> attributes are
        sufficient to describe both curved lines resulting from the split.</p>
      <p>Sometimes, however, one of these two symbols is missing in the document, or the encoder
        wants to provide additional (often visual) information about the slur or tie. In these
        cases, using an attribute is not an adequate solution. Therefore, MEI offers dedicated <gi
          scheme="MEI">tie</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">slur</gi> elements. A third element, <gi
          scheme="MEI">phrase</gi>, is used to identify a unified melodic idea (in German:
          <foreign>Phrasierungsbogen</foreign>), whereas the <gi scheme="MEI">slur</gi> element is
        used as a generic element for all curved lines (in German: <foreign>Bogensetzung</foreign>)
        except ties. All three elements have nearly identical models.</p>
      <p>Another reason for using elements instead of attributes for ties, slurs, and phrase marks
        is that only elements may be combined with the functionality provided in chapters <ptr
          target="#editTrans"/> and <ptr target="#critApp"/> of these Guidelines.</p>
      <p>Although these elements are allowed within a <gi scheme="MEI">layer</gi> to accommodate
        unmeasured notation, by convention in CMN they are normally placed inside <gi scheme="MEI"
          >measure</gi>, after the encoding of staves, alongside other so-called <soCalled>control
          events</soCalled>.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure>
  <staff n="1">
    <layer>
      <note pname="c" oct="5" dur="4"/>
      <note pname="f" oct="4" dur="4"/>
      <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="4"/>
      <note pname="c" oct="4" dur="4"/>
    </layer>
  </staff>
  <slur/>
  <tempo/>
  <dynam/>
</measure>
      </egXML>

      <p>Obviously, to be complete the slur in the above example needs to be
          <soCalled>attached</soCalled> to the notes somehow. The <soCalled>vertical
          assignment</soCalled> can be indicated for the example above using the <att>staff</att>
        and <att>layer</att> attributes like so:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<slur staff="1" layer="1"/>
      </egXML>

      <p>For the <soCalled>horizontal assignment</soCalled>, the encoder may choose between two
        different mechanisms. The first uses two timestamp attributes as described in section <ptr
          target="#cmnTstamp"/>. The start and end points of the slur may be indicated thusly:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<slur staff="1" layer="1" tstamp="1" tstamp2="0m+4"/>
      </egXML>

      <p>By using <att>tstamp</att> and <att>tstamp2</att> attributes, the encoder denotes a rather
        loose connection – the slur (or tie) is attached to a certain position in the measure, not
        to a specific note or chord. If the encoder wants to specify a close connection to a
        particular event, the <att>startid</att> and <att>endid</att> attributes may be used
        instead. Here, the <att>xml:id</att>s of the first and last note of the slur are referenced.
        This mechanism also allows the crossing of layers and staves.
        <!--, as in the following example:--></p>
      <!-- TODO:
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
        <!-\- TODO: Snippet from Webern, also as graphic -\->
      </egXML>-->

      <p>For human readability, it is recommended to encode <gi scheme="MEI">slur</gi>, <gi
          scheme="MEI">tie</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">phrase</gi> features in the <gi scheme="MEI"
          >measure</gi> where they begin; that is, in the measure that holds the element referenced
        by <att>startid</att>. On the other hand, for machine processability, it may be desirable to
        place <gi scheme="MEI">slur</gi>, <gi scheme="MEI">tie</gi>, and <gi scheme="MEI"
          >phrase</gi> elements in the measure <emph>where they end</emph> or even in the <emph>last
          measure</emph> regardless of their beginning and ending points in the music. This last
        option makes all references contained within these elements <soCalled>back
          references</soCalled>. Back references are necessary when using processing software that
        treats the encoded file as a stream; that is, programs that process the file without
        creating an in-memory representation of its contents.</p>
      <p>When using the <gi scheme="MEI">tie</gi>, <gi scheme="MEI">slur</gi> or <gi scheme="MEI"
          >phrase</gi> elements, the curvature of the line may be described using the
          <att>curvedir</att>, <att>bulge</att> and <att>bezier</att> attributes. Whereas the first
        attribute allows only specification of the slur's vertical placement, the others give
        increasingly more precise control of the curve.</p>
      <p>If the encoder wishes to draw attention to the appearance of a slur or tie in a given
        source, the <att>facs</att> attribute may be used instead of (or in addition to) the curve
        description attributes to point to a graphic image or a zone within an image (see <ptr
          target="#facsimiles"/>).</p>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnDynam">
      <head>Dynamics in CMN</head>
      <p>Common Music Notation provides two different methodologies for expressing the volume of a
        note, phrase, section, etc. The first is a verbal instruction providing such information in
        human language, possibly in an abbreviated form. An example is the word <term><hi
            rend="italic">piano</hi></term>, indicating a quiet volume, often abbreviated as
            <term><hi rend="italic">p</hi></term>. In MEI, verbal instructions like this are encoded
        using the <gi scheme="MEI">dynam</gi> element from the Shared module (see chapter <ptr
          target="#shared"/>):</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<dynam>p</dynam>
      </egXML>

      <p>By convention, <gi scheme="MEI">dynam</gi> elements, like <gi scheme="MEI">slur</gi> and
        other elements belonging to the <ident type="class">model.controleventLike</ident> class,
        are encoded at the end of the <gi scheme="MEI">measure</gi> to which they belong. This
        requires <gi scheme="MEI">dynam</gi> to be assigned to a certain <gi scheme="MEI">staff</gi>
        using the <att>staff</att> attribute, whose value refers to the target element's
          <att>n</att> attribute. In the absence of other information, all layers within the staff
        are assumed to have the same dynamic marking.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<dynam staff="1">p</dynam>
      </egXML>

      <p>However, when the layers of a staff have different dynamic indications, the
          <att>layer</att> attribute may be used to associate a dynamic marking with a particular
        layer:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<dynam staff="1" layer="1">p</dynam>
<dynam staff="1" layer="2">mf</dynam>
      </egXML>

      <p>A value in the range 0-127 may be assigned to a dynamic marking using the <att>val</att>
        attribute:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<dynam staff="2" layer="1" place="above" tstamp="1" val="84">f</dynam>
      </egXML>

      <p>The location of a dynamic marking in relation to a staff may be specified using the
          <att>place</att> attribute, which may be given as <emph>above</emph>, <emph>within</emph>,
        or <emph>below</emph> the staff:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<dynam staff="1" place="above">p</dynam>
      </egXML>

      <p>Dynamics must also be associated with a particular time point in a measure, using the
          <att>tstamp</att>, or with a particular event, using the <att>startid</att> attribute.
        Linking a control event with measures and events is discussed in section <ptr
          target="#cmnTstamp"/>:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure>
  <staff n="1">
    <!-- content omitted -->
  </staff>
  <staff n="2">
    <layer n="1">
      <note pname="c" oct="4" dur="2" stem.mod="2slash"/>
      <note pname="e" oct="4" dur="2" stem.mod="2slash"/>
    </layer>
    <layer n="2">
      <!-- content omitted -->
    </layer>
  </staff>
  <dynam staff="2" layer="1" place="above" tstamp="1">p</dynam>
  <dynam staff="2" layer="1" place="above" tstamp="2.5">cresc. poco a poco</dynam>
</measure>
      </egXML>
      <p>Dynamics which do not have an explicit endpoint are often referred to as
          <soCalled>instantaneous</soCalled>. On the other hand, some dynamic directions indicate a
        continuous change that must have a defined end point. It is possible to specify the logical
        scope of continuous dynamic marks using the attributes <att>tstamp2</att>, <att>dur</att> or
          <att>endid</att>. In order to capture the fact that they continue until the first beat of
        the next measure, the <term>crescendi</term> in the example above may be marked:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<!-- using the tstamp2 attribute -->
<dynam staff="2" place="above" tstamp="2.5" tstamp2="1m+1">cresc. poco a poco</dynam>
<!-- using the endid attribute -->
<dynam staff="2" place="above" tstamp="2.5" endid="ID_of_ending_note">cresc. poco a poco</dynam>
      </egXML>

      <p>Any combination of <att>tstamp</att>, <att>startid</att>, <att>tstamp2</att>, and
          <att>endid</att> attributes may be used to define the scope of a dynamic, although the
          <att>tstamp</att> and <att>tstamp2</att> or the <att>startid</att> and <att>endid</att>
        combinations are the most likely combinations. For example, the following alternatives are
        all possibilities for encoding up a <term>crescendo</term>. The choice of attributes is
        often task or processor dependent.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<!-- tstamp attribute indicates starting point, dur attribute marks the end -->
<dynam staff="2" place="above" tstamp="2.5" tstamp2="1m+1">cresc. poco a poco</dynam>
<!-- tstamp attribute indicates starting point, endid attribute marks the end -->
<dynam staff="2" place="above" tstamp="2.5" endid="ID of last note">cresc. poco a
  poco</dynam>
<!-- startid attribute indicates starting point, tstamp2 attribute marks the end -->
<dynam staff="2" place="above" startid="ID_of_starting_note" tstamp2="1m+1">cresc. poco a
  poco</dynam>
<!-- startid attribute indicates starting point, endid attribute marks the end -->
<dynam staff="2" place="above" startid="ID_of_starting_note" endid="ID_of_ending_note">cresc. poco
  a poco</dynam>
      </egXML>

      <p>All musical elements affected by the <gi scheme="MEI">dynam</gi> may be explicitly
        specified using the <att>plist</att> attribute, which contains <att>xml:id</att> attribute
        value references:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<dynam staff="2" place="above" startid="#note1" endid="#note4" plist="#note1 #note2   #note3 #note4">cresc. poco a poco</dynam>
      </egXML>

      <p>It is recommended that the list of references in <att>plist</att> include all participants
        in the dynamic marking, including the first and last notes as in the preceding example, even
        though they are duplicated by <att>startid</att> and <att>endid</att> attributes.</p>

      <p>In addition to verbal instructions, Common Music Notation uses graphical symbols to
        indicate <soCalled>continuous</soCalled> dynamics. These <term>crescendo</term> and
          <term>decrescendo</term> (or <term>diminuendo</term>) symbols are encoded in MEI using the
          <gi scheme="MEI">hairpin</gi> element. It also is a member of the <ident type="class"
          >model.controleventLike</ident> class, which means it too is used just before the close of
        a <gi scheme="MEI">measure</gi> element, following the encoding of all staves. The required
        attribute <att>form</att> specifies the direction of the symbol by taking one of two
        possible values: <emph>cres</emph> (growing louder) or <emph>dim</emph> (getting
        softer).</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<hairpin form="cres"/>
      </egXML>

      <p>Marking the logical extent of hairpins is possible using the same attributes as for <gi
          scheme="MEI">dynam</gi>. The following example shows a hairpin that begins on the second
        half of beat 2 (in the current measure) and ends on beat 1 (of the following measure).</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<hairpin form="cres" staff="2" layer="1" place="above" tstamp="2.5" tstamp2="1m+1"/>
      </egXML>

      <!-- TODO: discuss the other visual attributes of hairpin:
        @opening
        <memberOf key="att.color"/>
        <memberOf key="att.visualoffset"/>
        <memberOf key="att.visualoffset2"/>
        <memberOf key="att.xy"/>
        <memberOf key="att.xy2"/> -->

    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnTuplets">
      <head>Tuplets</head>
      <p>Tuplets indicate a localized change of meter; that is, a given duration in the regular
        meter is divided between a group of notes with irregular (according to the current meter)
        rhythmic values. The most common tuplet is a so-called <soCalled>triplet</soCalled>, in
        which three notes take the time normally occupied by two.</p>
      <p>The relation of the tuplet to the underlying meter is specified using the <att>num</att>
        and <att>numbase</att> attributes, where <att>num</att> specifies the number of replacing
        notes and <att>numbase</att> specifies the number of notes <emph>of the same duration</emph>
        to be replaced. For example, when three eighth notes replace one quarter note in common
        time, <att>num</att> takes a value of "3", whereas <att>numbase</att> reads "2", because a
        quarter note in common time is normally divided into two eighths. When three quarters
        replace two in the same meter, <att>numbase</att> also reads "2". The combination of these
        attributes may be read as "3 in the time of 2" in either case.</p>
      <p>The duration of the entire tuplet may be encoded using the usual <soCalled>power of
          2</soCalled> values, e.g., 1, 2, 4, etc., in the <att>dur</att> attribute, and the
          <att>dots</att> attribute, if necessary.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<layer>
  <tuplet num="3" numbase="2" dur="2">
    <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="4"/>
    <note pname="f" oct="4" dur="4" accid="s"/>
    <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="4"/>
  </tuplet>
  <note pname="d" oct="4" dur="2"/>
</layer>
      </egXML>

      <!-- TODO: Cover omission of numbase and/or dur. -->

      <p>Tuplets are often highlighted using brackets above or below the affected notes. The
        presence and position of these brackets can be encoded using the <att>bracket.place</att>
        (above / below) and <att>bracket.visible</att> (true / false) attributes.</p>
      <p>Usually, however, tuplets are rendered with a bracket (<att>bracket.visible</att>="true")
        and a single number (<att>num.format</att>="count" and <att>num.visible</att>="true").
        However, the number-to-numbase ratio may be provided in addition to, or in some cases as a
        replacement for, the bracket. The <att>num.format</att> attribute indicates whether a plain
        number (the value of <att>num</att>) or a ratio (comprised of <att>num</att> and
          <att>numbase</att>, e.g., "3:2") should be displayed and <att>num.visible</att> indicates
        the general presence of such a number. </p>
      <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
        <!-\- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -\->
      </egXML>-->

      <p>In addition to <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi> elements, <gi scheme="MEI">tuplet</gi> may
        contain other elements, such as <gi scheme="MEI">rest</gi> or <gi scheme="MEI">space</gi>,
        to match the content of a source document or an intended rendering. In particular, the <gi
          scheme="MEI">beam</gi> element is allowed so that custom beaming may be indicated, e.g., a
        septuplet may be divided into a group of three plus a group of four
        notes.<!--, as described in Read, p. 187-215.--></p>
      <!-- TODO:
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
        <!-\- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -\->
      </egXML>-->

      <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">tuplet</gi> element may also be used for repetition of the same pitch;
        that is, a single note or chord may be the only content of the tuplet. In some cases,
        optical music recognition software may treat these instances as bowed tremolandi due to the
        knowledge of the complete semantics of the notation at the time of recognition. However,
        marking these as tuplets is the recommended practice.</p>

      <p>In some situations, a tuplet is made up of events in different measures. As this raises the
        issue of non-concurrent hierarchies, it is not possible to encode such situations with the
          <gi scheme="MEI">tuplet</gi> element described above. Therefore, MEI offers the <gi
          scheme="MEI">tupletSpan</gi> element, which is member of the <ident type="class"
          >model.controleventLike</ident> class. It is nested inside of <gi scheme="MEI"
          >measure</gi>, following all the measure's <gi scheme="MEI">staff</gi> children. It uses
        the same attributes as <gi scheme="MEI">tuplet</gi> to describe tuplets, but instead of
        nesting all affected notes inside itself, it references the <att>xml:id</att> values of all
        affected notes in its <att>plist</att> attribute and the initial and terminal notes of the
        tuplet using <att>startid</att> and <att>endid</att> attributes. This configuration allows
        tuplets to cross measure boundaries. The following example demonstrates a typical example of
        such hierarchy-crossing tuplets:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<tupletSpan startid="#note1" endid="#note4" plist="#note1 #note2 #note3 #note4"/>
      </egXML>

    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnArtic">
      <head>Articulation and Performance Instructions in CMN</head>
      <p>This section introduces elements and attributes which may hold CMN-specific performance
        instructions. The functionality described herein is related to the <att>artic</att>
        attribute and <gi scheme="MEI">artic</gi> element introduced in <ptr target="#shared"/>. The
        following elements are relevant in this context:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="bend"/>
          <specDesc key="bTrem"/>
          <specDesc key="fTrem"/>
          <specDesc key="gliss"/>
          <specDesc key="arpeg"/>
          <specDesc key="octave"/>
          <specDesc key="fermata"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="cmnArpegGliss">
        <head>Arpeggio and Glissando</head>
        <p>In CMN, the notes of a chord are sometimes performed successively rather than
          simultaneously. This behavior, called <term>arpeggiation</term>, is normally indicated
          using a wavy line preceding the chord. MEI offers the <gi scheme="MEI">arpeg</gi> element
          to describe arpeggios. This element is a member of the <ident type="class"
            >model.controleventLike</ident> class and, like other members of this class, uses the
            <att>staff</att>, <att>layer</att> and <att>tstamp</att> or the <att>startid</att> and
            <att>endid</att> attributes to connect it to the affected chord.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure>
  <staff n="1">
    <!-- content omitted -->
  </staff>
  <staff n="2">
    <layer>
      <note dur="4"/>
      <note dur="4"/>
      <chord dur="4">
        <!-- notes omitted -->
      </chord>
      <note/>
    </layer>
  </staff>
  <arpeg staff="2" tstamp="3"/>
</measure>
        </egXML>

        <p>The usual direction for the performance of an arpeggio is from lowest note to highest,
          but this is not always the case. The customary signal of an downward arpeggio is an
          arrowhead added to the bottom of the wavy line. The indication of the presence of an
          arrowhead and the direction of the arpeggio are handled separately, however. The
            <att>arrow</att> attribute indicates the presence of an arrowhead in the arpeggiation
          sign, while the <att>order</att> attribute records the preferred sequence of notes.</p>
        <p>The following example illustrates various ways in which the arrow and order attributes
          may be employed. The default visual rendition and performance are assumed in the absence
          of both attributes, while the typical downward arpeggio is indicated by the presence of
          both attributes. The last two possibilities occur less frequently, but are sometimes
          appropriate: The presence of the arrow attribute without the order attribute may be used
          in those cases where the arrowhead is redundant but is added to the symbol for the sake of
          consistency or when the direction of successive arpeggios changes frequently. The last
          possibility, an order attribute without an arrow attribute, is ambiguous; however, it can
          be used as an encoding shortcut since a downward arpeggio must have a visual indication of
          its direction to distinguish it from the upward arpeggio; therefore, the presence of the
          arrowhead can be implied.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<!-- default visualization and performance -->
<arpeg staff="2" tstamp="3"/>
<!-- downward arpeggio with arrow added to visual symbol -->
<arpeg staff="2" tstamp="3" order="down" arrow="true"/>
<!-- default rendition with (redundant) arrow added to the top of the visual symbol -->
<arpeg staff="2" tstamp="3" arrow="true"/>
<!-- downward arpeggio with no visual indication of order -->
<arpeg staff="2" tstamp="3" order="down"/>
        </egXML>

        <p>A third, and somewhat counter-intuitive, value for <att>order</att>, "nonarp", indicates
          that no arpeggio shall be performed. Normally rendered as a bracket instead of a wavy
          line, this form of arpeggio is used to indicate a non-arpeggiated chord intervening in a
          sequence of arpeggiated ones. This is common in music for the harp, where arpeggiation is
          the usual method of performing chords and deviation from the norm must be explicitly
          indicated.</p>
        <!-- TODO:
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
          <!-\- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -\->
        </egXML>-->

        <p>For arpeggios that involve chords spanning multiple staves as a continuous arpeggio
          (instead of two separate arpeggios), the <att>plist</att> attribute may be used to point
          to all affected <gi scheme="MEI">chord</gi> elements' <att>xml:id</att> attributes.</p>
        <!-- TODO:
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
          <!-\- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -\->
          <!-\- TODO: Example from Rachmaninoff c#min sonata -\->
        </egXML>-->

        <p>Whereas an arpeggio <soCalled>staggers</soCalled> the onset times of the notes of a
          chord, a <term>glissando</term> denotes a situation where the pitch
            <soCalled>slides</soCalled> from one note to another. It makes no difference whether
          this slide produces distinct intermediate pitches (as on the piano) or not (as on the
          trombone), though the latter is sometimes referred to as <term>portamento</term>. The
          visual appearance of a glissando, which MEI encodes as <gi scheme="MEI">gliss</gi>, is
          normally a line connecting the two most distant notes in the glissando.</p>

        <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">gliss</gi> element is a member of the <ident type="class"
            >model.controleventLike</ident> class and therefore, like other control events, it
          occurs inside a measure after the staves and uses its <att>staff</att>, <att>layer</att>,
            <att>tstamp</att>, <att>tstamp2</att>, <att>startid</att> and <att>endid</att>
          attributes to connect it to the affected notes or chords. It is a semantic error not to
          specify a starting point attribute. The visual appearance of the indicating line may be
          recorded in the <att>rend</att> attribute. Any text accompanying the line, such as
          "gliss.", may be provided in the <att>text</att> attribute.</p>

      </div>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="cmnBend">
        <head>Bend</head>
        <p>A bend is a variation in pitch (often microtonal) upwards or downwards during the course
          of a note. Typically, the performer attacks the note at <soCalled>true</soCalled> pitch,
          changes the intonation, then returns to true pitch. The <gi scheme="MEI">bend</gi> element
          can also be used for so-called scoop, plop, falloff, and doit performance effects. It
          should <hi rend="bold">not</hi> be used for laissez vibrer (l.v.) indications. As with
          other control events, the starting point of the bend may be indicated by either a tstamp,
          tstamp.ges, tstamp.real or startid attribute. It is a semantic error not to specify a
          starting attribute.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="cmnTrem">
        <head>Tremolandi</head>
        <!-- TODO: In german terminology, a tremolo often indicates an unmeasured series of notes (play as
          fast as you can). What we call "Faulenzer" (lazy one) is measured, though. Basically, the rendition of both
          is the same, but we distinguish between measured and unmeasured, not between identical and differing
          pitches. Is this something we should discuss on MEI-L?
        -->
        <p>CMN has two slightly different concepts which are both called <term>tremolo</term>. The
          first is a rapid repetition of a single pitch or chord, whereas the second is a rapid
          alternation between two different notes or chords. In addition, either species of tremolo
          may be <term>measured</term> or <term>unmeasured</term>. A measured tremolo is an
          abbreviation for written-out notation; that is, the tremolo is intended to be perceived as
          notes with distinct rhythmic values. On the other hand, in an unmeasured tremolo no
          specific number of alternations is intended.</p>
        <p>For the repetition of a single note or chord, MEI offers the <gi scheme="MEI">bTrem</gi>
          (bowed tremolo) element, which is a member of the <ident type="class"
            >model.eventLike</ident> class, meaning it is encoded following the normal course of
          musical events within a <gi scheme="MEI">layer</gi>. It holds exactly one <gi scheme="MEI"
            >note</gi> or <gi scheme="MEI">chord</gi> element that is to be repeated.</p>
        <figure>
          <head>Bowed tremolandi</head>
          <graphic url="Images/ExampleImages/btrem-a-20100510.png" width="500px"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<bTrem>
  <note pname="b" oct="4" dur="1"/>
</bTrem>
        </egXML>

        <p>The <att>measperf</att> attribute value indicates the exact note values in an aural
          rendition of a measured tremolo, i.e., quarters, 8ths, and so on. The stem modifier must
          also be explicity set on the child <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi> or <gi scheme="MEI"
            >chord</gi> element for a complete visual representation. The number of slashes present
          on the note may disagree with the number of slashes that should be present according to
          the <att>measperf</att> attribute, especially in music manuscripts.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<bTrem measperf="32">
  <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="4" stem.mod="3slash"/>
</bTrem>
        </egXML>

        <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">bTrem</gi> element can be used as shorthand for a tuplet consisting
          of repetitions of a single note or chord. This kind of markup may be the result of an
          optical music recognition process in which complete semantics cannot be determined
            <foreign>a priori</foreign>. When used this way, the <att>num</att> attribute on <gi
            scheme="MEI">bTrem</gi> can record a number to be rendered along with the pseudo-tuplet.
          In spite of this capability, the <gi scheme="MEI">tuplet</gi> element is preferred.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<bTrem num="3">
  <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="4" stem.mod="3slash"/>
</bTrem>
        </egXML>

        <p>In the case of alternating pitches, MEI offers the <gi scheme="MEI">fTrem</gi> (fingered
          tremolo) element. While it mostly behaves the same as <gi scheme="MEI">bTrem</gi>, a
          fingered tremolo requires exactly two child elements, either being a <gi scheme="MEI"
            >note</gi> or <gi scheme="MEI">chord</gi>. The <att>measperf</att> attribute value
          indicates the exact note values in an aural rendition of a measured tremolo, i.e., 4ths,
          8ths, 16ths, etc. The number of slashes present in the source is captured by the
            <att>slash</att> attribute. The number of slashes present may disagree with the rhythmic
          value indicated by the <att>measperf</att> attribute, especially in manuscript
          sources.</p>
        <!-- Naive encoder may capture as a beam! -->
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<fTrem measperf="32">
  <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="4"/>
  <note pname="c" oct="4" dur="4"/>
</fTrem>
        </egXML>

      </div>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="cmnFermata">
        <head>Fermata</head>
        <p>A very common feature of music notation from the CMN period is the so-called
            <soCalled>fermata</soCalled>. It is usually written as a dot above or below an arc. It
          may stand above or below the staff it affects. If this symbol is used, its
            <soCalled>open</soCalled> side always faces the staff. A fermata indicates that the note
          or rest under it should be held longer than its written duration would normally require.
          Sometimes, a fermata occurs over a barline to indicate the end of a phrase or section.</p>
        <p>In MEI, fermatas may be encoded using an attribute on <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi>, <gi
            scheme="MEI">chord</gi> or <gi scheme="MEI">rest</gi>. This attribute allows placement
          of a fermata above or below the element to which it's attached.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<note fermata="above"/>
        </egXML>
        <p>However, if there is further information about the fermata that should be addressed in
          the encoding, MEI offers the <gi scheme="MEI">fermata</gi> element. This element, which is
          a member of the <ident type="class">model.controleventLike</ident> class and therefore
          requires the use of such attributes as <att>staff</att>, <att>layer</att>,
            <att>tstamp</att> and <att>startid</att>, allows specification of the orientation of the
          fermata using its <att>form</att> attribute. In addition, the <att>shape</att> attribute
          may be used to indicate whether the fermata is rendered as a semicircle ("curved") or
          semisquare ("square"). If the fermata should be rendered using some other symbol, a
          user-defined symbol may be referred to using the <att>altsym</att> attribute.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<fermata staff="2" tstamp="4" form="inv" place="above" shape="square"/>
<fermata staff="2" tstamp="5" place="above" altsym="#myFermata.1"/>
        </egXML>

      </div>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="cmnOctave">
        <head>Octave Shift</head>
        <p>An indication that a passage should be performed one or more octaves above or below its
          written pitch is represented by the <gi scheme="MEI">octave</gi> element.</p>
        <figure>
          <head>Octave displacement</head>
          <graphic url="Images/ExampleImages/octave-a-20100510.png" width="500px"/>
        </figure>
        <p>Its <att>dis</att> and <att>dis.place</att> attributes record the amount and direction of
          displacement, respectively. The <att>rend</att> attribute captures the appearance of the
          continuation line associated with the octave displacement. The starting point of the
          octave displacement may be indicated by either a <att>tstamp</att>, <att>tstamp.ges</att>,
            <att>tstamp.real</att> or <att>startid</att> attribute, while the ending point may be
          recorded by either a <att>tstamp2</att>, <att>dur</att>, <att>dur.ges</att> or
            <att>endid</att> attribute. It is a semantic error not to specify one starting-type
          attribute and one ending-type attribute.</p>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnInstr">
      <head>Instrument-specific Symbols in CMN</head>
      <p>CMN contains a number of symbols which are closely related to a specific instrument. MEI
        offers elements for three of these symbols, namely breath marks, harp pedal diagrams, and
        piano pedals.</p>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="cmnBreath">
        <head>Breath Marks</head>
        <p>A <term>breath mark</term> indicates a point at which the performer of a wind instrument
          or singer may breathe. It is sometimes also used to indicate a short pause or break for
          instruments <hi rend="italic">not</hi> requiring breath, which allows it to also serve as
          a guide to phrasing. In MEI, breath marks are encoded using the <gi scheme="MEI"
            >breath</gi> element, which is a member of <ident type="class"
            >model.controleventLike</ident>. It is a semantic error not to specify a starting point
          attribute.</p>
        <!-- TODO: Add schematron rule enforcing tstamp or startid on breath. -->
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure>
  <staff n="1">
    <layer>
      <note pname="g" oct="3" dur="2" syl="Wald,"/>
      <note pname="c" oct="3" dur="4" syl="so"/>
    </layer>
  </staff>
  <breath staff="1" tstamp="1.5"/>
</measure>
        </egXML>

        <p>The usual sign for the breath mark is a comma; however, other visual forms of the breath
          mark may be indicated using the <att>altsym</att> attribute (see chapter <ptr
            target="#userSymbols"/> for further details).</p>
      </div>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="cmnHarp">
        <head>Harp Pedals</head>
        <p>Modern harps have seven pedals which allow adjustment of their strings to different
          pitches. The settings for these pedals occur at the beginning of the harp notation and/or
          whenever it is necessary to change the harp's tuning. These settings may be rendered using
          letter pitches (in the order of the pedals from left to right) or in a diagrammatic
          fashion, such as the form invented by Carlos Salzedo.</p>
        <p>In MEI, harp pedal settings are encoded using the <gi scheme="MEI">harpPedal</gi>
          element. It is a member of the <ident type="class">model.controleventLike</ident> class
          and is therefore placed within <gi scheme="MEI">measure</gi>, following all <gi
            scheme="MEI">staff</gi> children. The <att>staff</att> and <att>layer</att> attributes
          may be used to assign it to a certain <gi scheme="MEI">staff</gi> or <gi scheme="MEI"
            >layer</gi>. Either a <att>tstamp</att> or <att>startid</att> attribute must be used to
          indicate the placement within the measure (see <ptr target="#cmnTstamp"/> and <ptr
            target="#ptrRef"/> for further details about those linking mechanisms).</p>
        <p>The musical intention of the element is described using the <att>c</att>, <att>d</att>,
            <att>e</att>, <att>f</att>, <att>g</att>, <att>a</att> and <att>b</att> attributes,
          which affect the corresponding strings of the harp. All of these attributes may take the
          values "<emph>f</emph>" (flat), "<emph>s</emph>" (sharp) or "<emph>n</emph>" (natural),
          where "n" is the default value, which is assumed when one of these attributes is not
          specified.</p>
        <!-- Add image! -->
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure>
  <!-- staves omitted -->
  <harpPedal staff="2" tstamp="1" b="f" e="f" a="f"/>
</measure>
        </egXML>
        <p>In the preceding example, the A, B, and E pedals are in the flat position, while the
          other, non-specified pedals are in the natural position.</p>

      </div>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="cmnPedal">
        <head>Piano Pedal</head>
        <p>Music for piano also often includes indications of the use of pedals. In MEI, these
          symbols are encoded using the <gi scheme="MEI">pedal</gi> element. As a member of the
            <ident type="class">model.controleventLike</ident> class, it is located within <gi
            scheme="MEI">measure</gi> and refers to a staff, layer and timestamp using the
            <att>staff</att>, <att>layer</att> and <att>tstamp</att> attributes. Alternatively, the
            <att>startid</att> attribute may be used to identify a <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi> or <gi
            scheme="MEI">chord</gi> to which the mark should be assigned.</p>
        <p>The meaning of the mark is captured using the <att>dir</att> attribute, which provides
          the following values:</p>
        <list type="gloss">
          <label>down</label>
          <item> - depress the pedal</item>
          <label>up</label>
          <item> - release the pedal</item>
          <label>bounce</label>
          <item> - release, then immediately depress the pedal again</item>
          <label>half</label>
          <item> - depress the pedal half way</item>
        </list>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure>
  <!-- staves omitted -->
  <pedal staff="2" tstamp="1" dir="down"/>
</measure>
        </egXML>
      </div>

      <!--<div type="div4" xml:id="cmnOtherArtic">
        <!-\- TODO: Organ pedal marks? With artic.-\->
      </div>-->
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnOssia">
      <head>Ossia</head>
      <p>The term <term>ossia</term>, Italian for "or", denotes an alternative for a certain passage
        which is provided by the composer <emph>without any preference</emph> of one alternative
        over another. An ossia often provides a simpler (easier to perform) version of the original
        content. Another frequent use case for ossia is the provision of indications about
        performance practice, such as an alternative version with ornamentation written out in full.
        In all cases, it is up to the performer to choose between the alternatives.</p>
      <!-- TODO: Mention <choice> here as a set of alternatives provided by an editor? Address this in the editTrans chapter. -->
      <p>Most often an ossia is rendered above the main staff on a reduced-size staff. Sometimes,
        however, the alternate material occurs on the same staff as the primary text, but in a
        separate layer. In this case, the alternative material is usually rendered in small-sized
        notation on the normal-sized staff. For both situations, MEI offers the <gi scheme="MEI"
          >ossia</gi> element, which may be nested either inside <gi scheme="MEI">measure</gi> to
        reflect an ossia on a separate staff, or inside <gi scheme="MEI">staff</gi> to reflect an
        inline ossia in a separate layer. The following example demonstrates an ossia on a separate
        staff:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure>
  <staff n="1">
    <!-- first staff, without ossia -->
  </staff>
  <ossia>
    <staff>
      <!-- alternative content on reduced-size staff -->
    </staff>
    <staff n="2">
      <!-- original content on regular staff -->
    </staff>
  </ossia>
  <staff n="3">
    <!-- third staff, without ossia -->
  </staff>
</measure>
      </egXML>

      <p>The example above demonstrates that only one of the two <gi scheme="MEI">staff</gi>
        elements within <gi scheme="MEI">ossia</gi> has an <att>n</att> attribute. This mechanism
        allows one to distinguish between the "regular" and the "alternative" content: The one
        bearing the <att>n</att> attribute goes in line with the preceding measure's staff, the
        other one is printed in reduced size above. In this case, the vertical order of staves
        follows document order: The top-most staff is encoded as the first child, the lowest comes
        last. In combination with the presence of the <att>n</att> attribute, this allows the
        capture of multiple simultaneous ossia staves.</p>
      <p>All staves within <gi scheme="MEI">ossia</gi>, even the alternative ones without a direct
        reference, obey the definitions of the associated <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi>, which can
        be derived from the value of the <att>n</att> attribute. Alternatively, a separate <gi
          scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> may be given at the beginning of the contained <gi scheme="MEI"
          >layer</gi> element(s).</p>
      <p>In case of an inline ossia, the whole setup of elements moves down one step in the
        hierarchy, as seen in the following example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure>
  <staff n="1">
    <!-- content omitted -->
  </staff>
  <staff n="2">
    <ossia>
      <layer n="1">
        <!-- original content in regular layer -->
      </layer>
      <layer>
        <!-- alternative content in separate layer -->
      </layer>
    </ossia>
  </staff>
  <staff n="3">
    <!-- content omitted -->
  </staff>
</measure>
      </egXML>

      <!-- TODO: There's also the "naive encoder" version of ossia (where all staves are the same, 
        only the number of them changes). Or not, depending on whether the maximum number of staves
      is recorded or only the number of "active" ones. -->

    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnDir">
      <head>Directions and Rehearsal marks</head>
      <p>In CMN scores, there is often a large number of natural language instructions. Some of them
        concern the loudness and the speed of the performance, in which case MEI offers the elements
          <gi scheme="MEI">dynam</gi> (described at <ptr target="#cmnDynam"/>) and <gi scheme="MEI"
          >tempo</gi>. In other cases, however, they provide other instructions for the performer.
        Instead of providing separate elements for all possible types of such directions, MEI offers
        the generic <gi scheme="MEI">dir</gi> element. Although this element is not CMN specific (it
        is defined in <ptr target="#shared"/>), it is especially important in this repertoire.</p>
      <p>A tempo or character indication is often provided above the topmost staff of the first
        measure of a score, movement, or section. This indication, such as "Allegro moderato" or
        "Andante maestoso", may be regarded as a label. Though it is possible to label the movement,
        etc. using a <att>label</att> attribute attached to the enclosing structural entity (that
        is, on <gi scheme="MEI">mdiv</gi> or <gi scheme="MEI">section</gi>), it is often required to
        capture the exact position, spelling, or other features of the label as found in the
        underlying source material. In these cases, an element is necessary.</p>
      <p>Labels which address the tempo at which the music should be performed should be encoded
        using the <gi scheme="MEI">tempo</gi> element, which is a specialized form of <gi
          scheme="MEI">dir</gi>. <gi scheme="MEI">tempo</gi> is a member of the <ident type="class"
          >model.controleventLike</ident> class and as such occurs as a child of <gi scheme="MEI"
          >measure</gi>, following all <gi scheme="MEI">staff</gi> children. Its <att>staff</att>,
          <att>layer</att> and <att>tstamp</att> attributes are used to ensure correct semantic
        positioning, and <att>place</att> indicates a visual position with respect to the staff.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure n="1">
  <!-- all staves omitted -->
  <tempo staff="1" tstamp="1" place="above">Allegro moderato</tempo>
</measure>
      </egXML>

      <p><term>Rehearsal marks</term> are another specialized kind of directive. Consisting of
        letters, numbers, or a combination of both, rehearsal marks are used in scores and
        corresponding performer parts to identify convenient points to restart rehearsal after
        breaks or interruptions. For this reason, they are often visually emphasized by placing them
        within a square or circle. In MEI, they are encoded using the <gi scheme="MEI">reh</gi>
        element, which holds the textual content of the rehearsal mark. The visual rendition of the
        rehearsal mark, including the surrounding shape, may be captured using the <gi scheme="MEI"
          >rend</gi> element described in chapter <ptr target="#sharedTextRendition"/>.</p>
      <p>The following detail from an edition of Hector Berlioz' <title>Symphonie
          Fantastique</title> shows a typical example:</p>
      <figure>
        <head>Rehearsal mark</head>
        <graphic url="Images/modules/cmn/reh_berlioz.png" width="185px"/>
      </figure>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure>
  <staff n="1">
    <!-- content omitted -->
  </staff>
  <staff n="2">
    <!-- content omitted -->
  </staff>
  <staff n="3">
    <!-- content omitted -->
  </staff>
  <reh staff="1" place="above" tstamp="1">
    <rend rend="box">37</rend>
  </reh>
</measure>
      </egXML>

      <p>The following example demonstrates how rehearsal marks often apply to more than one staff.
        In this instance, the rehearsal mark is placed above staff 1 and below staves 7 and 11.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<measure>
  <reh staff="1" place="above" tstamp="1">A</reh>
  <reh staff="7 11" place="below" tstamp="1">A</reh>
</measure>
      </egXML>

    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnRep">
      <head>Repetition in CMN</head>
      <p>Repetition is a characteristic feature of music. Many musical forms rely on repetition
        (sometimes with modification) of distinct sections of the music. Repetition in this sense
        can be thought of as <soCalled>structural</soCalled>. At the same time, composers and
        engravers of music often use local symbols for repeating smaller portions of music instead
        of writing them in full more than once. In this case, the repetition is better defined as a
        species of abbreviation.</p>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="cmnRepStruct">
        <head>Structural Repetition</head>
        <p>Large-scale structural repetition, utilizing <gi scheme="MEI">section</gi> and <gi
            scheme="MEI">expansion</gi> elements, is discussed in section <ptr
            target="#sharedMdivContent"/>. This section will focus on repetition within sections.
          <!-- TODO: What needs to be handled here:            
            section and ending details 
            measure/@right="rptstart" etc.
          -->
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="cmnRepSym">
        <head>Measure-Level Repetition Symbols</head>
        <p>In addition to repetition at the section level, CMN includes a number of different
          symbols for measure-level repetitions. Many of these symbols are found in manuscripts and
          may be regarded as personal conventions of their respective authors. Some signs, however,
          have been widely adopted. For example, it is common to indicate the repetition of a single
          beat or an entire measure with one or more diagonal lines, sometimes with dots at the
          upper left and lower right, much like a percent sign. The illustration below contains the
          most common signs:</p>
        <figure>
          <head>Beat repeat signs</head>
          <graphic url="Images/ExampleImages/beatrpt-20100510.png" height="400px"/>
        </figure>
        <p>In general, MEI places primary emphasis on the capture of the semantic meaning of
          symbols, not their visual rendition. In this case, the focus is on the material being
          repeated, for example, a beat, a measure, a 2-measure fragment, etc. The following
          elements are provided for this purpose:</p>
        <p>
          <specList>
            <specDesc key="beatRpt"/>
            <specDesc key="halfmRpt"/>
            <specDesc key="mRpt"/>
            <specDesc key="mRpt2"/>
            <specDesc key="multiRpt"/>
          </specList>
        </p>

        <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">beatRpt</gi> element is used to represent a single repeated beat.
          Its visual rendition can be recorded using the <att>rend</att> attribute. This attribute
          indicates the number of slashes required to render the appropriate repeat symbol, which,
          as demonstrated in the preceding figure, depends on the rhythmic content of the beat being
          repeated. When a beat that consists of a single note or chord is repeated, the repetition
          sign is typically rendered as a single thick, slanting slash; therefore, the value '1'
          should be used. The following values should be used when the beat is divided into even
          notes: 4ths or 8ths=1, 16ths=2, 32nds=3, 64ths=4, 128ths=5. When the beat is comprised of
          mixed duration values, the symbol is always rendered as 2 slashes and 2 dots.</p>
        <p>In addition to its indication of a repeated beat, the beatRpt element is sometimes used
          in popular music notation, especially in guitar or percussion parts, to indicate a
          repeated rhythmic pattern. The <gi scheme="MEI">beatRpt</gi> element can be used, but when
          these parts require durations longer or shorter than a beat, note elements with
          appropriately-shaped note heads should be employed instead.</p>
        <!-- TODO:
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
          <!-\- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -\->
        </egXML>-->

        <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">mRpt</gi> element is available for repetition of an entire measure.
          Like <gi scheme="MEI">mRest</gi>, it must be the sole child of <gi scheme="MEI"
          >layer</gi>, no other events should be used. The <att>n</att> attribute of <gi
            scheme="MEI">mRpt</gi> should not be used to record the number displayed above the
          measure in the figure below. Instead, the numbering of repetitions of the written-out
          measure can be enabled using the <att>multi.number</att> attribute available on the <gi
            scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> elements.</p>
        <figure>
          <head>Measure repetition</head>
          <graphic url="Images/ExampleImages/mrpt-20100510.png" height="100px"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<measure>
  <staff>
    <layer>
      <beam>
        <note pname="f" oct="4" dur="8"/>
        <note pname="a" dur="16"/>
        <note pname="c" oct="5"/>
        <note pname="a" oct="4" dur="8"/>
      </beam>
      <beam>
        <note pname="c" oct="5" dur="8"/>
        <note pname="a" oct="4"/>
        <note pname="g"/>
      </beam>
    </layer>
  </staff>
</measure>
<measure>
  <staff>
    <layer>
      <mRpt/>
    </layer>
  </staff>
</measure>
<measure>
  <staff>
    <layer>
      <mRpt/>
    </layer>
  </staff>
</measure>
<measure>
  <staff>
    <layer>
      <mRpt/>
    </layer>
  </staff>
</measure>
        </egXML>

        <!-- TODO: Re: the halfmRpt, I have a kind of bad feeling. It seems arbitrary to have that, instead of a generic
          rptSnippet or so. I know that you invented it for my Waldstein example (or was it one of the others?), but it seems
          wrong. I'd prefer to specify the snippet to be repeated by a tstamp and dur combination, maybe also with a reference 
          to a measure in there. That would definitely be much more helpful than halfmRpt. Should we put this on the table and
          offer to deprecate halfmRpt? I know we have to keep it for now, but…
        -->

        <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">halfmRpt</gi> element represents the incorrect, but frequently
          found, use of the measure repeat (or similar) sign to indicate repetition of half of a
          measure. This practice mostly occurs in hand-written notation and usually involves the
          repetition of the second half of a measure in duple time. This element is necessary
          because the function of the symbol, not the visual symbol itself, is of primary
          importance. The following example from the beginning of Beethoven's
            <title>Waldstein</title> sonata illustrates such usage:</p>
        <figure>
          <head>Half-measure repeat</head>
          <graphic url="Images/modules/cmn/halfmRpt_beethoven.png" width="418px"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<measure>
  <staff n="1"><!-- omitted --></staff>
  <staff n="2">
    <layer n="1"><!-- omitted --></layer>
    <layer n="2">
      <chord dur="2" stem.mod="1slash">
        <note pname="g" oct="2"/>
        <note pname="b" oct="1"/>
      </chord>
      <halfmRpt/>
    </layer>
  </staff>
</measure>
<measure>
  <staff n="1"><!-- omitted --></staff>
  <staff n="2">
    <layer n="2">
      <halfmRpt/>
      <halfmRpt/>
    </layer>
  </staff>
</measure>
        </egXML>

        <p>As seen in the example above, it is possible to continuously repeat half measures, even
          across barlines.</p>
        <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">mRpt2</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">multiRpt</gi> elements (like the <gi
            scheme="MEI">multiRest</gi> element) never occur in scores, only in performer parts,
          where it is often necessary to abbreviate the notation due to page size limitations.</p>
        <figure>
          <head>Two-measure repetition</head>
          <graphic url="Images/ExampleImages/mrpt2-20100510.png" height="200px"/>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <head>Multi-measure repetition</head>
          <graphic url="Images/ExampleImages/multirpt-20100510.png" height="100px"/>
        </figure>

        <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">mRpt2</gi> element represents repetition of a 2-measure fragment,
          while <gi scheme="MEI">multiRpt</gi> is for repetition of fragments longer than two
          measures. In modern publishing practice, repeats of more than two measures are written out
          using repeat signs. This element is provided, however, for handling non-standard practices
          often found in manuscripts. The <att>num</att> attribute on <gi scheme="MEI">multiRpt</gi>
          records the number of preceding measures to be repeated.</p>
        <p>All elements described above allow for association of the sign with a symbol in a digital
          facsimile (via the <att>facs</att> attribute) and with a user-defined symbol (using
            <att>altsym</att>). See <ptr target="#facsimiles"/> and <ptr target="#userSymbols"/> for
          further details. In addition, the <att>expand</att> attribute is available on the
          foregoing elements to inform a rendering process whether to use the repeat symbol or the
          full content represented by it. A value of "true" indicates that the content should be
          displayed, while a "false" value means to show only the repeat symbol.</p>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <!--<div type="div2" xml:id="cmnOriginalContent">
    <head>Overview of the CMN Module</head>
    <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:</p>
    <!-\-<div type="div3" xml:id="cmnElements">
      <head>Elements</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="_arpeg"/>
          <specDesc key="_beam"/>
          <specDesc key="_beamSpan"/>
          <specDesc key="_beatRpt"/>
          <specDesc key="_bend"/>
          <specDesc key="_breath"/>
          <specDesc key="_bTrem"/>
          <specDesc key="_fermata"/>
          <specDesc key="_fTrem"/>
          <specDesc key="_hairpin"/>
          <specDesc key="_harpPedal"/>
          <specDesc key="_gliss"/>
          <specDesc key="_halfmRpt"/>
          <specDesc key="_measure"/>
          <specDesc key="_mRest"/>
          <specDesc key="_mRpt"/>
          <specDesc key="_mRpt2"/>
          <specDesc key="_mSpace"/>
          <specDesc key="_multiRest"/>
          <specDesc key="_multiRpt"/>
          <specDesc key="_octave"/>
          <specDesc key="_ossia"/>
          <specDesc key="_pedal"/>
          <specDesc key="_reh"/>
          <specDesc key="_slur"/>
          <specDesc key="_tie"/>
          <specDesc key="_tuplet"/>
          <specDesc key="_tupletSpan"/>
        </specList>
     </p>
    </div>-\->
    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnAttributeClasses">
      <head>Attribute Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="att.arpeg.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.arpeg.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.arpeg.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.arpeg.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beam.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beam.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beam.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beam.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beamed"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beamedwith"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beaming.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beamrend"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beamsecondary"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beamSpan.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beamSpan.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beamSpan.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beamSpan.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beatRpt.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beatRpt.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beatRpt.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.beatRpt.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.bend.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.bend.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.bend.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.bend.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.breath.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.breath.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.breath.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.breath.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.bTrem.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.bTrem.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.bTrem.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.bTrem.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.chord.ges.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.chord.log.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.chord.vis.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.cutout"/>
          <specDesc key="att.expandable"/>
          <specDesc key="att.fermata.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.fermata.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.fermata.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.fermata.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.fTrem.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.fTrem.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.fTrem.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.fTrem.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.gliss.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.gliss.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.gliss.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.gliss.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.graced"/>
          <specDesc key="att.hairpin.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.hairpin.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.hairpin.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.hairpin.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.halfmRpt.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.halfmRpt.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.halfmRpt.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.halfmRpt.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.harpPedal.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.harpPedal.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.harpPedal.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.harpPedal.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.layerDef.log.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.lvpresent"/>
          <specDesc key="att.measure.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mRest.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mRest.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mRest.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mRest.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mRpt.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mRpt.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mRpt.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mRpt.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mRpt2.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mRpt2.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mRpt2.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mRpt2.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mSpace.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mSpace.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mSpace.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mSpace.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.multiRest.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.multiRest.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.multiRest.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.multiRest.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.multiRpt.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.multiRpt.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.multiRpt.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.multiRpt.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.note.ges.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.note.log.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.note.vis.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.numbered"/>
          <specDesc key="att.numberplacement"/>
          <specDesc key="att.octave.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.octave.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.octave.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.octave.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.ornamentaccid"/>
          <specDesc key="att.ossia.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.ossia.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.ossia.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.ossia.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.pedal.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.pedal.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.pedal.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.pedal.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.phrase.vis.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.pianopedals"/>
          <specDesc key="att.reh.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.reh.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.reh.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.reh.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.rehearsal"/>
          <specDesc key="att.rest.log.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.rest.vis.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.scoreDef.log.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.scoreDef.vis.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.slur.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.slur.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.slur.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.slur.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.slurrend"/>
          <specDesc key="att.space.log.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.staffDef.log.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.staffDef.vis.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.stemmed.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="att.tie.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.tie.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.tie.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.tie.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.tierend"/>
          <specDesc key="att.tuplet.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.tuplet.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.tuplet.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.tuplet.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.tupletSpan.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.tupletSpan.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.tupletSpan.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.tupletSpan.vis"/>
        </specList>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnModelClasses">
      <head>Model Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="model.controleventLike.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="model.eventLike.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="model.eventLike.measureFilling"/>
          <specDesc key="model.layerPart.cmn"/>
          <specDesc key="model.measureLike"/>
          <specDesc key="model.measurePart"/>
          <specDesc key="model.ossiaLike"/>
          <specDesc key="model.sectionPart.cmn"/>
        </specList>
     </p>
    </div>
  </div>-->
</div>
