<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  © 2010 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs Unported License, 
  Version 3.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/.
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="cmnOrnaments" n="0">
  <head>Common Music Notation Ornaments</head>
  <p>This module includes elements and attributes for the encoding of ornaments typical of
      <soCalled>Common Music Notation</soCalled> (<term>CMN</term>). Ornaments are formulae of
    embellishment that can be realized by adding supplementary notes to one or more notes of the
    melody. In writte form, these are usually expressed as symbols written above or belove a note;
    though some other have a more complex written expression such as those that involve multiple
    notes and/or include grace notes to specify conluding turns or variations.</p> 
  <p>These symbols may
    have different resolutions depending on a large number of factors such as historical context,
    national boundaries, composer, scribe, etc. The elements here described, therefore, are not bound to a
    specific symbol; they are, instead, meant to encode the encoder's interpretation of a symbol and
    its position on the staff.</p>
  <p>Nonetheless, in order to establish a common ground, the guidelines suggest commonly accepted
    realizations for each type of symbol.</p>

  <p>Ornaments are typically encoded within a <gi>layer</gi> or within a <gi>measure</gi> and are
    connected to events on the staff via attributes. For example, an inverted mordent over a central
    C would be encoded in the following way:</p>
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <measure n="1">
      <staff n="1">
        <layer n="1">
          <note xml:id="n1" dur="4" oct="4" pname="c"/>
        </layer>
      </staff>
      <mordent form="inv" startid="n1"/>
    </measure>
  </egXML>
  <p>Alternatively or additionally, the relationship with a note can be expressed in terms of beats
    with the attribute <att>tstamp</att>. For example, assuming that the following measure is in
    2/2, the mordent would be related to the note on the first beat.</p>
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <measure n="1">
      <staff n="1">
        <layer n="1">
          <note dur="2" oct="4" pname="c"/>
          <note dur="2" oct="4" pname="c"/>
        </layer>
      </staff>
      <mordent form="inv" tstamp="1"/>
    </measure>
  </egXML>
  <p>The following sections will introduce each element in detail for all types of ornaments
    supported.</p>

  <div xml:id="cmnOrnamentsMordent" type="div2">
    <head>Mordents</head>
    <p> There are two common types of mordents: <soCalled>normal</soCalled> or
        <soCalled>lower</soCalled> mordent and <soCalled>inverted</soCalled> or
        <soCalled>upper</soCalled>mordent.</p>

    <p>The type is specified with the attribute <att>form</att>, which accepts the following values: <list>
        <label>norm</label>
        <item>
          <soCalled>normal</soCalled> mordent, corresponding to the symbol: <figure>
            <figDesc/>
            <graphic url="Images/modules/cmnOrnaments/lower_mordent.png"/>
          </figure>. It is commonly performed as the written note, followed by its lower neighbor,
          with a return to the written note. </item>
        <label>inv</label>
        <item>
          <soCalled>inverted</soCalled> mordent, corresponding to the symbol: <figure>
            <figDesc/>
            <graphic url="Images/modules/cmnOrnaments/upper_mordent.png"/>
          </figure> e.g., performed as the principal note, followed by its upper neighbor, with a
          return to the principal note. </item>
      </list>
    </p>

    <p> The resultions suggested above are to be considered default. It is possible, however, to
      override these defaults by describing a different resolution in the header using
        <gi>encodingDesc</gi>. Alternatively, resolutions can be defined case-by-case by encoding a
      specific resolution within the element <gi>mordent</gi>.</p>
    <p>For example, in the <title>Klavierbüchlein für Wilhelm Friedemann Bach</title> the symbol
      corresponding to what is here called an inverted mordent is called <emph>trillo</emph> and
      resolves in a series of notes beginning from </p>


    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnOrnamentsAttributeClasses">
      <head>Attribute Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="att.ornamentaccid"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mordent.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mordent.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mordent.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mordent.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.trill.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.trill.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.trill.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.trill.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.turn.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.turn.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.turn.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.turn.vis"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnOrnamentsElements">
      <head>Elements</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="mordent"/>
          <specDesc key="trill"/>
          <specDesc key="turn"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
  </div>

  <!--<div type="div2" xml:id="cmnOrnamentsOverview">
    <!-\- Overview -\->
    <head>Overview of the CMN Module</head>

    <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:</p>
    
    
    <div type="div3" xml:id="cmnOrnamentsModelClasses">
      <head>Model Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="model.ornamentLike.cmn"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
  </div>-->
</div>
