<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
  © 2012 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
  not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License
  at http://www.osedu.org/licenses/ECL-2.0.
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
  OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language
  governing permissions and limitations under the License.
  
  This is a derivative work based on earlier versions of the schema © 2001-2006 Perry Roland
  and the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia; licensed under the Educational
  Community License version 1.0.
  
  CONTACT: info@music-encoding.org
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="corpus" n="0">
  <head>Musical Corpora</head>
  <p>The term <term>corpus</term> may refer to any collection of musical data, although it is often
    reserved for collections which have been organized or collected with a particular end in view,
    generally to illustrate a particular characteristic of, or to demonstrate the variety found in,
    a group of related texts. The principal distinguishing characteristic of a corpus is that its
    components have been selected or structured according to some conscious set of design
    criteria.</p>
  <p>In MEI, a corpus is regarded as a composite text because, although each discrete document in a
    corpus clearly has a claim to be considered as a text in its own right, it is also regarded as a
    subdivision of some larger object, if only for convenience of analysis. In corpora, the
    component samples are clearly distinct texts, but the systematic collection, standardized
    preparation, and common markup of the corpus often make it useful to treat the entire corpus as
    a unit, too. Corpora share a number of characteristics with other types of composite texts,
    including anthologies and collections. Most notably, different components of composite texts may
    exhibit different structural properties, thus potentially requiring elements from different MEI
    modules.</p>
  <p>Aside from these high-level structural differences, and possibly differences of scale, the
    encoding of language corpora and the encoding of individual texts present identical sets of
    problems. Therefore, any of the encoding techniques and elements presented in other chapters of
    these Guidelines may therefore prove relevant to some aspect of corpus encoding and may be used
    in corpora.</p>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="corpusModuleOverview">
    <head>Corpus Module Overview</head>
    <p>The meiCorpus module defines a single element:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="meiCorpus"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">meiCorpus</gi> element is intended for the encoding of corpora, though
      it may also be useful in encoding any collection of disparate materials. The individual
      samples in the corpus are encoded as separate <gi scheme="MEI">mei</gi> elements, and the
      entire corpus is enclosed in an <gi scheme="MEI">meiCorpus</gi> element. Each sample has the
      usual structure for a <gi scheme="MEI">mei</gi> document, comprising an <gi scheme="MEI"
        >meiHead</gi> followed by a <gi scheme="MEI">music</gi> element. The corpus, too, has a
      corpus-level <gi scheme="MEI">meiHead</gi> element, in which the corpus as a whole, and
      encoding practices common to multiple samples may be described. The overall structure of an
      MEI-conformant corpus is thus:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<meiCorpus>
  <meiHead type="corpus"><!-- metadata for the corpus --></meiHead>
  <mei>
    <meiHead type="text"><!-- metadata for sample 1 --></meiHead>
    <music><!-- the encoding of sample 1 --></music>
  </mei>
  <mei>
    <meiHead type="text"><!-- metadata for sample 2 --></meiHead>
    <music><!-- the encoding of sample 2 --></music>
  </mei>
</meiCorpus>
    </egXML>
    <p>This two-level structure allows for metadata to be specified at the corpus level, at the
      individual text level, or at both. However, metadata which relates to the whole corpus rather
      than to its individual components should be removed from the individual component metadata and
      included only in the <gi scheme="MEI">meiHead</gi> element prefixed to the whole.</p>
    <p>In some cases, the design of a corpus is reflected in its internal structure. For example, a
      corpus of musical incipits might be arranged to combine all compositions of one type
      (symphonies, songs, chamber music, etc.) into some higher-level grouping, possibly with
      sub-groups for date of publication, instrumentation, key, etc. The <gi scheme="MEI"
        >meiCorpus</gi> element provides no support for reflecting such internal structure in the
      markup: it treats the corpus as an undifferentiated series of components, each tagged with an
        <gi scheme="MEI">mei</gi> element.</p>
    <p>If it is essential to reflect the organization of a corpus into sub-components, then the
      members of the corpus should be encoded as composite texts instead, using the <gi scheme="MEI"
        >group</gi> element described section <ptr target="#musicElement"/>. The mechanisms for
      corpus characterization described in this chapter, however, are designed to reduce the need to
      do this. Useful groupings of components may easily be expressed using the classification and
      identification elements described in section <ptr target="#workClass"/>, and those for
      associating declarations with corpus components described in section <ptr
        target="#associatingMetadataAndData"/>. These mechanisms also allow several different
      methods of text grouping to co-exist, each to be used as needed at different times. This helps
      minimize the danger of cross-classification and mis-classification of samples, and helps
      improve the flexibility with which parts of a corpus may be characterized for different
      applications.</p>
    <p>All composite texts share the characteristic that their different component texts may be of
      structurally similar or dissimilar types. If all component texts may all be encoded using the
      same module, then no problem arises. If however they require different modules, then the
      various modules must all be included in the schema. <!--This process is described in more detail in chapter <ptr target="#"/>.-->
      <!-- TODO: Add pointer to chapter on customization -->
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="corpusCombiningHeaders">
    <head>Combining Corpus and Text Headers</head>
    <p>An MEI-conformant document may have more than one header only in the case of a TEI corpus,
      which must have a header in its own right, as well as the obligatory header for each text.
      Every element specified in a corpus-header is understood as if it appeared within every text
      header in the corpus. An element specified in a text header but not in the corpus header
      supplements the specification for that text alone. If any element is specified in both corpus
      and text headers, the corpus header element is over-ridden for that text alone.</p>
    <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">titleStmt</gi> for a corpus text is understood to be prefixed by the <gi
        scheme="MEI">titleStmt</gi> given in the corpus header. All other optional elements of the
        <gi scheme="MEI">fileDesc</gi> should be omitted from an individual corpus text header
      unless they differ from those specified in the corpus header. All other header elements behave
      identically, in the manner documented in chapter <ptr target="#header"/>. This makes it
      possible to state information which is common to the whole of the corpus in the corpus header,
      while still allowing for individual texts to vary from this common metadata.</p>
    <p>For example, the following markup shows the structure of a corpus consisting of three texts,
      the first and last of which share the same encoding description. The second one has its own
      encoding description.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<meiCorpus>
  <meiHead>
    <fileDesc><!-- corpus file description--></fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <!-- default encoding description -->
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc><!-- corpus revision description --></revisionDesc>
  </meiHead>
  <mei>
    <meiHead>
      <fileDesc>
        <!-- file description for this corpus text -->
      </fileDesc>
    </meiHead>
    <music>
      <!-- first corpus text -->
    </music>
  </mei>
  <mei>
    <meiHead>
      <fileDesc>
        <!-- file description for this corpus text -->
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <!-- encoding description for this corpus text, over-riding the default  -->
      </encodingDesc>
    </meiHead>
    <music>
      <!-- second corpus text -->
    </music>
  </mei>
  <mei>
    <meiHead>
      <fileDesc>
        <!-- file description for third corpus text -->
      </fileDesc>
    </meiHead>
    <music>
      <!-- third corpus text -->
    </music>
  </mei>
</meiCorpus>
    </egXML>
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="corpusRecommendations">
    <head>Recommendations for the Encoding of Large Corpora</head>
    <p>These Guidelines include proposals for the identification and encoding of a far greater
      variety of textual features and characteristics than is likely to be either feasible or
      desirable in any one corpus, however large and ambitious. For most large-scale corpus
      projects, it will therefore be necessary to determine a subset of recommended elements
      appropriate to the anticipated needs of the
      project<!--, as further discussed in chapter <ptr
        target="#"/>--><!--TODO: add reference to chapter on customization -->;
      these mechanisms include the ability to exclude selected element types, add new element types,
      and change the names of existing elements.</p>
    <p>Because of the high cost of identifying and encoding many textual features, and the
      difficulty in ensuring consistent practice across very large corpora, encoders may find it
      convenient to divide the set of elements to be encoded into the following four categories:
        <list type="gloss">
        <label>required</label>
        <item> - texts included within the corpus will always encode textual features in this
          category, should they exist in the text</item>
        <label>recommended</label>
        <item> - textual features in this category will be encoded wherever economically and
          practically feasible; where present but not encoded, a note in the header should be
          made.</item>
        <label>optional</label>
        <item> - textual features in this category may or may not be encoded; no conclusion about
          the absence of such features can be inferred from the absence of the corresponding element
          in a given text.</item>
        <label>proscribed</label>
        <item> - textual features in this category are deliberately not encoded; they may be
          transcribed as unmarked up text, or represented as <gi scheme="MEI">gap</gi> elements, or
          silently omitted, as appropriate.</item>
      </list>
    </p>
  </div>

</div>
