<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
  © 2012 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
  not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License
  at http://www.osedu.org/licenses/ECL-2.0.
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
  OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language
  governing permissions and limitations under the License.
  
  This is a derivative work based on earlier versions of the schema © 2001-2006 Perry Roland
  and the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia; licensed under the Educational
  Community License version 1.0.
  
  CONTACT: info@music-encoding.org
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="editTrans" n="0">
  <head>Editorial Markup</head>
  <p>It is often necessary to render an account of any changes made to a musical text during its
    creation (and any subsequent editing) and to accommodate editorial comment necessitated by an
    editorial process. The elements and attributes described in this chapter may be used to record
    such editorial interventions, whether made by the composer, the copyists of the manuscript, the
    editor of a earlier edition used as a copy text, or the current encoder/editor.</p>
  <p>The scope of the elements described herein is therefore the description of features relating to
    the genesis, later revision and editorial interpretation of a text. Mechanisms for describing
    multiple sources are described in chapter <ptr target="#critApp"/> of these Guidelines.</p>
  <p>The elements described in this chapter may be contained by a wide range of other MEI elements
    and, in turn, may contain a variety of elements. The encoder must assume responsibility for the
    appropriateness of the markup; that is, a great many combinations of editorial and
    transcriptional markup are technically possible, but care must be taken to see that the encoding
    does not contravene the rationale of these Guidelines.</p>
  <p>For most of the elements discussed here, some encoders may wish to indicate both a
    responsibility; that is, a coded value indicating the person or agency responsible for making
    the editorial intervention in question, and an indication of the degree of certainty which the
    encoder wishes to associate with the intervention. Because these requirements are common to many
    of the elements discussed in this section, they are provided by an attribute class, <ident
      type="class">att.edit</ident>, to which these elements subscribe. Any of the elements
    discussed here thus may potentially carry the following optional attributes:</p>
  <p>
    <specList>
      <specDesc key="att.edit" atts="cert"/>
      <specDesc key="att.responsibility" atts="resp"/>
    </specList>
  </p>

  <!-- PR: OK, so what are the 2 ways?!  You say there are 2, but only describe 1. :) -->
  <p>Many of the elements discussed here can be used in two ways. Their primary purpose is to
    indicate that their content represents an editorial intervention (or, in some cases, the lack of
    intervention) of a specific kind. Sometimes, pairs or other meaningful groupings of such
    elements can be recorded, wrapped within the special purpose <gi>choice</gi> element:</p>
  <p>
    <specList>
      <specDesc key="choice"/>
    </specList>
  </p>
  <p>Wrapping elements this way enables the encoder to represent, for example, a text in its
      <soCalled>original</soCalled>, uncorrected form alongside the same text in one or more
      <soCalled>edited</soCalled> forms. Making use of this style of representation, software may
    dynamically switch between the Urtext <soCalled>view</soCalled> of the text and one or more
      <soCalled>views</soCalled> of the text after the application of the encoded editorial
    interventions.</p>
  <p>Elements which can be combined in this way constitute the <ident type="class"
      >model.choicePart</ident> class. The default members of this class are <gi>sic</gi>,
      <gi>corr</gi>, <gi>reg</gi>, <gi>orig</gi>, <gi>unclear</gi>, <gi>add</gi>, and <gi>del</gi>;
    their functions and usage are described in greater detail below.</p>
  <p>Three categories of editorial intervention are discussed by the remainder of this chapter:</p>
  <list type="simple">
    <item>indication or correction of apparent errors;</item>
    <item>indication of regularization of variant, irregular, non-standard, or eccentric forms;
      and</item>
    <item>editorial additions, suppressions, and omissions.</item>
  </list>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="abbreviations">
    <head>Abbreviations</head>
    <p>MEI offers methods for marking abbreviations. This includes abbreviations in text, as in the
      following example:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> ... the next passage shall be performed in
        <abbr>pno:</abbr> … </egXML>

    <p>or abbreviations in the music itself, as in the following example:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <abbr>
        <note pname="c" oct="5" dur="4" stem.mod="2slash"/>
      </abbr>
    </egXML>
    <!-- TODO: add btrem to this example and check for correctness -->

    <p>The type attribute may be used to classify the abbreviation according to a convenient
      typology. Sample values include:</p>
    <list type="gloss">
      <label>suspension - </label>
      <item>the abbreviation provides the first letter(s) of the word or phrase, omitting the
        remainder;</item>
      <label>contraction -</label>
      <item>the abbreviation omits some letter(s) in the middle;</item>
      <label>brevigraph - </label>
      <item>the abbreviation comprises a special symbol or mark;</item>
      <label>superscription - </label>
      <item>the abbreviation includes writing above the line;</item>
      <label>acronym - </label>
      <item>the abbreviation comprises the initial letters of the words of a phrase;</item>
      <label>title -</label>
      <item>the abbreviation is for a title of address (Dr, Ms, Mr, ...);</item>
      <label>organization - </label>
      <item>the abbreviation is for the name of an organization;</item>
      <label>geographic - </label>
      <item>the abbreviation is for a geographic name.</item>
    </list>

    <p>This tag is the mirror image of the <gi>expan</gi> tag (not to be confused with the
        <gi>expansion</gi> element described in <ptr target="#mdivContent"/>). Both <gi>abbr</gi>
      and <gi>expan</gi>allow the encoder to transcribe an abbreviation and its expansion. In the
      case of <gi>abbr</gi>, the original is transcribed as the content of the element and the
      expansion as an attribute value, while <gi>expan</gi> reverses this. The choice between the
      two is up to the user. For example:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <!-- using abbr -->
      <p>... the next passage shall be performed in <abbr expan="piano">pno:</abbr> ...</p>
      <!-- using expan -->
      <p>... the next passage shall be performed in <expan abbr="pno:">piano</expan> ...</p>
    </egXML>

    <p>The <gi>abbr</gi> tag is not required; if appropriate, the encoder may transcribe
      abbreviations in the source text silently, without tagging them. If abbreviations are not
      transcribed directly but expanded silently, then the MEI header should indicate this is the
      case. The <att>cert</att> attribute signifies the degree of certainty ascribed to the
      expansion of the abbreviation. The <att>expan</att> attribute gives an expansion of the
      abbreviation. The <att>resp</att> attribute contains an ID reference to an element containing
      the name of the editor or transcriber responsible for supplying the expansion of the
      abbreviation.</p>
    <p>When the content of the <att>abbr</att> or <att>expan</att> attributes requires additional
      markup, an attribute cannot be used. In this case, the abbreviated and expanded forms must be
      presented within elements. Furthermore, as alternatives to each other, the <gi>abbr</gi> and
        <gi>expan</gi> elements must be wrapped by the <gi>choice</gi> element, as described above.
      The previous example, where the 'o:' in 'pno:' is written as superscript, would be encoded
      as:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <p>... the next passage shall be performed in <choice>
          <abbr>pn<rend rend="sup">o:</rend></abbr>
          <expan>piano</expan>
        </choice>
      </p>
    </egXML>
  </div>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="edittransErrors">
    <head>Apparent Errors</head>
    <p>When the source material to be encoded is manifestly faulty, an encoder or transcriber may
      elect simply to correct it without comment, although for scholarly purposes it will often be
      more generally useful to record both the correction and the original state of the text. The
      elements described here enable all three approaches, and allows the last to be done is such a
      way as make it easy for software to present either the original or the correction.</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="sic"/>
        <specDesc key="corr"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>The following examples show alternative treatment of the same material. The text to be
      encoded contains a chord (c4, e4, g4, a4), where c4, e4, and a4 are quarter notes, but g4 is a
      half note.</p>
    <p>An encoder may choose to silently correct the engraver's error:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <chord>
        <note pname="c" dur="4" oct="4"/>
        <note pname="e" dur="4" oct="4"/>
        <note pname="g" dur="4" oct="4"/>
        <note pname="a" dur="4" oct="4"/>
      </chord>
    </egXML>

    <p>or the correction may be made explicit:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <chord>
        <note pname="c" dur="4" oct="4"/>
        <note pname="e" dur="4" oct="4"/>
        <corr>
          <note pname="g" dur="4" oct="4"/>
        </corr>
        <note pname="a" dur="2" oct="4"/>
      </chord>
    </egXML>

    <p>Alternatively, the encoder may simply record the typographic error without correcting it,
      either without comment or with a <gi>sic</gi> element to indicate the error is not a
      transcription error in the encoding:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <chord>
        <note pname="c" dur="4" oct="4"/>
        <note pname="e" dur="4" oct="4"/>
        <sic>
          <note pname="g" dur="2" oct="4"/>
        </sic>
        <note pname="a" dur="4" oct="4"/>
      </chord>
    </egXML>

    <p>If the encoder elects to record the original source text and provide a correction for the
      sake of transparency, both <gi>sic</gi> and <gi>corr</gi> may be used, wrapped in a
        <gi>choice</gi> element. The order of the <gi>sic</gi> and <gi>corr</gi> elements is not
      significant:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <chord>
        <note pname="c" dur="4" oct="4"/>
        <note pname="e" dur="4" oct="4"/>
        <choice>
          <sic>
            <note pname="g" dur="2" oct="4"/>
          </sic>
          <corr>
            <note pname="g" dur="4" oct="4"/>
          </corr>
        </choice>
        <note pname="a" dur="4" oct="4"/>
      </chord>
    </egXML>

    <p>An indication of the person or agency responsible for the emendation can be provided as
      follows:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <!-- … -->
      <chord>
        <note pname="c" dur="4" oct="4"/>
        <note pname="e" dur="4" oct="4"/>
        <choice>
          <sic>
            <note pname="g" dur="2" oct="4"/>
          </sic>
          <corr resp="#JK">
            <note pname="g" dur="4" oct="4"/>
          </corr>
        </choice>
        <note pname="a" dur="4" oct="4"/>
      </chord>
      <!-- within the header for this document: -->
      <respStmt>
        <name xml:id="editTrans.JK" role="editor">Johannes Kepper</name>
      </respStmt>
    </egXML>

    <p>Here the <att>resp</att> attribute has been used to indicate responsibility for the
      correction. Its value (<val>#editTrans.JK</val>) is an example of the <term>pointer</term>
      values discussed in section <ptr target="#ptrRef"/>. In this case, the <att>resp</att>
      attribute points to a <gi>name</gi> element within the metadata header, but any element might
      be indicated in this way, if the correction has been taken from some other source. The
        <att>resp</att> attribute is available for all elements which are members of the <ident
        type="class">att.responsibility</ident> class. The <ident type="class">att.edit</ident>
      class makes available a <att>cert</att> attribute,which may be used to indicate the degree of
      editorial confidence in a particular correction, as in the following example:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <chord>
        <note pname="c" dur="4" oct="4"/>
        <note pname="e" dur="4" oct="4"/>
        <choice>
          <sic>
            <note pname="g" dur="2" oct="4"/>
          </sic>
          <corr cert="high">
            <note pname="g" dur="4" oct="4"/>
          </corr>
        </choice>
        <note pname="a" dur="4" oct="4"/>
      </chord>
    </egXML>

    <p>Where, as here, the correction takes the form of amending information present in the text
      being encoded, the encoder should use the <gi>corr</gi> element. Where the correction is
      present in the text being encoded, and consists of some combination of visible additions and
      deletions, the elements <gi>add</gi> or <gi>del</gi> should be used. For additional
      information on the use of <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi>, see section <ptr
        target="#edittransAddDel"/> below. Where the correction takes the form of an addition of
      material not present in the original because of physical damage or illegibility, the
        <gi>supplied</gi> element may be used. Where the <soCalled>correction</soCalled> is simply a
      matter of expanding abbreviated notation, the <gi>expan</gi> element may be used.</p>
  </div>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="edittransReg">
    <head>Regularization and Normalization</head>
    <p>When the musical source makes extensive use of unusual symbol shapes or non-standard notation
      features, it may be desirable for a number of reasons to <term>regularize</term> it; that is,
      provide <soCalled>standard</soCalled> or <soCalled>regularized</soCalled> forms that are
      equivalent to the non-standard forms.</p>
    <p>As with other such changes to the source text, the changes may be made silently (in which
      case the MEI header should still specify the types of silent changes made) or may be
      explicitly marked using the following elements:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="reg"/>
        <specDesc key="orig"/>
        <specDesc key="choice"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>Consider this traditional soprano clef appearing somewhere in the course of a musical piece:
      <!-- TODO: graphic of simple C-Clef on second line… -->
    </p>
    <p>An encoder may choose to preserve this original clef, but flag it as nonstandard from the
      perspective of current practice by using the <gi>orig</gi> element with no attributes
      specified, as follows:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <orig>
        <clef shape="C" line="2"/>
      </orig>
    </egXML>

    <p>Alternatively, the encoder may indicate that the clef has been modernized into a G-clef by
      using the <gi>reg</gi> element with no attributes specified, as follows:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <reg>
        <clef shape="G" line="2"/>
      </reg>
    </egXML>

    <p>As another alternative, the encoder may encode both the old and modernized shapes, so that
      applications may render both at the reader's will:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <choice>
        <orig>
          <clef shape="C" line="2"/>
        </orig>
        <reg>
          <clef shape="G" line="2"/>
        </reg>
      </choice>
    </egXML>

    <p>As described above, the <att>resp</att> attribute may be used to specify the agent
      responsible for the regularization.</p>
  </div>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="edittransAddDelOmissions">
    <head>Additions, Deletions, and Omissions</head>
    <p>The following elements are used to indicate when single notational symbols have been omitted
      from, added to, or marked for deletion from, a musical text. Like the other editorial elements
      described in this chapter, they allow for a wide range of editorial practices:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="gap" atts="reason"/>
        <specDesc key="unclear" atts="reason"/>
        <specDesc key="add"/>
        <specDesc key="del"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="edittransOmission">
      <head>Omissions, Unclear Readings, Damage, and Supplied Readings</head>
      <p>Encoders may choose to omit parts of the source for reasons ranging from illegibility,
        (making transcription difficult or impossible), to editorial policy, e.g., systematic
        exclusion of poetry or prose from an encoding. The full details of the policy decisions
        concerned should be documented in the MEI header (see section <ptr
          target="#encodingDescription"/>). Each place in the text at which omission has taken place
        should be marked with a <gi>gap</gi> element, optionally with further information about the
        reason for the omission, its extent, and the person or agency responsible for it, as in the
        following examples:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <gap reason="illegible" unit="quarter" quantity="2"/>
      </egXML>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <gap reason="overwriting illegible" extent="several notes"/>
      </egXML>

      <p>Note that the extent of the gap may be marked precisely using attributes <att>unit</att>
        and <att>quantity</att>, or more descriptively using the <att>extent</att> attribute.</p>
      <p>Unlike TEI, MEI does not offer a <foreign>desc</foreign> element for further description of
        the reason for a gap. Instead, an <gi>annot</gi> may refer to the gap via its
          <att>startid</att>, <att>endid</att>, or <att>plist</att> attributes and provide
        additional information.</p>
      <p>The <gi>unclear</gi> element is used to mark passages in the original which cannot be read
        with confidence, or about which the transcriber is uncertain for other reasons, as for
        example when transcribing a illegible source. Its <att>reason</att> and <att>resp</att>
        attributes are used, as with the <gi>gap</gi> element, to indicate the cause of uncertainty
        and the person responsible for the conjectured reading.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <note pname="c" dur="4" oct="4">
          <unclear reason="ink blot">
            <artic artic="acc"/>
          </unclear>
        </note>
      </egXML>

      <p>Where the difficulty in transcription arises from an identifiable cause, the
          <att>agent</att> attribute signifies the causative agent. The <att>cert</att> attribute
        signifies the degree of certainty ascribed to the transcription of the text contained within
        the <gi>unclear</gi> element. Where the difficulty in transcription arises from action
        (partial deletion, etc.) assignable to an identifiable hand, the <att>hand</att> attribute
        may record the hand responsible for the action.</p>
      <p>When the reason for a gap in the encoding is damage of the document carrier (the paper on
        which the document is written, for example), the <gi>damage</gi> element should be used
        instead of the <gi>gap</gi> element. In the case of damage resulting from an identifiable
        cause, the <att>agent</att> attribute signifies the causative agent. The <att>degree</att>
        attribute signifies the degree of damage according to a convenient scale. A <gi>damage</gi>
        tag with this attribute should only be used where the text may be read with some confidence;
        data supplied from other sources should be tagged as <gi>supplied</gi>. The
          <att>extent</att> attribute indicates approximately how much text is in the damaged area,
        in notes, measures, inches, or any appropriate unit, where this cannot be deduced from the
        contents of the tag. For example, the damage may span structural divisions in the text so
        that the tag must then be empty of content. In the case of damage (deliberate defacement,
        etc.) assignable to an identifiable hand, the <att>hand</att> attribute signifies the hand
        responsible for the damage.</p>
      <p>Sometimes the editor provides information not present in the source material. These
        conjectures or emendations are marked up in MEI using the <gi>supplied</gi> element.</p>
      <p>The following example demonstrates the use of the <gi>supplied</gi> element in combination
        with <gi>choice</gi> and <gi>gap</gi>:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <beam>
          <note pname="c" oct="3" dur="4"/>
          <note pname="d" oct="3" dur="4"/>
          <choice>
            <gap extent="two eighth notes" reason="missing notes"/>
            <supplied>
              <note pname="e" oct="3" dur="4"/>
              <note pname="f" oct="3" dur="4"/>
            </supplied>
          </choice>
          <note pname="g" oct="3" dur="4"/>
          <note pname="a" oct="3" dur="4"/>
        </beam>
      </egXML>

      <p>When the presumed loss of text arises from an identifiable cause, <att>agent</att>
        signifies the causative agent. When the presumed loss of text arises from action (partial
        deletion, etc.) assignable to an identifiable hand, the <att>hand</att> attribute signifies
        the hand responsible for the action. The <att>reason</att> attribute indicates why the text
        has to be supplied, e.g. 'overbinding', 'faded ink', 'lost folio', 'omitted in original',
        etc. The <att>source</att> attribute contains the source of the supplied text. The editor(s)
        responsible for supplied material may be recorded in the <att>resp</att> attribute. The
        value of <att>resp</att> must point to one or more identifiers declared in the document
        header. The <att>cert</att> attribute signifies the degree of certainty ascribed to the
        supplied material.</p>
      <!-- TODO:
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <!-\- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -\->
      </egXML>-->
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="edittransAddDel">
      <head>Additions and Deletions</head>
      <p>The <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi> elements may be used to record where material has been
        added or deleted in the source material.</p>
      <p>The following example demonstrates the usage of <gi>add</gi> to mark up a note being added
        to an existing chord:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <chord>
          <note pname="c"/>
          <note pname="e"/>
          <note pname="g"/>
          <add>
            <note pname="b" accid="f"/>
          </add>
        </chord>
      </egXML>

      <p>The next example shows how <gi>del</gi> may be used to capture the information that two
        measures have been cancelled. As seen in this example, the <att>rend</att> attribute is used
        to specify the method of deletion.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <measure><!-- … --></measure>
        <measure><!-- … --></measure>
        <del rend="strikethrough">
          <measure><!-- … --></measure>
          <measure><!-- … --></measure>
        </del>
        <measure><!-- … --></measure>
      </egXML>

      <p>Additional information for both elements may be specified using attributes. Whereas the
          <att>hand</att> attribute marks responsibility for the textual change, the <att>resp</att>
        attribute is used to refer to the editor who identified this textual change as such. The
          <att>cert</att> attribute signifies the degree of certainty ascribed to the identification
        of the hand of the deletion or addition.</p>
      <p>The <gi>add</gi> element should not be used to mark editorial changes, such as supplying a
        note omitted by mistake from the source text or a passage present in another source. In
        these cases, either the <gi>corr</gi> or <gi>supplied</gi> tags should be used instead.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="edittransSubst">
      <head>Substitutions, Restorations, and Handshifts</head>
      <p>When several interventions to the musical text are to be regarded as a single action, they
        may be grouped using the <gi>subst</gi> element. The most common combination is a
        replacement of portions of the musical text using both the <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi>
        element, as seen in the following example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <layer>
          <!-- preceding content -->
          <subst>
            <del>
              <note pname="c" oct="4" dur="4"/>
            </del>
            <add>
              <beam>
                <note pname="c" oct="4" dur="8"/>
                <note pname="d" oct="4" dur="8"/>
              </beam>
            </add>
          </subst>
          <!-- subsequent content -->
        </layer>
      </egXML>

      <p>An intervention closely related to substitution is the restoration of a previously deleted
        section. For this purpose MEI offers the <gi>restore</gi> element, which may contain a
          <gi>del</gi> or other content directly.</p>
      <p>The following example illustrates an instance where a lyric which was cancelled and later
        restored by overwriting it:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <note pname="c" oct="4" dur="4">
          <syl>
            <restore desc="overwritten">
              <del>God</del>
            </restore>
          </syl>
        </note>
      </egXML>

      <p>The <att>desc</att> attribute gives a prose description of the means of restoration. The
          <att>cert</att> attribute signifies the degree of certainty ascribed to the identification
        of the hand of the restoration. The <att>type</att> attribute may be used to indicate the
        action cancelled by the restoration. The <att>resp</att> attribute contains an ID reference
        to an element containing the name of the editor or transcriber responsible for identifying
        the hand of the restoration. The <att>hand</att> attribute signifies the hand of the agent
        which made the restoration.</p>

      <!-- PR: I don't think this example is actually possible anymore. Note is not a member of att.crit
      or att.trans where @hand is provided. -->
      <!--<p>In the case of manuscripts created over time by multiple scribes, the encoder may want to
        assign scribal responsibility for passages in the source. Whereas the scribal hands may be
        identified and described in the MEI header (see section <ptr target="#header"/>), the
        musical content may refer to them using the <att>hand</att> attribute provided by the model
        class <ident type="class">att.handident</ident> in the Shared Module (see section <ptr
          target="#shared"/>). The following example illustrates how to assign a single note to a
        particular scribe:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <note pname="f" oct="5" dur="8" hand="#copyist1"/>
        <!-\- In document Header: -\->
        <handList>
          <hand xml:id="copyist1" medium="brown ink"/>
          <!-\- other hands… -\->
        </handList>
      </egXML>-->

      <p>MEI offers a <gi>handShift</gi> milestone element that can be used to mark a change of
        scribe or scribal style.</p>
      <p>The <att>character</att> attribute describes characteristics of the hand, particularly
        those related to the quality of the writing, e.g., 'shaky', 'thick', regular'. A description
        of the tint or type of ink, e.g., 'brown' or the writing medium, e.g., 'pencil', may be
        placed in the <att>medium</att> attribute.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <layer>
          <note/>
          <note/>
          <handShift medium="blue ink"/>
          <note/>
          <note/>
        </layer>
      </egXML>

      <p>The new hand may be identified using the <att>new</att> attribute, while the previous hand
        may be recorded in the <att>old</att> attribute. The <att>resp</att> attribute contains an
        ID reference to an element containing the name of the editor or transcriber responsible for
        identifying the change of hand. The <att>cert</att> attribute signifies the degree of
        certainty ascribed to the identification of the new hand.</p>

      <!-- PR: Is this true? model.editLike, of which handShift is a member, is allowed within and between
        measures. Therefore, handShifts could be indicated for an entire measure (when inside the measure)
        or for groups of measures (when between them), including any staves or layers contained therein. -->
      <p>When using this element within a layer, it is important to ensure that all layers and
        staves are considered. Every <gi>handShift</gi> affects only the content of its own layer
        and staff, even in the following measures. Therefore, there must be a separate
          <gi>handShift</gi> for every <gi>staff</gi> and <gi>layer</gi>. This mechanism allows the
        description of shifts at timestamps that differ between each staff.
        <!-- TODO: It seems like slur is not memberOf key="att.handident", which seems to me to be a clear bug -->
      </p>
    </div>

  </div>
</div>
