<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  © 2010 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs Unported License, 
  Version 3.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/.
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="facsimile" n="0">
  <head>Facsimiles</head>
  <p>This chapter describes the usage of the facsimile module its elements and attributes.
  Facsimiles contain a representation of some written source in the form of a set of images, 
  so the chapter defines a module 
  intended for use in the representation of sources.
  The following paragraphs recommend the usage of the allowed elements and attributes in a MEI file and
  discusses the way of encoding transcription of such material. This module seems to be useful for the encoding
  of critical editions, but therefore it is recommend to use the elements of the critapp module.
  In this section elements and attributes will be presented, designed to support various possibilities in this module and
  discuss the associated mechanisms provided by theses Guidelines.
  <div type="div2" xml:id="facsimileOverview">
    <!-- Overview -->
    <head>Overview of the facsimile Module</head>
    <p>The module includes elements and attributes for encoding facsimiles which are in the simplest way a 
    collection of images with some metadata. </p>
    <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:
    </p>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="facsimileElements">
      <head>Elements in the facsimile module</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="facsimile"/>
          <specDesc key="surface"/>
          <specDesc key="zone"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>
        The facsimile module adds a separate subtree to MEI, starting as child of the 
        <gi>music</gi> element and preceding sibling to the <gi>body</gi>.
         The following example shows how to add a <gi>facsimile</gi> to MEI in the simplest form.
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <mei>
            <meiHead/>
            <music>
              <facsimile>
                …
              </facsimile>
              <body>
                …
              </body>
            </music>
          </mei>
        </egXML>
        The next example illustrates the use of the <att>decls</att> attribute which is to be used to link the 
        collection of images with a particular source described in the header.
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <mei>
            <meiHead>
              <!-- defined source -->
            </meiHead>
            <music>
              <facsimile decls="#defined source"/>
              <body/>
            </music>
          </mei>
        </egXML>
      </p>
       <!--<head>Surface</head>-->
      <p> The surface element defines a written surface as a two-dimensional coordinate space 
        on some physical surface forming part of the source material such as a piece of paper 
        or anything else, optionally grouping one or more graphic representations
        of that space and zones. A surface establishes a coordinate system which may be used to 
        address parts or the whole of some digital representation of a written surface.
        To define coordinates it is recommend to use the specific attributes 
      which are part of the att.coordinated.class. illustrated in the following example. The 
      @ulx, @uly, @lrx and the @lry (...). The startid attribute may be used to hold a reference to the first
      feature occurring on this surface. The surface element is modelled on an element in the 
      Text Encoding Initiative (TEI).
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <facsimile>
          <surface startid="#xy"/>
          <surface lrx="123" lry="456" ulx="78" uly="910"/>
        </facsimile>
        </egXML>
        The surface element may however contain graphic representations of zones and indicates the location of an inline graphic
        illustration, or figure. For further information please read the chapter (X).
      </p>
      <p>
        The following example illustrates the usage of the <gi>graphic</gi> element within a surface element.
        It is also possible to encode more than one graphic in a facsimile. 
      </p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <facsimile>
          <surface xml:id="page1">
            <graphic/>
            <graphic/>
            <zone/>
            <zone/>
          </surface>
          <surface xml:id="page2">
            <graphic/>
            <zone/>
            <zone/>
          </surface>
        </facsimile>
      </egXML>
      <p>
        The example shows the graphic element within a surface element which indicates the location of an illustration. The graphic element is member of 
        the figtable Module, so please read that chapter for further information about the graphic element and its usage in a MEI file.
      </p>
      <!--<head>Zone</head>-->
      <p>A zone, by contrast to the surface element, defines any arbitrary area of interest relative to that surface, using the same coordinate system
        and defines a rectangular area within a surface element. 
        The position of every zone for a given surface is always defined by reference to the coordinate system defined for that surface.
        <!-- is only permitted within the surface element -->
     <!-- A graphic element contained by a zone represents the whole of the zone.-->
      The example shows...
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <facsimile>
          <surface>
            <zone xml:id="zone3" ulx="10" uly="10" lrx="100" lry="100"/>
            <zone/>
            <zone/>
          </surface>
        </facsimile>
      </egXML>
      The zone element may be enriched by some attributes similar to those allowed on surface
      and may contain the graphic and the figDesc element.
      The zone element makes it possible to describe and define any region of interest, such a detail or a illustration.
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <facsimile>
          <surface>
            <zone >
              <graphic/>
            </zone>
          </surface>
        </facsimile>
      </egXML>
      </p>
     <!--<head>Attributes</head>-->
      <p>
        <!-- The facs attribute associate a feature corresponding with all or part of an image -->
        The <att>facs</att> attribute permits the current element to reference a facsimile image or zone which corresponds to it.
        The following examples show how to use the attributes on several elements.
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <measure>
          <!-- … -->
        </measure>
        <pb facs="#page2"/>
        <measure facs="#zone3">
          <!-- … -->
        </measure>
      </egXML>
        This example illustrates the <att>facs</att> on the <gi>pb</gi> element to associate an image with an appropriate point in the encoding. 
        The image indicated by the <att>facs</att> attribute represents the whole of the music following the <gi>pb</gi> element.
        The second measure including the <att>facs</att> indicates the belonging
      to a zone withe the ID "zone3" defined elsewhere in the document.</p> 
      <p>
        The next example shows a note including the <att>facs</att> attribute (...)
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
       <staff>
         <layer> 
           <note facs="#zoneXY">
           </note>
         </layer>
       </staff>
      </egXML>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="facsimileAttributeClasses">
      <head>Attribute Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="att.facsimile"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="facsimileModelClasses">
      <head>Model Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="model.facsimileLike"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
