<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  © 2010 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs Unported License, 
  Version 3.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/.
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="figTable" n="0">
  <head>Figures and Tables</head>
  <p>Apart from music and text, musical documents, both historical and contemporary, may also
    contain material in graphical or tabular format. In such materials, details of layout and
    presentation may also be of comparatively greater significance or complexity than they are for
    running text. Although some types of images can be represented directly with markup, it is more
    common practice to include such information by using a reference to an external entity
    (typically a URL) encoded in a suitable graphical notation.</p>
  <p>The module defined by this chapter defines special purpose ‘container’ elements that can be
    used to encapsulate occurrences of such data within an MEI-conformant document in a portable
    way. Specific recommendations for the encoding of figures, figure descriptions and graphics as
    well as tables with their sub-elements <gi>tr</gi>, <gi>td</gi> and <gi>th</gi> are provided in
    at the beginnig of this chapter. As there exists a wide variety of different graphic formats, a
    short list of formats that are widely used at the present time, is given in section <ptr
      target="#graphic"/>. Each one includes a very brief description. The chapter closes with
    attribute and model classes which are defined by the module.</p>
  <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:</p>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="figtableElements">
    <head>Elements</head>
    <div type="div3">
      <head>figure (fig)</head>
      <p> The figure element groups elements representing or containing graphic information such as
        an illustration or figure. This element is modelled on the figure element in the Text
        Encoding Initiative (TEI). The figure element is used to contain images, captions, and
        textual descriptions of the pictures. The images themselves are specified using the graphic
        element, whose @url attribute provides the location of an image. For example: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <figure>
            <graphic url="../samples/snippets/mei2012-30shortexamples/beam-grace/grace-300.png"
              width="500px"/>
          </figure>
        </egXML> Three kinds of content may be supplied inside a figure element: the element head
        may be used to transcribe (or supply) a descriptive heading or title for the graphic itself
        as in this example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <figure>
            <head>Grace notes</head>
            <graphic url="../samples/snippets/mei2012-30shortexamples/beam-grace/grace-300.png"
              width="500px"/>
          </figure>
        </egXML> Figures are often accompanied not only by a title or heading, but by a paragraph or
        so of commentary or caption. One or more p elements may be used to transcribe any caption or
        discussion of the figure in the source: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <figure>
            <head>Grace notes</head>
            <figDesc>The example shows grace notes within beams</figDesc>
            <graphic url="../samples/snippets/mei2012-30shortexamples/beam-grace/grace-300.png"
              width="500px"/>
          </figure>
        </egXML> 
      </p>
    </div>
    
    <div type="div3">
      <head>figDesc</head>
      <p>The figure description (<gi>figdesc</gi>) element contains a brief prose description of the
        appearance or content of a graphic figure, for use when documenting an image without
        displaying it. Best practice suggests the use of controlled covabulary. Don't confuse this
        element with a figure caption. A caption is text primarily intended for display with an
        illustration. It may or may not function as a description of the illustration.</p>
      <p>This element is intended for use as an alternative to the content of its parent
          <gi>figure</gi> element; for example, to display when the image is required but the
        equipment in use display graphic images. It may also be used for indexing or documentary
        purposes. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <figure>
            <graphic url="emblem1.png"/>
            <head>Emblemi d'Amore</head>
            <figDesc>A pair of naked winged cupids, each holding a flaming torch, in a rural
              setting.</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </egXML>
      </p>
    </div>
    
    <div type="div3">
      <head>graphic</head>
      <p>The graphic element indicates the location of an inline graphic, illustration, or figure.
        As noted above, there exists a wide variety of different graphics formats, and the following
        list is in no way exhaustive. Moreover, inclusion of any format in this list should not be
        taken as indicating endorsement by the MEI of this format or any profucts associated with
        it. Some of the formats listed here are proprietary to a greater or lesser extent and cannot
        therefore be regarded as standards in any meaningful sense. They are however widely used by
        many different vendors. The following formats are widely used at the present time, and
        likely to remain supported by more than one vendor's software: <list>
          <item>BMP: Microsoft bitmap format</item>
          <item>CGM: Computer Graphics Metafile</item>
          <item>GIF: Graphics Interchange Format</item>
          <item>JPEG: Joint Photographic Expert Group</item>
          <item>PBM: Portable Bit Map</item>
          <item>PCX: IBM PC raster format</item>
          <item>PICT: Macintosh drawing format</item>
          <item>PNG: Portable Network Graphics format</item>
          <item>Photo-CD: Kodak Photo Compact Disk format</item>
          <item>QuickTime: Apple real-time image system</item>
          <item>SMIL: Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language format</item>
          <item>SVG: Scalable Vector Graphics format</item>
          <item>TIFF: Tagged Image File Format</item>
        </list> Brief descriptions of all the above are given below. Where possible, current
        addresses or other contact information are shown for the originator of each format. Many
        formal standards, especially those promulgated by ISO and many related national
        organizations (ANSI, DIN, BSI, and many more), are available from those national
        organizations. Addresses may be found in any standard organizational directory for the
        country in question.</p>

      <div type="div4" xml:id="VectorGraphicFormats">
        <head>Vector Graphic Formats</head>
        <p>
          <list>
            <label>CGM: Computer Graphics Metafile</label>
            <item>This vector graphics format is specified by an ISO standard, ISO 8632:1987,
              amended in 1990. It defines binary, character, and plain-text encodings; the
              non-binary forms are safer for blind interchange, especially over networks.
              Documentation on CGM is available from ISO and from its member national bodies such as
              AFNOR, ANSI, BSI, DIN, JIS, etc.</item>
            <label>SVG: Scalable Vector Graphics format</label>
            <item>SVG is a language for describing two-dimensional vector and mixed vector or raster
              graphics in XML. It is defined by the Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) 1.0
              Specification, W3C Recommendation, 04 September 2001, and is available at <ref
                target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2001/REC-SVG-20010904/"/></item>
            <label>PICT: Macintosh drawing format</label>
            <item>This format is universally supported on Macintosh (tm) systems, and readable by a
              limited range of software for other systems. Documentation is available from Apple
              Computer Company, Cupertino, California USA.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="RasterGraphicFormats">
        <head>Raster Graphic Formats</head>
        <p>
          <list>
            <label>PNG: Portable Network Graphics format</label>
            <item>PNG is a non-proprietary raster format currently widely available. It provides an
              extensible file format for the lossless, portable, well-compressed storage of raster
              images. Indexed-color, grayscale, and truecolor images are supported, plus an optional
              alpha channel. Sample depths range from 1 to 16 bits. It is defined by IETF RFC 2083,
              March 1997. </item>
            <label>TIFF: Tagged Image File Format</label>
            <item>Currently the most widely supported raster image format, especially for black and
              white images, TIFF is also one of the few formats commonly supported on more than one
              operating system. The drawback to TIFF is that it actually is a wrapper for several
              formats, and some TIFF-supporting software does not support all variants. TIFF files
              may use LZW, CCITT Group 4, or PackBits compression methods, or may use no compression
              at all. Also, TIFF files may be monochrome, greyscale, or polychromatic. All such
              options should be specified in prose at the end of the encodingDesc section of the TEI
              header for any document including TIFF images. TIFF is owned by Aldus Corporation.
              Documentation on TIFF is available from them at Craigcook Castle, Craigcook Road,
              Edinburgh EH4 3UH, Scotland, or 411 First Avenue South, Seattle, Washington 98104
              USA.</item>
            <label>GIF: Graphics Interchange Format</label>
            <item>Raster images are widely available in this form, which was created by CompuServe
              Information Services, but has by now been implemented for many other systems as well.
              Documentation on GIF is copyright by, and is available from, CompuServe Incorporated,
              Graphics Technology Department, 5000 Arlington Center Boulevard, Columbus, Ohio 43220
              USA. </item>
            <label>PBM: Portable Bit Map</label>
            <item>PBM files are easy to process, eschewing all compression in favor of transparency
              of file format. PBM files can, of course, be compressed by generic file-compression
              tools for storage and transfer. Public domain software exists which will convert many
              other formats to and from PBM. Documentation on PBM is copyright by Jeff Poskanzer,
              and is available widely on the Internet.</item>
            <label>PCX: IBM PC raster format</label>
            <item>This format is used by most IBM PC paint programs, and supports both monochrome
              and polychromatic images. Documentation is available from ZSoft Corporation, Technical
              Support Department, ATTN: Technical Reference Manual, 450 Franklin Rd. Suite 100,
              Marietta, GA 30067 USA.</item>
            <label>BMP: Microsoft bitmap format</label>
            <item>This format is the standard raster format for computer using Microsoft Windows
              (tm) or Presentation Manager (tm). Documentation is available from Microsoft
              Corporation. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="PhotographicAndMotionVideoFormats">
        <head>Photographic and Motion Video Formats</head>
        <p>
          <list>
            <label>JPEG: Joint Photographic Experts Group</label>
            <item>This standard is sponsored by CCITT and by ISO. It is ISO/IEC Draft International
              Standard 10918-1, and CCITT T.81. It handles monochrome and polychromatic images with
              a variety of compression techniques. JPEG per se, like CCITT Group IV, must be
              encapsulated before transmission; this can be done via TIFF, or via the JPEG File
              Interchange Format (JFIF), as commonly done for Internet delivery.</item>
            <!-- <label>QuickTime: Apple real-time image system</label>
            <item>QuickTime is a proprietary method introduced by Apple Computer Company to
              synchronize the display of various data. The data can include frames of video, sound,
              lighting control mechanisms, and other things. Viewers for QuickTime productions are
              available for Apple and other computers. Further information is available from Apple
              Computer Incorporated, 10201 North de Anza Boulevard MS 23AQ, Cupertino, California
              95014 USA.</item>-->
            <label>Photo-CD: Kodak Photo Compact Disk format</label>
            <item>This format was introduced by Kodak for rasterizing photographs and storing them
              on CD-ROMs (about one hundred 35mm file images fit on one disk), for display on
              televisions or CD-I systems. Information on Photo-CD is available from Kodak Limited,
              Research and Development, Headstone Drive, Harrow, Middlesex HA1 4TY, UK.</item>
            <!--<label>SMIL: Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language format</label>
            <item>SMIL is a W3C Recommendation which supports the integration of independent
              multimedia objects into a synchronized multimedia presentation. It provides multimedia
              authors with easily-defined basic timing relationships, fine-tuned synchronization,
              spatial layout, direct inclusion of non-text and non-image media objects, hyperlink
              support for time-based media, adaptiveness to varying user and system characteristics.
              SMIL 1.0 (<ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-smil/"/>) became a W3C Recommendation
              on June 15, 1998, and was further developed in SMIL 2.0. SMIL 2.0 adds native support
              for transitions, animation, event-based interaction, extended layout facilities, and
              more sophisticated timing and synchronization primitives to the SMIL 1.0 language. It
              also allows reuse of SMIL syntax and semantics in other XML-based languages, in
              particular those who need to represent timing and synchronization. For example, SMIL
              2.0 components are used for integrating timing into XHTML Document Types and into SVG.
              SMIL 2.0 also provides recommendations for Document Types based on SMIL 2.0 Modules
                (<ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/smil20/smil-modules.html"/>). One such Document
              Type is the SMIL 2.0 Language Profile (<ref
                target="http://www.w3.org/TR/smil20/smil20-profile.html"/>). It contains support for
              all of the major SMIL 2.0 features including animation, content control, layout,
              linking, media object, meta-information, structure, timing, and transition effects and
              is designed for Web clients that support direct playback from SMIL 2.0 markup. SMIL
              2.0 (<ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/smil20/"/>) became a W3C Recommendation on
              August 7, 2001, becoming the first vocabulary to provide XML Schema support and to
              have reached such status.</item>-->
          </list> As noted above, the reader will encounter many, many other graphics formats.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="div3">
        <head>table</head>
        <p>The element <gi>table</gi> contains text displayed in tabular form, in rows and columns.
          A table is the least 'graphic' of the elements discussed in this chapter. Almost any text
          structure can be presented as a series of rows and columns: one might, for example, choose
          to show a glossary or other form of list in tabular form, without necessarily regarding it
          as a table. When tabular presentation is regarded as of less intrinsic importance, it is
          correspondingly simpler to encode descriptive or functional information about the contents
          of the table, for example to identify one cell as containing a name and another as
          containig a date, though the two methods may be combined. </p>
        <p>The <gi>table</gi> element is defined as a member of the class xy
          <!--TODO: add class name-->; it may therefore appear both within other components (such as
          paragraphs), or between them, provided that the module defined in this chapter has been
          enabled. It is to a large extent arbitrary whether a table should be regarded as a series
          of rows or as a series of columns. For compatibility with currently available systems,
          however, these Guidelines require a row-by-row description of a table. It is also possible
          to describe a table simply as a series of cells; this may be useful for tabular material
          which is not presented as a simple matrix.</p>
        <p>The element <gi>tr</gi> contains one row of a table. For tables, rows and columns are
          always given in top-to-bottom, left-to-right order, although formatting properties such as
          those provided by CSS may be used to specify that they should be displayed
          differently.</p>
      </div>

      <div type="div3">
        <head>td</head>
        <p>The <gi>td</gi> element designates a table cell that contains data as opposed to a cell
          that contains column or row heading information. The <att>colspan</att> and
            <att>rowspan</att> attributes tabular display rendering information. They indicate that
          a particular cell or row of a table spans more than one row or column. <egXML
            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <table>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2" rowspan="2">unmittelbares Schlagen</td>
                <td colspan="2" rowspan="2">mittelbares Schlagen</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Gegenschlag</td>
                <td>Aufschlag</td>
                <td>Schütteln</td>
                <td>Schrapen</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>1. Stäbe</td>
                <td>1. Stäbe</td>
                <td>1. Rahmen</td>
                <td>1. Raspeln</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>2. Platten</td>
                <td>2. Röhren</td>
                <td>2. Gefäße</td>
                <td>2. Räder</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td>3. Platten</td>
                <td>3. Reihen</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td>4. Gefäße</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
            </table>
          </egXML></p>
      </div>

      <div type="div3">
        <head>th</head>
        <p>The <gi>th</gi> element designates a table cell containing column or row heading
          information as opposed to one containing data. The <att>colspan</att> and
            <att>rowspan</att> attributes tabular display rendering information. They indicate that
          a particular cell or row of a table spans more than one row or column. <egXML
            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <table>
              <tr>
                <th colspan="4">Systematische Einteilung der Idiophone</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2">unmittelbares Schlagen</td>
                <td colspan="2">mittelbares Schlagen</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Gegenschlag</td>
                <td>Aufschlag</td>
                <td>Schütteln</td>
                <td>Schrapen</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>1. Stäbe</td>
                <td>1. Stäbe</td>
                <td>1. Rahmen</td>
                <td>1. Raspeln</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>2. Platten</td>
                <td>2. Röhren</td>
                <td>2. Gefäße</td>
                <td>2. Räder</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td>3. Platten</td>
                <td>3. Reihen</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td>4. Gefäße</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
            </table>
          </egXML>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div type="div3">
        <head>tr</head>
        <p>The <gi>tr</gi> element is a formatting element that contains one or more <gi>td</gi> or
            <gi>th</gi> elements (cells) in a <gi>table</gi>. A cell is the intersection of a row
          and a column. The precise rendition of the table and its cells should be specified in a
          style steet. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <table>
              <tr>
                <th colspan="7">Besetzungen der Triosonate und ihrer Nachfolger</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <td>Triosonate<lb/>Standardbes.</td>
                <td>Triosonate für<lb/>Orgel (Bach)</td>
                <td>Sonate mit obl.<lb/>Cembalo (Bach)</td>
                <td>Klaviertrio</td>
                <td>Streichquartett</td>
                <td>Streichtrio</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>1. Oberstimme</td>
                <td>1. Violine</td>
                <td>Orgel r.H.</td>
                <td>Violine<lb/>(Flöte, Gambe)</td>
                <td>Violine</td>
                <td>1. Violine</td>
                <td>1. Violine</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>2. Oberstimme</td>
                <td>2. Violine</td>
                <td>Orgel l.H.</td>
                <td>Cembalo r.H.</td>
                <td>Klavier r.H.</td>
                <td>2. Violine</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>harmonische Füllung</td>
                <td>Cembalo r.H.</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
                <td/>
                <td>Bratsche</td>
                <td>Bratsche</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Bass-Stimme</td>
                <td>Cello</td>
                <td>Orgel Pedal</td>
                <td>Cello</td>
                <td>Cello</td>
                <td>Cello</td>
                <td>Cello</td>
              </tr>
            </table>
          </egXML>
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div type="div2" xml:id="figtableAttributeClasses">
      <head>Attribute Classes</head>
      <p>The module figTable defines the following attribute class: <specList>
          <specDesc key="att.tabular"/>
        </specList> The attribute class att.tabular groups attributes shared by table cells. </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div2" xml:id="figtableModelClasses">
      <head>Model Classes</head>
      <div type="div3" xml:id="modelFigDescLike">
        <head>model.figDescLike</head>
        <p>The model class model.figDescLike groups elements that provide a brief prose description
          of the appearance or content of a graphic figure.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="div3" xml:id="modelFigureLike">
        <head>model.figureLike</head>
        <p>The model class model.figureLike groups elements representing or containing graphic
          information such as an illustration or figure.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="div3" xml:id="modelGraphicLike">
        <head>model.graphicLike</head>
        <p>The model class model.graphicLike groups elements that indicate the location of an inline
          graphic, illustration, or figure.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="div3" xml:id="modelTableLike">
        <head>model.tableLike</head>
        <p>The model class model.tableLike groups table-like elements.</p>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
