<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
  © 2012 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
  not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License
  at http://www.osedu.org/licenses/ECL-2.0.
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
  OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language
  governing permissions and limitations under the License.
  
  This is a derivative work based on earlier versions of the schema © 2001-2006 Perry Roland
  and the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia; licensed under the Educational
  Community License version 1.0.
  
  CONTACT: info@music-encoding.org
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="figTable" n="0">
  <head>Figures and Tables</head>
  <p>Apart from music and text, musical documents, both historical and contemporary, may also
    contain material in graphical or tabular format. In such materials, details of layout and
    presentation may also be of comparatively greater significance or complexity than they are for
    running text. Although some types of graphical material can be represented directly with markup,
    it is more common practice to include such information by using a reference to an external
    entity (typically a URL) encoded in a suitable graphical format.</p>
  <p>The module defined by this chapter defines special purpose <soCalled>container</soCalled>
    elements that can be used to encapsulate occurrences of such data within an MEI-conformant
    document in a portable way. Specific recommendations for the encoding of figures, figure
    descriptions and graphics as well as tables with their sub-elements <gi>tr</gi>, <gi>td</gi> and
      <gi>th</gi> are provided at the beginnig of this chapter. As there exists a wide variety of
    different graphic formats, a short list of formats that are widely used at the present time, is
    given in section <ptr target="#figtableImages"/>. Each one includes a very brief description.
    The chapter closes with attribute and model classes which are defined by the module.</p>
  <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:</p>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="figures">
    <head>Figures</head>
    <p> The <gi>fig</gi> element groups elements representing or containing graphic information such
      as an illustration or figure. This element is modelled on the figure element in the Text
      Encoding Initiative (TEI). The <gi>fig</gi> element is used to contain images, captions, and
      textual descriptions of the pictures. The images themselves are specified using the
        <gi>graphic</gi> element, whose <att>target</att> attribute provides the location of an
      image. For example:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <fig>
        <graphic target="../samples/snippets/mei2012-30shortexamples/beam-grace/grace-300.png"/>
      </fig>
    </egXML>
    <p>The graphic element may occur multiple times within the markup of the figure in order to
      indicate the availablity of different image formats or resolutions:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <fig>
        <graphic target="../samples/snippets/mei2012-30shortexamples/beam-grace/grace-72.png"/>
        <graphic target="../samples/snippets/mei2012-30shortexamples/beam-grace/grace-300.png"/>
        <graphic target="../samples/snippets/mei2012-30shortexamples/beam-grace/grace-600.png"/>
      </fig>
    </egXML>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="figureCaptionsDescriptions">
      <head>Figure Captions and Descriptions</head>
      <p>The element <gi>caption</gi> may be used to transcribe (or supply) a title or descriptive
        heading for the graphic itself, as in the following example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <fig>
          <caption>Grace notes</caption>
          <graphic target="../samples/snippets/mei2012-30shortexamples/beam-grace/grace-300.png"/>
        </fig>
      </egXML>
      <p>The figure description (<gi>figDesc</gi>) element usually contains a brief prose
        description of the appearance or content of a graphic figure, for use when documenting an
        image, perhaps without displaying it. This element is intended for use as an alternative to
        the content of its parent <gi>figure</gi> element; for example, for display when the
        equipment in use cannot display graphic images. It may also be used for indexing or
        documentary purposes, in which case best practice suggests the use of controlled vocabulary
        terms.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <fig>
          <graphic target="emblem1.png"/>
          <caption>Emblemi d'Amore</caption>
          <figDesc>A pair of naked winged cupids, each holding a flaming torch, in a rural
            setting.</figDesc>
        </fig>
      </egXML>
      <p>Occasionally, a figure description may have a complex structure. In this case, one or more
        textual component elements (<gi>paragraph</gi>, <gi>table</gi>, <gi>list</gi>,
          <gi>quote</gi>, or <gi>lg</gi>) may be used to model the internal structure of the
        description:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <fig>
          <caption>Grace notes</caption>
          <figDesc>
            <p>The example shows grace notes within beams ...</p>
            <p>This illustration was created by ...</p>
          </figDesc>
          <graphic target="../samples/snippets/mei2012-30shortexamples/beam-grace/grace-300.png"/>
        </fig>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="figtableImages">
      <head>Images</head>
      <p>The <gi>graphic</gi> element indicates the location of an inline graphic, illustration, or
        figure. As noted above, there exists a wide variety of different graphics formats, and the
        following list is in no way exhaustive. Moreover, inclusion of any format in this list
        should not be taken as indicating endorsement by the MEI of this format or any products
        associated with it. Some of the formats listed here are proprietary to a greater or lesser
        extent and cannot therefore be regarded as standards in any meaningful sense. They are,
        however, widely used by many different vendors. The following formats are widely used at the
        present time, and are likely to remain supported by more than one vendor's software:</p>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>BMP: Microsoft bitmap format</item>
        <item>CGM: Computer Graphics Metafile</item>
        <item>GIF: Graphics Interchange Format</item>
        <item>JPEG: Joint Photographic Expert Group</item>
        <item>PBM: Portable Bit Map</item>
        <item>PCX: IBM PC raster format</item>
        <item>PICT: Macintosh drawing format</item>
        <item>PNG: Portable Network Graphics format</item>
        <item>Photo-CD: Kodak Photo Compact Disk format</item>
        <item>QuickTime: Apple real-time image system</item>
        <item>SMIL: Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language format</item>
        <item>SVG: Scalable Vector Graphics format</item>
        <item>TIFF: Tagged Image File Format</item>
      </list>
      <p>Brief descriptions of all the above are given below. Where possible, current addresses or
        other contact information are shown for the originator of each format. Many formal
        standards, especially those promulgated by the ISO and many related national organizations
        (ANSI, DIN, BSI, and many more), are available from those national organizations. Addresses
        may be found in any standard organizational directory for the country in question.</p>

      <div type="div4" xml:id="VectorGraphicFormats">
        <head>Vector Graphic Formats</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <item><label>CGM: Computer Graphics Metafile</label> This vector graphics format is
            specified by an ISO standard, ISO 8632:1987, amended in 1990. It defines binary,
            character, and plain-text encodings; the non-binary forms are safer for blind
            interchange, especially over networks. Documentation is available from ISO and from its
            member national bodies, such as AFNOR, ANSI, BSI, DIN, JIS, etc.</item>
          <item><label>SVG: Scalable Vector Graphics format</label> SVG is a language for describing
            two-dimensional vector and mixed vector or raster graphics in XML. It is defined by the
            Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) 1.0 Specification, W3C Recommendation, 04 September 2001,
            available at <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2001/REC-SVG-20010904/"
              >http://www.w3.org/TR/2001/REC-SVG-20010904/</ref>.</item>
          <item><label>PICT: Macintosh drawing format</label> This format is universally supported
            on Macintosh (tm) systems, and readable by a limited range of software for other
            systems. Documentation is available from Apple Computer, Cupertino, California
            USA.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="RasterGraphicFormats">
        <head>Raster Graphic Formats</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <item><label>PNG: Portable Network Graphics format</label> PNG is a non-proprietary raster
            format currently widely available. It provides an extensible file format for the
            losslessly compressed storage of raster images. Indexed-color, grayscale, and true-color
            images are supported, plus an optional alpha channel. Sample depths range from 1 to 16
            bits. It is defined by IETF RFC 2083, March 1997.</item>
          <item><label>TIFF: Tagged Image File Format</label> Currently the most widely supported
            raster image format, especially for black and white images, TIFF is also one of the few
            formats commonly supported on more than one operating system. The drawback to TIFF is
            that it actually is a wrapper for several formats, and some TIFF-supporting software
            does not support all variants. TIFF files may use LZW, CCITT Group 4, or PackBits
            compression methods, or may use no compression at all. Also, TIFF files may be
            monochrome, greyscale, or polychromatic. All such options should be specified in prose
            at the end of the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> section of the MEI header for any document
            including TIFF images. TIFF is owned by Aldus Corporation. Documentation on TIFF is
            available from the owner at Craigcook Castle, Craigcook Road, Edinburgh EH4 3UH,
            Scotland, or 411 First Avenue South, Seattle, Washington 98104 USA.</item>
          <item><label>GIF: Graphics Interchange Format</label> Raster images are widely available
            in this form, which was created by CompuServe Information Services, but has by now been
            implemented for many other systems as well. Documentation is copyright by, and is
            available from, CompuServe Incorporated, Graphics Technology Department, 5000 Arlington
            Center Boulevard, Columbus, Ohio 43220 USA. </item>
          <item><label>PBM: Portable Bit Map</label> PBM files are easy to process, eschewing all
            compression in favor of transparency of file format. PBM files can, of course, be
            compressed by generic file-compression tools for storage and transfer. Public domain
            software exists which will convert many other formats to and from PBM. Documentation of
            PBM is copyright by Jeff Poskanzer, and is available widely on the Internet.</item>
          <item><label>PCX: IBM PC raster format</label> This format is used by most IBM PC paint
            programs, and supports both monochrome and polychromatic images. Documentation is
            available from ZSoft Corporation, Technical Support Department, ATTN: Technical
            Reference Manual, 450 Franklin Rd. Suite 100, Marietta, GA 30067 USA.</item>
          <item><label>BMP: Microsoft bitmap format</label> This format is the standard raster
            format for computer using Microsoft Windows (tm) or Presentation Manager (tm).
            Documentation is available from Microsoft Corporation. </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="div4" xml:id="PhotographicAndMotionVideoFormats">
        <head>Photographic and Motion Video Formats</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <item><label>JPEG: Joint Photographic Experts Group</label> This format is sponsored by
            CCITT and by ISO. It is ISO/IEC Draft International Standard 10918-1, and CCITT T.81. It
            handles monochrome and polychromatic images with a variety of compression techniques.
            JPEG per se, like CCITT Group IV, must be encapsulated before transmission; this can be
            done via TIFF, or via the JPEG File Interchange Format (JFIF), as commonly done for
            Internet delivery.</item>
          <!-- <label>QuickTime: Apple real-time image system</label>
            <item>QuickTime is a proprietary method introduced by Apple Computer Company to
              synchronize the display of various data. The data can include frames of video, sound,
              lighting control mechanisms, and other things. Viewers for QuickTime productions are
              available for Apple and other computers. Further information is available from Apple
              Computer Incorporated, 10201 North de Anza Boulevard MS 23AQ, Cupertino, California
              95014 USA.</item>-->
          <item><label>Photo-CD: Kodak Photo Compact Disk format</label> This format was introduced
            by Kodak for rasterizing photographs and storing them on CD-ROMs (about one hundred 35mm
            file images fit on one disk), for display on televisions or CD-I systems. Information on
            Photo-CD is available from Kodak Limited, Research and Development, Headstone Drive,
            Harrow, Middlesex HA1 4TY, UK.</item>
          <!--<label>SMIL: Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language format</label>
            <item>SMIL is a W3C Recommendation which supports the integration of independent
              multimedia objects into a synchronized multimedia presentation. It provides multimedia
              authors with easily-defined basic timing relationships, fine-tuned synchronization,
              spatial layout, direct inclusion of non-text and non-image media objects, hyperlink
              support for time-based media, adaptiveness to varying user and system characteristics.
              SMIL 1.0 (<ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-smil/"/>) became a W3C Recommendation
              on June 15, 1998, and was further developed in SMIL 2.0. SMIL 2.0 adds native support
              for transitions, animation, event-based interaction, extended layout facilities, and
              more sophisticated timing and synchronization primitives to the SMIL 1.0 language. It
              also allows reuse of SMIL syntax and semantics in other XML-based languages, in
              particular those who need to represent timing and synchronization. For example, SMIL
              2.0 components are used for integrating timing into XHTML Document Types and into SVG.
              SMIL 2.0 also provides recommendations for Document Types based on SMIL 2.0 Modules
                (<ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/smil20/smil-modules.html"/>). One such Document
              Type is the SMIL 2.0 Language Profile (<ref
                target="http://www.w3.org/TR/smil20/smil20-profile.html"/>). It contains support for
              all of the major SMIL 2.0 features including animation, content control, layout,
              linking, media object, meta-information, structure, timing, and transition effects and
              is designed for Web clients that support direct playback from SMIL 2.0 markup. SMIL
              2.0 (<ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/smil20/"/>) became a W3C Recommendation on
              August 7, 2001, becoming the first vocabulary to provide XML Schema support and to
              have reached such status.</item>-->
        </list>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="tables">
    <head>Tables</head>
    <p>The element <gi>table</gi> contains text displayed in tabular form, i.e., in rows and
      columns. A table is the least <soCalled>graphic</soCalled> of the elements discussed in this
      chapter. Almost any text structure can be presented as a series of rows and columns: one
      might, for example, choose to show a glossary or other form of list in tabular form, without
      necessarily regarding it as a table. When tabular presentation is regarded as of less
      intrinsic importance, it is correspondingly simpler to encode descriptive or functional
      information about the contents of the table, for example to identify one cell as containing a
      name and another as containig a date, though the two methods may be combined. </p>
    <p>The <gi>table</gi> element may appear both within other components (such as paragraphs), or
      between them, provided that the module defined in this chapter has been enabled. It is to a
      large extent arbitrary whether a table should be regarded as a series of rows or as a series
      of columns. For compatibility with currently available systems, however, these Guidelines
      require a row-by-row description of a table.</p>
    <p>While rows and columns are always encoded in top-to-bottom, left-to-right order, formatting
      properties such as those provided by CSS may be used to specify that they should be displayed
      differently.</p>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="tableRows">
      <head>Rows</head>
      <p>The <gi>tr</gi> (table row) element is a formatting element that contains one or more
          <gi>td</gi> or <gi>th</gi> elements (cells) in a <gi>table</gi>. A cell is the
        intersection of a row and a column. The precise rendition of the table and its cells should
        be specified in a style steet.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th colspan="7">Besetzungen der Triosonate und ihrer Nachfolger</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td/>
            <td>Triosonate<lb/>Standardbes.</td>
            <td>Triosonate für<lb/>Orgel (Bach)</td>
            <td>Sonate mit obl.<lb/>Cembalo (Bach)</td>
            <td>Klaviertrio</td>
            <td>Streichquartett</td>
            <td>Streichtrio</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>1. Oberstimme</td>
            <td>1. Violine</td>
            <td>Orgel r.H.</td>
            <td>Violine<lb/>(Flöte, Gambe)</td>
            <td>Violine</td>
            <td>1. Violine</td>
            <td>1. Violine</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>2. Oberstimme</td>
            <td>2. Violine</td>
            <td>Orgel l.H.</td>
            <td>Cembalo r.H.</td>
            <td>Klavier r.H.</td>
            <td>2. Violine</td>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>harmonische Füllung</td>
            <td>Cembalo r.H.</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td>Bratsche</td>
            <td>Bratsche</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Bass-Stimme</td>
            <td>Cello</td>
            <td>Orgel Pedal</td>
            <td>Cello</td>
            <td>Cello</td>
            <td>Cello</td>
            <td>Cello</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="tableCells">
      <head>Cells</head>
      <p>The <gi>td</gi> (table data) element designates a table cell that contains data as opposed
        to a cell that contains column or row heading information. The <att>colspan</att> and
          <att>rowspan</att> attributes provide tabular rendering information. They indicate that a
        particular cell or row of a table spans more than one row or column.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="2" rowspan="2">unmittelbares Schlagen</td>
            <td colspan="2" rowspan="2">mittelbares Schlagen</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Gegenschlag</td>
            <td>Aufschlag</td>
            <td>Schütteln</td>
            <td>Schrapen</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>1. Stäbe</td>
            <td>1. Stäbe</td>
            <td>1. Rahmen</td>
            <td>1. Raspeln</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>2. Platten</td>
            <td>2. Röhren</td>
            <td>2. Gefäße</td>
            <td>2. Räder</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td/>
            <td>3. Platten</td>
            <td>3. Reihen</td>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td/>
            <td>4. Gefäße</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </egXML>

      <p>The <gi>th</gi> (table header) element designates a table cell containing column or row
        heading information as opposed to one containing data. The <att>colspan</att> and
          <att>rowspan</att> attributes tabular display rendering information. They indicate that a
        particular cell or row of a table spans more than one row or column.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th colspan="4">Systematische Einteilung der Idiophone</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="2">unmittelbares Schlagen</td>
            <td colspan="2">mittelbares Schlagen</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Gegenschlag</td>
            <td>Aufschlag</td>
            <td>Schütteln</td>
            <td>Schrapen</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>1. Stäbe</td>
            <td>1. Stäbe</td>
            <td>1. Rahmen</td>
            <td>1. Raspeln</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>2. Platten</td>
            <td>2. Röhren</td>
            <td>2. Gefäße</td>
            <td>2. Räder</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td/>
            <td>3. Platten</td>
            <td>3. Reihen</td>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td/>
            <td>4. Gefäße</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </egXML>
    </div>
  </div>

  <!--<div type="div2" xml:id="figtableAttributeClasses">
    <head>Attribute Classes</head>
    <p>The module figTable defines the att.tabular attribute class which groups attributes shared by table cells:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="att.tabular" atts="rowspan colspan"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="figtableModelClasses">
    <head>Model Classes</head>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="modelFigDescLike">
      <head>model.figDescLike</head>
      <p>The model class model.figDescLike groups elements that provide a brief prose description of
        the appearance or content of a graphic figure.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="modelFigureLike">
      <head>model.figureLike</head>
      <p>The model class model.figureLike groups elements representing or containing graphic
        information such as an illustration or figure.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="modelGraphicLike">
      <head>model.graphicLike</head>
      <p>The model class model.graphicLike groups elements that indicate the location of an inline
        graphic, illustration, or figure.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="modelTableLike">
      <head>model.tableLike</head>
      <p>The model class model.tableLike groups table-like elements.</p>
    </div>
  </div>-->

</div>
