<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<front>
  <titlePage>
    <docTitle>
      <titlePart>
        <hi rend="bold">Music Encoding Initiative Guidelines<lb/><lb/><lb/>MEI Technical Document
          No. 3</hi>
      </titlePart>
    </docTitle>
    <docEdition>
      <hi rend="bold">2012 Release</hi>
    </docEdition>
    <byline><lb/><lb/>Prepared and maintained by the Music Encoding Initiative Council<lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/>
      <figure rend="center">
        <graphic url="Images/meilogo.png"/>
      </figure>
      <lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/>
    </byline>
    <byline>Edited by Perry Roland and Johannes Kepper<lb/><lb/></byline>
    <byline>With contributions by Benjamin Bohl, Andrew Hankinson, Maja Hartwig,<lb/>Laurent Pugin,
      Kristina Richts, Raffaele Viglianti, and Thomas Weber<lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></byline>
    <docEdition>
      <hi rend="center">
        <table>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <graphic url="Images/hzonlineart.png"/>
            </cell>
            <cell>
              <graphic url="Images/dfg_logo_schwarz.png"/>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </hi>
      <lb/>
      <lb/>
    </docEdition>
    <docImprint>This project is supported jointly by the National Endowment for the Humanities and
      the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations
      expressed in this publication do not necessarily reflect those of the National Endowment for
      the Humanities or the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft.<lb/><lb/></docImprint>
    <!--<pb n="ii"/>-->
    <docEdition><lb/><lb/>Music Encoding Initiative Guidelines, 2012 Release<lb/><lb/></docEdition>
    <docImprint>© by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.<lb/>
      <pubPlace>Charlottesville and Detmold</pubPlace><docDate>2012</docDate></docImprint>
    <byline>
      <lb/><lb/>Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you<lb/>
      may not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy<lb/>
      of the License at <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/"
        >http://www.osedu.org/licenses/ECL-2.0</ref>.<lb/><lb/><lb/></byline>
  </titlePage>
  <div>
    <head>Table of Contents</head>
    <divGen type="toc"/>
  </div>
  <!--<pb n="iii"/>-->

  <!--<pb n="iv"/>-->
  <div>
    <head>Acknowledgments</head>
    <p>Many institutions and individuals assisted in the preparation of these Guidelines and in the
      overall development of the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) schema.</p>
    <p>Grateful acknowledgment is given to the following institutions for their generous
      contributions: the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) and the Deutsche
      Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) for their joint support of the MEI project, the Institute for
      Advanced Technology in the Humanities at the University of Virginia and the Hochschule für
      Musik in Detmold for graciously hosting grant-funded meetings, the Center for
      Computer-Assisted Research in the Humanities at Stanford University for permission to make use
      of their large collection of encoded music, the Akademie der Wissenschaften und der Literatur
      in Mainz for their recognition of the potential of MEI, and the Musikwissenschaftliches
      Seminar Detmold/Paderborn and the University of Virginia Library for providing financial
      support and environments that encourage experimentation.</p>
    <p>The Text Encoding Initiative is also owed a special debt of gratitude. In addition to
      providing much of the inspiration for MEI, the TEI organization supplied funding for the MEI
      Technical Group in its efforts to adopt ODD. The editors of these Guidelines are grateful for
      those of the TEI, which provided a stellar exemplar and from which we have <q>borrowed</q>
      shamelessly.</p>
    <p>The following individuals have provided much-appreciated commitments of time and energy to
      the development of MEI: Donald Byrd (Indiana University, Bloomington); Richard Freedman
      (Haverford College); Ichiro Fujinaga (McGill University, Montreal); Andrew Hankinson (McGill
      University); Johannes Kepper (Musikwissenschaftliches Seminar Detmold/Paderborn); Erin Mayhood
      (University of Virginia Library); Stefan Morent (University of Tübingen); Daniel Pitti
      (Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities, University of Virginia); Laurent Pugin
      (RISM Switzerland); Daniel Röwenstrunk (Musikwissenschaftliches Seminar Detmold/Paderborn);
      Perry Roland (University of Virginia Library); Craig Sapp (Center for Computer-Assisted
      Research in the Humanities, Stanford); Eleanor Selfridge-Field (Center for Computer-Assisted
      Research in the Humanities, Stanford); Christine Siegert (OPERA Project, Bayreuth); Axel Teich
      Geertinger (Royal Danish Library); Joachim Veit (Carl-Maria-von-Weber-Gesamtausgabe, Detmold);
      and Raffaele Viglianti (King's College, London).</p>
    <p>Thanks to Bernhard R. Appel (Beethoven-Haus); J. Stephen Downie (University of Illinois at
      Urbana-Champaign); Oliver Huck (Universität Hamburg); Fotis Jannidis (Universität Würzburg);
      and Frans Wiering (University of Utrecht) for providing expertise on a wide range of topics
      related to music notation modelling.</p>
    <p>Also thanks to Syd Bauman, Terry Catapano, and Sebastian Rahtz for their invaluable
      problem-solving assistance during the development of the 2010 RNG schema. Thanks to Sebastian
      Rahtz and James Cummings of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) for their help with making ODD
      work with MEI, their assistance in more closely aligning MEI and TEI, and their quick
      responses to questions and Roma bug reports.</p>
    <p>Finally, the members of the Music Encoding Initiative would like to thank Perry Roland for
      his foresight, engagement and determination in laying the foundations of this initiative.</p>
  </div>
  <div>
    <head>Introduction</head>
    <p>This release of the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) provides three major components:</p>
    <list>
      <item>formalized rules for recording the intellectual and physical characteristics of music
        notation documents so that the information contained in them may be searched, retrieved,
        displayed, and exchanged in a predictable and platform-independent manner;</item>
      <item>a <q>Tag Library</q> that documents the components of the MEI model; and</item>
      <item>best practices guidelines for the application of those rules.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Both the MEI rules and their documentation are expressed in the form of a One Document
      Does-it-all (ODD) document, which was developed for the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI). The
      MEI ODD document has been processed to create the MEI application guidelines, Tag Library, and
      accompanying schemas.</p>
    <p>The MEI Guidelines, which include the Tag Library, are intended to serve as a reference tool
      for music encoders. Through the use of natural-language definitions and examples, this
      document assists users of MEI in achieving effective and consistent markup. Despite
      translating XML and RNG terminology and concepts into more accessible language, it is still a
      technical one that presupposes a minimal understanding of XML and music notation. Novice
      encoders will need to supplement their use of the Guidelines by participating in discussions
      on the MEI-L list, attending introductory MEI workshops and training classes and referring to
      other information sources.</p>
    <p>As a natural-language translation of the MEI conceptual model, the Guidelines convey
      information about the three principal tasks accomplished by the model. First, the model breaks
      down the content of music notation documents into data fields or categories of information
      called "elements". All of these elements are named, defined, and described in the tag library.
      Second, the tag library identifies and defines attributes associated with those elements.
      Attributes are characteristics or properties that further refine the element. Last, and
      perhaps most importantly, the tag library documents the structure of the MEI model by
      explaining the relationship between elements, specifying where the elements may be used and
      describing how they may be modified by attributes. While two of the basic purposes of MEI are
      to facilitate the searching and display of encoded music notation documents in an electronic
      environment, nothing in the tag library addresses their specific implementation. Searching and
      display are entirely dependent on software applications outside the scope of the MEI
      model.</p>
    <p>The MEI model contains only a few required elements, the majority are optional. Therefore,
      the amount of markup desired will vary from one situation to another depending on
      intellectual, technical, and temporal considerations. Creating encoded music notation
      documents for inclusion in union databases may also result in tagging requirements that are
      separate from those dictated by the model.</p>
    <p>Suggestions for new elements or revised descriptions may be submitted to the MEI Working
      Group via the MEI discussion list at <ref target="mei-l@lists.uni-paderborn.de"
        >mei-l@lists.uni-paderborn.de</ref>.</p>
  </div>
  <div>
    <head>MEI Design Principles</head>
    <p>This section of the Guidelines defines principles and criteria for designing, developing, and
      maintaining an XML-based encoding scheme for music notation documents.</p>
    <list>
      <head>Definitions and Parameters</head>
      <item>A music notation document is one that contains music notation; that is, any one of a
        number of "visual analogues of musical sound, either as a record of sound heard or imagined,
        or as a set of visual instructions for performers." (Ian D. Bent, et al. "Notation." Grove
        Music Online. Oxford Music Online. 25 May 2010. &lt;<ref
          target="http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/subscriber/article/grove/music/20114"
          >http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/subscriber/article/grove/music/20114</ref>&gt;.)</item>
      <item>The encoding scheme permits both the creation of new music notation documents and the
        conversion of existing ones from print and other electronic formats. However, conversion of
        existing documents may require revisions in content or rearrangement of information.</item>
    </list>
    <list>
      <head>General Principles</head>
      <item>No prima facia distinction is made between a primary source of music notation, such as
        an autograph or published score, and a secondary source, such as a scholarly edition based
        on one or more primary sources. The tag set encompasses both, and the encoder must choose
        the elements and attributes most appropriate in each case.</item>
      <item>As an encoded representation of one or more music notation documents, an MEI file may be
        employed as a surrogate for the original materials.</item>
      <item>Although the encoding scheme does not define or prescribe intellectual content for music
        notation documents, it does define content designation and is intended to be used with
        available data content standards. MEI identifies the essential data elements within music
        notation documents and establishes codes and conventions necessary for capturing and
        distinguishing information within those elements for future action or manipulation. While
        there are a few elements that ought to appear in any MEI document, various intellectual,
        technical, and economic factors influence the level of detail of analysis and encoding
        actually undertaken. Taking this into consideration, the encoding scheme is designed with a
        minimum of required elements and allows for progressively more detailed levels of
        description as desired.</item>
      <item>The encoding scheme preserves and enhances the current functionality of existing music
        notation documents. It permits identification of document structures and content that
        support description, navigation, analysis, and online and print presentation.</item>
      <item>The encoding scheme is intended to facilitate interchange between notational tools. It
        aims to assist in the creation of more effective and consistent encoding, encourage the
        creation of union databases of music notation documents, and permit the reuse of encoded
        data for multiple output purposes. It will also ensure that machine-readable music notation
        documents will outlive changing hardware and software environments because they are based on
        a platform-independent standard.</item>
    </list>
    <list>
      <head>Structural Features</head>
      <item>The encoding scheme is based on eXtensible Markup Language (XML), a text-based format
        for representing structured information. It is expressed as an One Document Does-it-all
        (ODD) document, referred to as the "Music Encoding (MEI) Guidelines". For more information
        on ODD, please refer to TEI Guidelines chapter 22 (<ref
          target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html"
          >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html</ref>), chapter 23 (<ref
          target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/USE.html"
          >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/USE.html</ref>), and to the TEI's
        "Getting Started with P5 ODDs" document (<ref
          target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/odds.xml"
          >http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/odds.xml</ref>).</item>
      <item>Related or complementary standards, such as the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI)
        Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange, the Encoded Archival Description
        (EAD) DTD, MARC formats, existing notation encoding schemes, etc. have been consulted and
        employed as appropriate. The data model includes a header that is comparable to the TEI
        header, and TEI and EAD naming conventions and tag structures have been used whenever
        feasible. With respect to metadata, MEI recognizes the inter-relationship between the
        metadata content found in the MEI header and that of catalog records, authority records, and
        finding aids, and it provides for the use of an encoding equivalency attribute for MEI
        elements corresponding to fields in other metadata standards.</item>
      <item>To ensure broad international and multi-repertoire application of MEI, existing musical
        terminology was used in building the data model where practical. In addition, a method for
        localization of the data model's names has been provided. Finally, extensive use of
        attributes in the schema permits the refinement of element meanings with specific musical,
        geographic, or temporal contexts.</item>
    </list>
    <list>
      <head>Control and Maintenance</head>
      <item>Control and maintenance of the schema and its documentation will be provided by a
        maintenance agency working in concert with the national and international music communities,
        assisted in an advisory capacity by other interested groups of users.</item>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div>
    <head>Guidelines Revision</head>
    <p>It is important to note that not every feature of the MEI schema is covered in these
      Guidelines. Encoders are encouraged to post questions and comments to MEI-L when clarification
      is necessary. The Guidelines will be updated periodically.</p>
  </div>
</front>
