<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
  © 2014 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
  not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License
  at http://www.osedu.org/licenses/ECL-2.0.
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
  OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language
  governing permissions and limitations under the License.
  
  This is a derivative work based on earlier versions of the schema © 2001-2006 Perry Roland
  and the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia; licensed under the Educational
  Community License version 1.0.
  
  CONTACT: info@music-encoding.org
-->

<div type="div1" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="harmony" n="0">
  <head>Harmony</head>
  <p>This chapter describes the encoding of indications of harmony ocurring within a music text,
    e.g., chord names, tablature grids, figured bass, or signs for harmonic analysis, and the
    methods by which these indications can be connected with their interpretations. For
    encoder-supplied analysis of intervallic content, please see chapter <ptr target="#analysis"/>. </p>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="harmonyOverview">
    <head>Overview of the Harmony Module</head>
    <p>The module makes available the following components:</p>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="harmonyElements">
      <head>Elements</head>
      <p>The following elements are provided by the harmony module:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="barre"/>
          <specDesc key="chordDef"/>
          <specDesc key="chordMember"/>
          <specDesc key="chordTable"/>
          <specDesc key="f"/>
          <specDesc key="fb"/>
          <specDesc key="harm"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="harmonyAttributeClasses">
      <head>Attribute Classes</head>
      <p>The harmony module contains the following attribute classes:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="att.fretlocation"/>
          <specDesc key="att.harm.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.harm.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.harm.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.harm.vis"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="harmonyModelClasses">
      <head>Model Classes</head>
      <p>The following model classes are enabled by the harmony module:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="model.chordTableLike"/>
          <specDesc key="model.controleventLike.harmony"/>
          <specDesc key="model.figbassLike"/>
          <specDesc key="model.fLike"/>
          <specDesc key="model.harmLike"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
  </div>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="harmonyDetails">
    <head>Indications of Harmony</head>
    <p>On the most basic level, chords in the musical text can be encoded using the <gi scheme="MEI"
        >chord</gi> element:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="chord"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>Additional information on the use of the <gi scheme="MEI">chord</gi> element is available in
        <ptr target="#basicEvents"/> and <ptr target="#cmnNotesChords"/>.</p>
    <p>With only this kind of markup, harmonic information is implicit in the notes themselves. The
      elements and attributes of this module, however, provide for the encoding of explicit
      indications of harmony, such as chord symbols, tablature grids, figured bass signs, and the
      symbols of harmonic analysis like Roman numerals and their interpretation.</p>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="harmonyMetadataInscoreDef">
      <head>Interpreted Chord Data in scoreDef</head>
      <p>An harmonic label, such as "7", may occur many times throughout an MEI instance. Where the
        goal is diplomatic transcription, simply recording the uninterpreted label is sufficient.
        Recording the precise meaning of such a label requires storing an interpretation. But,
        including the interpretation at every point of occurrence of the label would swell the size
        of the file and complicate the markup for those users who are not interested in the
        interpretation. Therefore, MEI separates the encoding of harmonic labels from the encoding
        of the interpretation of those labels.</p>
      <p>The following elements enable the creation and re-use of interpreted chord data:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="chordTable"/>
          <specDesc key="chordDef" atts="pos"/>
          <specDesc key="chordMember" atts="inth fing fret"/>
          <specDesc key="barre" atts="fret"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">chordTable</gi> element is a container for a set of chord definitions,
        while the <gi scheme="MEI">chordDef</gi> element defines a single chord. Chord definitions
        may be created <foreign>a priori</foreign> or as the result of analysis of the pitch content
        of the music at hand, for instance, by examination of the notes occurring on the downbeat of
        each measure. In this way, the chord definitions serve as a record of the analysis.</p>
      <p>Even though it is not required by the schema, an <att>xml:id</att> attribute on <gi
          scheme="MEI">chordDef</gi> is necessary to permit the creation of associations between
        harmonic indications in the musical text with the chord defined here. The <att>xml:id</att>
        attribute provides a unique identifier for the chord definition that can be referenced by
        the <gi scheme="MEI">harm</gi> element's <att>chordref</att> attribute.</p>
      <p>Individual pitches of a chord are encoded using <gi scheme="MEI">chordMember</gi>. The
          <att>inth</att> attribute provides the means for indicating the number of half steps of
        the chord note above the bass note.</p>
      <p>These simple resources allow for the detailed specification and interpretation of harmonic
        indications found in the musical text. For example, the harmonic label <q>A</q> can be
        equated with a fully spelled-out indication of functional harmony that can be substituted
        for the harmonic label, say, in an aural rendition:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<!-- Chord defined in scoreDef -->
<chordDef xml:id="harmonychordA">
  <chordMember pname="a" oct="2"/>
  <chordMember pname="e" oct="3"/>
  <chordMember pname="c" accid.ges="s" oct="4"/>
  <chordMember pname="e" oct="4"/>
  <chordMember pname="a" oct="4"/>
</chordDef>
<!-- Later in musical text -->
<harm chordref="#harmonychordA" tstamp="1">A</harm>
      </egXML>

      <p>Alternatively, the non-bass chord tones may be indicated, not with pitch names, but with
        their intervallic distance above the bass note. Therefore, the example above may also be
        encoded:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<chordDef xml:id="harmonychordA2">
  <chordMember pname="a" oct="2"/>
  <chordMember inth="7"/>
  <chordMember inth="16"/>
  <chordMember inth="19"/>
  <chordMember inth="24"/>
</chordDef>
      </egXML>

      <p>The preceding encoding possibilities provide the detailed information necessary to create
        playable chord annotations. For more generic uses, however, the encoding can be taken one
        step further; that is, it can be reduced to its minimum intervallic content by eliminating
        octave duplications and expressing all chord members, including the bass note, using
        intervals above the bass. Of course, the <att>inth</att> attribute for the bass note itself
        should be set to <q>0</q>. For example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<chordDef xml:id="harmonychordA3">
  <chordMember inth="0"/>
  <chordMember inth="4"/>
  <chordMember inth="7"/>
</chordDef>
      </egXML>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="harmonyTablatureGrids">
      <head>Chord Tablature Grids</head>
      <p>The <att>pos</att> attribute on <gi scheme="MEI">chordDef</gi>, the <att>fing</att> and
          <att>fret</att> attributes on <gi scheme="MEI">chordMember</gi>, and the <gi scheme="MEI"
          >barre</gi> element child of <gi scheme="MEI">chordDef</gi> are provided in order to
        create displayable and performable chord tablature grids for guitar and other fretted string
        instruments. The fret at which a finger should be placed is recorded in the <att>fret</att>
        attribute, while <att>fing</att> indicates which finger, if any, should be used to play an
        individual string. The values <q>x</q> and <q>o</q> are used to indicate muffled and open
        strings, respectively.</p>
      <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">chordDef</gi> element may contain <gi scheme="MEI">barre</gi>
        sub-elements when a single finger is used to stop multiple strings. Here the <att>fret</att>
        attribute gives the fret position at which the barre should be created, while the
          <att>startid</att> and <att>endid</att> attributes are used to indicate the <gi
          scheme="MEI">chordMember</gi> elements on which the barre starts and finishes.</p>

    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="harmonyMusicText">
      <head>Indications of Harmony in the Music Text</head>
      <p>With regard to indications of harmony, MEI attempts to strike a balance between very
        precise (interpreted) and very loose (uninterpreted) markup needs. Therefore, various kinds
        of harmonic labels are accommodated by the <gi scheme="MEI">harm</gi> element. While some
        are more <q>structured</q> than others, in the final analyis they all function as
          <emph>labels</emph>. Therefore, MEI provides only a single element for the capture of
        harmonic indications of all kinds:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="harm" atts="extender rendgrid"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">harm</gi> element can be used to capture chord labels that consist
        entirely of text:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<harm tstamp="1">Cmaj</harm>
<harm tstamp="2">ii6</harm>
      </egXML>
      <p>or labels that are chord tablature grids:</p>
      <figure>
        <head>Chord grid without label</head>
        <graphic url="Images/modules/harmony/A7_5th.gif" width="124px"/>
      </figure>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<harm tstamp="1" chordref="#harmonychordA"/>
      </egXML>
      <p>or labels that mix these styles:</p>
      <figure>
        <head>Chord grid with label</head>
        <graphic url="Images/modules/harmony/A7_1st.gif" width="124px"/>
      </figure>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<harm tstamp="1" chordref="#harmonychordA" rendgrid="gridtext">A7</harm>
      </egXML>

      <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">harm</gi> element must define a point of attachment using one of the
        following attributes: <att>startid</att>, <att>tstamp</att>, <att>tstamp.ges</att> or
          <att>tstamp.real</att>. The most commonly-used of these are <att>startid</att> and
          <att>tstamp</att>.</p>
      <p>The <att>dur</att> attribute encodes the logical and visual duration of the harmony. Please
        note that the <att>dur</att> attribute here is not a true duration, but rather a time stamp
        for the end point of the harmony.</p>
      <p>Precise placement of the harmonic label can be controlled through the use of attributes in
        the <ident type="class">att.harm.vis</ident> attribute class.</p>

      <div type="div4" xml:id="harmonyFigbass">
        <head>Figured Bass</head>
        <p>Figured bass is a specialized form of harmonic indication. In order to support the
          capture of the semantics of figured bass, and not just its visual representation, MEI
          provides the following elements:</p>
        <p>
          <specList>
            <specDesc key="fb"/>
            <specDesc key="f" atts="extender"/>
          </specList>
        </p>

        <p>Figured bass, consisting as it does of text, can always be represented purely visually.
          This is probably how an OMR program or other naive encoder might deal with the markup of
          figured bass:</p>
        <figure>
          <head>Figured bass</head>
          <graphic url="Images/modules/harmony/figuredBass01.png"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<harm staff="1" tstamp="1" place="above">6</harm>
        </egXML>

        <p>However, this kind of approach fails to recognize that a figured bass is being used and
          not some other system of harmonic indications. To capture this knowledge, the preceding
          example can also be marked more explicitly with:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<harm staff="1" tstamp="1" place="above">
  <fb>
    <f>6</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
        </egXML>

        <p>In order to provide greater control over the individual components of the figured bass,
          each component can be treated as a figure. The natural symbol is encoded using the Unicode
          MUSIC NATURAL SIGN character.</p>
        <figure>
          <head>Figured bass with accidental</head>
          <graphic url="Images/modules/harmony/figuredBass02.png"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<harm staff="1" tstamp="1" place="above">
  <fb>
    <f>7</f>
    <f>&#x266E;</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
        </egXML>

        <p>Encoding order of the component <gi scheme="MEI">f</gi> elements is significant as is the
          encoding order of the characters within each component. In the preceding example, the
          entire figured bass sign is encoded from top to bottom, in other words, just as the figure
          appears on the page. In the following examples, the encoding order of the characters in
            <gi scheme="MEI">f</gi> explicitly locates the accidentals:</p>
        <figure>
          <head>Figured bass with chromatically altered figure</head>
          <graphic url="Images/modules/harmony/figuredBass03.png"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<harm place="below">
  <fb>
    <f>7&#x266D;</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
        </egXML>

        <figure>
          <head>Figured bass with chromatically altered figures</head>
          <graphic url="Images/modules/harmony/figuredBass04.png"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<harm>
  <fb>
    <f>6</f>
    <f>4+</f>
    <f>&#x266E;3</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
        </egXML>

        <p>Characters with combining slashes can be handled using the Unicode characters COMBINING
          REVERSE SOLIDUS OVERLAY (6&#x20e5;) and COMBINING LONG SOLIDUS OVERLAY (6&#x338;). The
          combining nature of these Unicode characters indicates very clearly that they "overstrike"
          the preceding character. The usual convention for slashes; that is, <q>6\</q> and
            <q>6/</q> for backslash and slash, respectively, may also be followed:</p>
        <figure>
          <head>Figured bass with chromatically altered figure</head>
          <graphic url="Images/modules/harmony/figuredBass05.png"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<harm>
  <fb>
    <f>6&#x20E5;</f>
    <!-- or -->
    <f>6\</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
        </egXML>

        <p>Each component of the figured bass sign may use the <att>extender</att> attribute to
          indicate that horizontal lines are used to mark the extent of the figure's harmonic
          influence. The <att>altsym</att> attribute can be used to point to a user-defined symbol
          that better represents the figure component, for example, the combined "2" and "+" below.
          Similar to the slash in the preceding example before, the small curve over the "5" in
          example 6 can be represented by the Unicode COMBINING INVERTED BREVE.</p>
        <figure>
          <head>Figured bass with alternative sign</head>
          <graphic url="Images/modules/harmony/figuredBass06.png"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<harm tstamp="1">
  <fb>
    <f>&#x0311;</f>
    <f extender="true">5</f>
    <f altsym="combo2plus">2+</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
<harm tstamp="3">
  <fb>
    <f>3</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
        </egXML>

        <p>Because the repertoire of signs is so large, figures which consist entirely of a mark
          indicating repetition of the preceding figure, should be represented by the character
          appearing in the document. For example, in some notational styles, the repetition sign is
          a dash (<q>-</q>), while in others it is a solidus (<q>/</q>). Using characters like this
          is also consistent with other existing figured bass encoding schemes.</p>
        <figure>
          <head>Figured bass repetition </head>
          <graphic url="Images/modules/harmony/figuredBass07.png"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<harm tstamp="1.5">
  <fb>
    <f>-</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
        </egXML>

        <p>Often, the distinction between extending lines and repetition signs is unclear. Treating
          what at first appear to be extenders as repetition signs, however, can sometimes help to
          simplify the required markup and to make the intent of the signs explicit. For example, in
          the following example the dashes on beat 4 and 4.5 are treated as repetition signs:</p>
        <figure>
          <head>Extenders and repetition</head>
          <graphic url="Images/modules/harmony/figuredBass09.png"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<harm tstamp="3.5">
  <fb>
    <f>&#x266D;3</f>
    <f>6</f>
    <f>5</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
<harm tstamp="4">
  <fb>
    <f>-</f>
    <f>&#x266F;3</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
<harm tstamp="4.5">
  <fb>
    <f>7</f>
    <f>-</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
        </egXML>

        <p>Using <att>extender</att> attributes for this example may make it easier to render the
          figured bass symbol, but it is less explicit with regard to the intended harmony. For
          example, it is difficult to ascertain what harmony should be sounding on beat 4 and its
          after-beat.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<harm tstamp="3.5">
  <fb>
    <f>&#x266D;3</f>
    <f extender="true">6</f>
    <f>5</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
<harm tstamp="4">
  <fb>
    <f extender="true">&#x266F;3</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
<harm tstamp="4.5">
  <fb>
    <f>7</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
        </egXML>

        <p>The primary goal of <gi scheme="MEI">fb</gi> is not the capture all the visual
          idiosyncracies that can be found in printed and manuscript scores throughout the
          centuries, but to provide a more-or-less standardized label. The markup below, or any
          markup in fact, cannot capture the exact look of the figured bass signs. The
            <att>altsym</att> attribute may be used to provide access to a user-defined symbol for
          precise rendition. Similarly, the <att>facs</att> attribute may be employed to point to
          the symbol as it occurs in the encoding source material.</p>
        <figure>
          <head>Figured bass with alternative sign</head>
          <graphic url="Images/modules/harmony/figuredBass10.png"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<!-- Ex. a -->
<harm tstamp="3">
  <fb>
    <f>8</f>
    <f altsym="#my6_1" facs="#source6_1">6&#x266E;</f>
    <f>4+</f>
    <f>2</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
<harm tstamp="4">
  <fb>
    <f altsym="#my6_2" facs="#source6_2">6\</f>
    <f>4</f>
    <f>3</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
<!-- Ex. b -->
<harm tstamp="4.5">
  <fb>
    <f>6\</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
<!--  Ex. c -->
<harm tstamp="1">
  <fb>
    <f>5/</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
<!--  Ex. d -->
<harm>
  <fb>
    <f altsym="#my5" facs="#source5">5+</f>
  </fb>
</harm>
        </egXML>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
