<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  © 2010 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs Unported License, 
  Version 3.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/.
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="header1" n="0">
  <head>The MEI Header</head>
  <p>This chapter addresses the description of an encoded item so that the musical text, as well as
    its sources, encoding, and revisions are all thoroughly documented. Such documentation is
    necessary for scholars using the texts, for software processing them, and for catalogers in
    libraries and archives. Together these descriptions and declarations provide an electronic
    analog to the title page attached to a printed work. They also constitute an equivalent for the
    content of the code books or introductory manuals customarily accompanying electronic data
    sets.</p>
  <p>Every MEI-conformant text must carry such a set of descriptions, prefixed to it and encoded as
    described in this chapter. The set is known as the MEI header, tagged <gi>meiHead</gi>, and has
    five major parts:</p>
  <list type="ordered">
    <item>one or more identifiers, tagged with <gi>altId</gi>, each of which provides an identifying
      name or number associated with the file.</item>
    <item>a <term>file description</term>, tagged <gi>fileDesc</gi>, containing a full
      bibliographical description of the computer file itself, from which a user of the text could
      derive a proper bibliographic citation, or which a librarian or archivist could use in
      creating a catalog entry recording its presence within a library or archive. The term
        <term>computer file</term> here is to be understood as referring to the whole intellectual
      entity or document described by the header, even when this is stored in multiple physical
      operating system files. The file description also includes information about the source or
      sources from which the electronic document was derived. The MEI elements used to encode the
      file description are described in section <ptr target="#header1.1"/> below.</item>
    <item>an <term>encoding description</term>, tagged <gi>encodingDesc</gi>, which describes the
      relationship between an electronic text and its source or sources. It allows for detailed
      description of whether (or how) the text was normalized during transcription, how the encoder
      resolved ambiguities in the source, what levels of encoding or analysis were applied, and
      similar matters. The MEI elements used to encode the encoding description are described in
      section <ptr target="#header1.2"/> below.</item>
    <item>a <term>work description</term>, tagged <gi>workDesc</gi>, containing classification and
      contextual information about the text, such as its subject matter, the situation in which it
      was produced, the individuals described by or participating in producing it, and so forth.
      Such a text profile is of particular use in highly structured composite texts such as corpora
      or language collections, where it is often highly desirable to enforce a controlled
      descriptive vocabulary or to perform retrievals from a body of text in terms of text type or
      origin. The text profile may however be of use in any form of automatic text processing. The
      MEI elements used to encode the <term>work description</term> are described in section <ptr
        target="#header1.3"/> below.</item>
    <item>a <term>revision history</term>, tagged <gi>revisionDesc</gi>, which allows the encoder to
      provide a history of changes made during the development of the electronic text. The revision
      history is important for <term>version control</term> and for resolving questions about the
      history of a file. The MEI elements used to encode the revision description are described in
      section <ptr target="#header1.4"/> below.</item>
  </list>
  <div xml:id="header1.1" type="div2">
    <head>File description</head>
    <p>The structure of the bibliographic description of a machine-readable or digital musical text
      resembles that of a book, an article, or other kinds of textual objects. The file description
      element of the MEI header has therefore been closely modeled on existing standards in library
      cataloging; it should thus provide enough information to allow users to give standard
      bibliographic references to the electronic text, and to allow catalogers to catalog it.
      Bibliographic citations occurring elsewhere in the header, and in the text itself, are derived
      from the same model.</p>
    <p>The bibliographic description of an electronic musical text should be supplied by the
      mandatory <gi>fileDesc</gi> element:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="fileDesc"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>The <gi>fileDesc</gi> element contains two mandatory and six optional elements, each of which
      is described in more detail below. These elements are listed below in the order in which they
      must be given within the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element.</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="titleStmt"/>
        <specDesc key="editionStmt"/>
        <specDesc key="extent"/>
        <specDesc key="fingerprint"/>
        <specDesc key="publicationStmt"/>
        <specDesc key="seriesStmt"/>
        <specDesc key="notesStmt"/>
        <specDesc key="sourceDesc"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>A complete file description will resemble the following example:</p>

    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title><!-- title of the resource --></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <!-- information about the edition of the resource -->
        </editionStmt>
        <extent><!-- description of the size of the resource --></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
          <!-- information about the distribution of the resource -->
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <!-- information about any series to which the resource belongs -->
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <annot><!-- notes on other aspects of the resource --></annot>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <!-- information about the source from which the resource was derived -->
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </egXML>

    <p>Of these elements, only the <gi>titleStmt</gi> and <gi>publicationStmt</gi> are required; the
      others may be omitted unless considered useful.</p>
    <div xml:id="header1.1.1" type="div3">
      <head>Title statement</head>
      <p>The <gi>titleStmt</gi> element is the first component of the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element, and
        is mandatory:</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="titleStmt"/>
      </p>
      <p>It contains the title given to the electronic work, together with one or more optional
        statements of responsibility which identify the encoder, editor, author, compiler, or other
        parties responsible for it:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="title"/>
          <specDesc key="respStmt"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>title</gi> element contains the chief name of the electronic work, including any
        alternative title or subtitles it may have. Its content takes the form considered
        appropriate by its creator. The element may be repeated, if the work has more than one title
        (perhaps in different languages). Where the electronic work is derived from an existing
        source text, it is strongly recommended that the title for the former should be derived from
        the latter, but clearly distinguishable from it, for example by the addition of a phrase
        such as ‘: an electronic transcription’ or ‘a digital edition’. This will distinguish the
        electronic work from the source text in citations and in catalogs which contain descriptions
        of both types of material.</p>
      <p>The electronic work will also have an external name (its ‘filename’ or ‘data set name’) or
        reference number on the computer system where it resides at any time. This name is likely to
        change frequently, as new copies of the file are made on the computer system. Its form is
        entirely dependent on the particular computer system in use and thus cannot always easily be
        transferred from one system to another. Moreover, a given work may be composed of many
        files. For these reasons, these Guidelines strongly recommend that such names should not be
        used as the title for any electronic work.</p>
      <p>Helpful guidance on the formulation of useful descriptive titles in difficult cases may be
        found in the Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules (Gorman and Winkler, 1978, chapter 25) or in
        equivalent national-level bibliographical documentation.</p>
      <p>Any number of responsibility statements may occur within the title statement. The
          <gi>respStmt</gi> element has two subcomponents: a <gi>name</gi> element identifying a
        responsible individual or organization, and a <gi>resp</gi> element indicating the nature of
        the responsibility. All names should be stated in the form in which the persons or bodies
        wish to be publicly cited. This would usually be the fullest form of the name, including
        first names. No specific recommendations are made at this time as to appropriate content for
          <gi>resp</gi>. However, it should make clear the nature of the responsibility concerned,
        as in the examples below.</p>
      <p>At a minimum, the author of the text and (where appropriate) the creator of the file should
        be identified. If the bibliographic description is for a corpus, identify the creator of the
        corpus. Optionally also include the names of others involved in the transcription or
        elaboration of the text, sponsors, and funding agencies. The name of the person responsible
        for physical data input need not normally be recorded, unless that person is also
        intellectually responsible for some aspect of the creation of the file.</p>
      <p>Names given may be personal names or corporate names. When the MEI.namesdates module is
        enabled, two additional elements are permitted:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="corpName"/>
          <specDesc key="persName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>These elements allow for more precise identification of the entity associated with the name
        than is permitted by the simpler <gi>name</gi> element.</p>
      <p>Examples:</p>
      <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Capgrave's Life of St. John Norbert: a machine-readable transcription</title>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>compiled by</resp>
            <name>P.J. Lucas</name>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
      </egXML>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Two stories by Edgar Allen Poe: electronic version</title>
          <author>Poe, Edgar Allen (1809-1849)</author>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>compiled by</resp>
            <name>James D. Benson</name>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
      </egXML>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Yogadarśanam (arthāt yogasūtrapūṭhaḥ): a digital edition.</title>
          <title>The Yogasūtras of Patañjali: a digital edition.</title>
          <funder>Wellcome Institute for the History of Medicine</funder>
          <principal>Dominik Wujastyk</principal>
          <respStmt>
            <name>Wieslaw Mical</name>
            <resp>data entry and proof correction</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <respStmt>
            <name>Jan Hajic</name>
            <resp>conversion to MEI-conformant markup</resp>
          </respStmt></titleStmt>
      </egXML>-->
    </div>
    <div xml:id="header1.1.2" type="div3">
      <head>Edition statement</head>
      <p>The <gi>editionStmt</gi> element is the second component of the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element.
        It is optional but recommended when applicable.</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="editionStmt"/>
      </p>
      <p>It contains either phrases or more specialized elements identifying the edition and those
        responsible for it:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="edition"/>
          <specDesc key="respStmt"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>For printed texts, the word edition applies to the set of all the identical copies of an
        item produced from one master copy and issued by a particular publishing agency or a group
        of such agencies. A change in the identity of the distributing body or bodies does not
        normally constitute a change of edition, while a change in the master copy does.</p>
      <p>For electronic texts, the notion of a ‘master copy’ is not entirely appropriate, since they
        are far more easily copied and modified than printed ones; nonetheless, the term edition may
        be used for a particular state of a machine-readable text at which substantive changes are
        made and fixed. Synonymous terms used in these Guidelines are
        <mentioned>version</mentioned>, <mentioned>level</mentioned>, and
          <mentioned>release</mentioned>. The words <mentioned>revision</mentioned> and
          <mentioned>update</mentioned>, by contrast, are used for minor changes to a file which do
        not amount to a new edition.</p>
      <p>No simple rule can specify how ‘substantive’ changes have to be before they are regarded as
        producing a new edition, rather than a simple update. The general principle proposed here is
        that the production of a new edition entails a significant change in the intellectual
        content of the file, rather than its encoding or appearance. The addition of analytic coding
        to a text would thus constitute a new edition, while automatic conversion from one coded
        representation to another would not. Changes relating to the character code or physical
        storage details, corrections of misspellings, simple changes in the arrangement of the
        contents and changes in the output format do not normally constitute a new edition, whereas
        the addition of new information (e.g., a linguistic analysis expressed in part-of-speech
        tagging, sound or graphics, referential links to external data sets) almost always does.</p>
      <p>Clearly, there will always be borderline cases and the matter is somewhat arbitrary. The
        simplest rule is: if you think that your file is a new edition, then call it such. An
        edition statement is optional for the first release of a computer file; it is mandatory for
        each later release, though this requirement cannot be enforced.</p>
      <p>Note that all changes in a file, whether or not they are regarded as constituting a new
        edition or simply a new revision, should be independently noted in the revision description
        section of the file header (see section <ptr target="#header1.4"/>).</p>
      <p>The edition element should contain phrases describing the edition or version, including the
        word edition, version, or equivalent, together with a number or date, or terms indicating
        difference from other editions such as new edition, revised edition etc. Any dates that
        occur within the edition statement should be marked with the date element. The @n attribute
        of the edition element may be used as elsewhere to supply any formal identification (such as
        a version number) for the edition.</p>
      <p>One or more <gi>respStmt</gi> elements may also be used to supply statements of
        responsibility for the edition in question. These may refer to individuals or corporate
        bodies and can indicate functions such as that of a reviser, or can name the person or body
        responsible for the provision of supplementary matter, of appendices, etc., in a new
        edition.</p>
      <p>Some examples follow:</p>
      <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="P2">Second draft, substantially extended, revised, and corrected.</edition>
        </editionStmt></egXML>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <editionStmt>
          <edition>Student's edition, <date>June 1987</date></edition>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>New annotations by</resp>
            <name>George Brown</name>
          </respStmt>
        </editionStmt></egXML>-->
    </div>
    <div xml:id="header1.1.3" type="div3">
      <head>Physical description of the file</head>
      <p>The third component of the fileDesc is a description of the physical qualities of the file.
        Two elements, both optional, are provided for this purpose:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="extent"/>
          <specDesc key="fingerprint"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>extent</gi> element describes the approximate size of a text as stored on some
        carrier medium, whether digital or non-digital, specified in any convenient units.</p>
      <p>For printed books, information about the carrier, such as the kind of medium used and its
        size, are of great importance in cataloging procedures. The print-oriented rules for
        bibliographic description of an item's medium and extent need some re-interpretation when
        applied to electronic media. An electronic file exists as a distinct entity quite
        independently of its carrier and remains the same intellectual object whether it is stored
        on a magnetic tape, a CD-ROM, a set of floppy disks, or as a file on a mainframe computer.
        Since, moreover, these Guidelines are specifically aimed at facilitating transparent
        document storage and interchange, any purely machine-dependent information should be
        irrelevant as far as the file header is concerned.</p>
      <p>This is particularly true of information about file-type although library-oriented rules
        for cataloging often distinguish two types of computer file: ‘data’ and ‘programs’. This
        distinction is quite difficult to draw in some cases, for example, hypermedia or texts with
        built in search and retrieval software.</p>
      <p>Although it is equally system-dependent, some measure of the size of the computer file may
        be of use for cataloging and other practical purposes. Because the measurement and
        expression of file size is fraught with difficulties, only very general recommendations are
        possible; the element extent is provided for this purpose. It contains a phrase indicating
        the size or approximate size of the computer file in one of the following ways:</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <item>in bytes of a specified length (e.g. ‘4000 16-bit bytes’)</item>
        <item>as falling within a range of values, for example: <list type="simple">
            <item>less than 1 Mb</item>
            <item>between 1 Mb and 5 Mb</item>
            <item>between 6 Mb and 10 Mb</item>
            <item>over 10 Mb</item>
          </list>
        </item>
        <item>in terms of any convenient logical units (for example, words or sentences, citations,
          paragraphs)</item>
        <item>in terms of any convenient physical units (for example, blocks, disks, tapes)</item>
      </list>
      <p>The use of standard abbreviations for units of quantity is recommended where applicable,
        here as elsewhere (see http://physics.nist.gov/cuu/Units/binary.html).</p>
      <p>Examples:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <extent>between 1 16-bit MB and 2 16-bit MB</extent>
        <extent>4.2 MiB</extent>
        <extent>4532 Mbytes</extent>
        <extent>3200 sentences</extent>
        <extent>5 90 mm High Density Diskettes</extent>
      </egXML>
      <p>In one sense, the <gi>fingerprint</gi> element holds an identifier for the file. However,
        because this identifier, often referred to as a <term>checksum</term>, is computed from the
        file's contents, it can also be said to capture physical information about the file. The
        computed fingerprint can be used to distinguish between different versions of the file. That
        is, if the checksum of two files do not match, the data may have been altered or corrupted.
        MEI does not prescribe any particular method for computing the checksum/fingerprint.</p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="header1.1.4" type="div3">
      <head>Publication, Distribution, etc.</head>
      <p>The <gi>publicationStmt</gi> element is the fourth component of the <gi>fileDesc</gi>
        element and is mandatory.</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="publicationStmt"/>
      </p>
      <p>It may contain either a single <gi>unpub</gi> element, indicating that the file has yet to
        be published, or one or more elements from the model.addressLike, model.dateLike,
        model.identifierLike, or model.nameLike.geogname classes or the <gi>availability</gi> and
          <gi>respStmt</gi> elements. The use of <gi>unpub</gi> is recommended for unpublished
        manuscript materials.</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="respStmt"/>
      </p>
      <p>The respStmt element may be used to identify the publisher and distributor of the file. The
        publisher is the person or institution by whose authority a given edition of the file is
        made public. The distributor is the person or institution from whom copies of the text may
        be obtained.</p>
      <p>The following elements may be used to provide additional details regarding the publication
        and distribution of a bibliographic entity:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="geogName"/>
          <specDesc key="address"/>
          <specDesc key="identifier"/>
          <specDesc key="availability"/>
          <specDesc key="date"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The sub-elements of availability should be used to provide detailed information regarding
        the availability of an item.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="acqSource"/>
          <specDesc key="accessRestrict"/>
          <specDesc key="price"/>
          <specDesc key="useRestrict"/>
          <specDesc key="sysReq"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>Note that the dates, places, etc., given in the publication statement relate to the
        publisher, distributor, or release authority most recently mentioned. If the text was
        created at some date other than its date of publication, its date of creation should be
        given within the <gi>workDesc</gi> element, not in the publication statement. Give any other
        useful dates (e.g., dates of collection of data) in an <gi>annotation</gi> within the notes
        statement.</p>
      <p>Examples:</p>
      <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
          <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
          <date>1989</date>
          <identifier type="ISBN">0-19-254705-4</identifier>
          <availability>
            <p>Copyright 1989, Oxford University Press</p>
          </availability>
        </publicationStmt></egXML>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <publicationStmt>
          <authority>James D. Benson</authority>
          <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
          <date>1984</date>
        </publicationStmt></egXML>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>Sigma Press</publisher>
          <address>
            <addrLine>21 High  Street,</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Wilmslow,</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Cheshire M24 3DF</addrLine>
          </address>
          <date>1991</date>
          <distributor>Oxford Text Archive</distributor>
          <identifier type="ota">1256</identifier>
          <availability>
            <p>Available with prior consent of depositor for purposes of academic research and
              teaching only.</p>
          </availability>
        </publicationStmt></egXML>-->
    </div>
    <div xml:id="header1.1.5" type="div3">
      <head>Series statement</head>
      <p>The <gi>seriesStmt</gi> element is the fifth component of the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element and
        is optional.</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="seriesStmt"/>
      </p>
      <p>A series may be defined in one of the following ways:</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <item>A group of separate items related to one another by the fact that each item bears, in
          addition to its own title proper, a collective title applying to the group as a whole. The
          individual items may or may not be numbered.</item>
        <item>Each of two or more volumes of essays, lectures, articles, or other items, similar in
          character and issued in sequence.</item>
        <item>A separately numbered sequence of volumes within a series or serial.</item>
      </list>
      <p>The <gi>seriesStmt</gi> element may contain one or more of the following more specific
        elements:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="title"/>
          <specDesc key="respStmt"/>
          <specDesc key="identifier"/>
          <specDesc key="contents"/>
          <specDesc key="seriesStmt"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>title</gi> and <gi>respStmt</gi> elements have the same function described above:
        identification of the item, in this case the series, and the individuals or groups
        responsible for its creation and production.</p>
      <p>The <gi>identifier</gi> element may be used to supply any identifying number associated
        with the series, including both standard numbers such as an ISSN and particular issue
        numbers. (Arabic numerals separated by punctuation are recommended for this purpose:
        '6.19.33', for example, rather than 'VI/xix:33'). Its @type attribute is used to categorize
        the number further, taking the value 'ISSN' for an ISSN for example.</p>
      <p>The contents of the series may be enumerated using the <gi>contents</gi> element. Use of
        this element should be determined by the complexity of the resource and whether or not the
        information is readily available. The description may consist of a single paragraph or
          <gi>contentItem</gi> elements may be used to provide structured information. A link to an
        external table of contents may be supplied in lieu of or in addition to this element's child
        elements.</p>
      <p>The <gi>seriesStmt</gi> element is allowed to within itself in order to accommodate series
        within series.</p>
      <p>Examples:</p>
      <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <seriesStmt>
          <title level="s">Machine-Readable Texts for the Study of Indian Literature</title>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>ed. by</resp>
            <name>Jan Gonda</name>
          </respStmt>
          <identifier type="vol">1.2</identifier>
          <identifier type="ISSN">0 345 6789</identifier>
        </seriesStmt>
      </egXML>-->
    </div>
    <div xml:id="header1.1.6" type="div3">
      <head>Notes statement</head>
      <p>The <gi>notesStmt</gi> element is the sixth component of the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element and
        is optional. If used, it contains one or more <gi>annot</gi> elements, each containing a
        single piece of descriptive information of the kind treated as ‘general notes’ in
        traditional bibliographic descriptions.</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="notesStmt"/>
      </p>
      <p>Some information found in the notes area in conventional bibliography has been assigned
        specific elements in these Guidelines; in particular the following items should be tagged as
        indicated, rather than as general notes:</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <item>the nature, scope, artistic form, or purpose of the file; also the genre or other
          intellectual category to which it may belong: e.g. ‘Text types: newspaper editorials and
          reportage, science fiction, westerns, and detective stories’. These should be formally
          described within the <gi>workDesc</gi> element (section <ptr target="#header1.3"
          />).</item>
        <item>summary description providing a factual, non-evaluative account of the subject content
          of the file: e.g. ‘Transcribes interviews on general topics with native speakers of
          English in 17 cities during the spring and summer of 1963.’ These should also be formally
          described within the <gi>workDesc</gi> element (section <ptr target="#header1.3"
          />).</item>
        <item>bibliographic details relating to the source or sources of an electronic text: e.g.
          ‘Transcribed from the Norton facsimile of the 1623 Folio’. These should be formally
          described in the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element (section <ptr target="#header1.1.7"
          />).</item>
        <item>further information relating to publication, distribution, or release of the text,
          including sources from which the text may be obtained, any restrictions on its use or
          formal terms on its availability. These should be placed in the appropriate division of
          the <gi>publicationStmt</gi> element (section <ptr target="#header1.1.4"/>).</item>
        <item>publicly documented numbers associated with the file: e.g. ‘ICPSR study number 1803’
          or ‘Oxford Text Archive text number 1243’. These should be placed in an <gi>altId</gi>
          element within the <gi>meiHead</gi> element. International Standard Serial Numbers (ISSN),
          International Standard Book Numbers (ISBN), and other internationally agreed upon standard
          numbers that uniquely identify an item, should be treated in the same way, rather than as
          specialized bibliographic notes.</item>
      </list>
      <p>Nevertheless, the <gi>notesStmt</gi> element may be used to record potentially significant
        details about the file and its features, e.g.:</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <item>dates, when they are relevant to the content or condition of the computer file: e.g.
          ‘manual dated 1983’, ‘Interview wave I: Apr. 1989; wave II: Jan. 1990’</item>
        <item>names of persons or bodies connected with the technical production, administration, or
          consulting functions of the effort which produced the file, if these are not named in
          statements of responsibility in the title or edition statements of the file description:
          e.g. ‘Historical commentary provided by Mark Cohen’</item>
        <item>availability of the file in an additional medium or information not already recorded
          about the availability of documentation: e.g. ‘User manual is loose-leaf in eleven
          paginated sections’</item>
        <item>language of work and abstract, if not encoded in the langUsage element, e.g. ‘Text in
          English with summaries in French and German’</item>
        <item>The unique name assigned to a serial by the International Serials Data System (ISDS),
          if not encoded in an identifier</item>
        <item>lists of related publications, either describing the source itself, or concerned with
          the creation or use of the electronic work, e.g. ‘Texts used in Burrows (1987)’</item>
      </list>
      <p>Each such item of information may be tagged using the general-purpose <gi>annot</gi>
        element. Groups of annotations are contained within the <gi>notesStmt</gi> element, as in
        the following example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <notesStmt>
          <annot>Historical commentary provided by John Smith.</annot>
          <annot>OCR scanning done at University of Virginia.</annot>
        </notesStmt>
      </egXML>
      <p>There are advantages, however, to encoding such information with more precise elements
        elsewhere in the MEI header, when such elements are available. For example, the notes above
        might be encoded as follows:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <titleStmt>
          <title>…</title>
          <respStmt>
            <persName>John Smith</persName>
            <resp>historical commentary</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <respStmt>
            <orgName>University of Virginia</orgName>
            <resp>OCR scanning</resp>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="header1.1.7" type="div3">
      <head>Source description</head>
      <p>The <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element is the seventh and final component of the <gi>fileDesc</gi>
        element. In MEI, <gi>sourceDesc</gi> is a grouping element containing one or more
          <gi>source</gi> elements, each of which records details of a source from which a computer
        file is derived. This might be a printed text or manuscript, another computer file, an audio
        or video recording of some kind, or a combination of these. An electronic file may also have
        no source, if what is being cataloged is an original text created in electronic form.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="sourceDesc"/>
          <specDesc key="source"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>source</gi> element may contain nothing more than a notes statement giving a simple
        prose description or a brief note stating that the document has no source:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <sourceDesc>
          <source>
            <notesStmt>
              <annot>Born digital.</annot>
            </notesStmt>
          </source>
        </sourceDesc>
      </egXML>
      <p>Alternatively, it may contain a more detailed bibliographic description:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <sourceDesc>
          <source>
            <notesStmt>
              <annot>The first folio of Shakespeare, prepared by Charlton Hinman (The Norton
                Facsimile, 1968)</annot>
            </notesStmt>
          </source>
        </sourceDesc>
      </egXML>
      <p>or with still more elaboration:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <sourceDesc>
          <source xml:lang="fr">
            <titleStmt>
              <title>Martin, l'enfant trouvé</title>
              <title type="sub">Mémoires d'un valet de chambre</title>
              <respStmt>
                <name>Eugène Sue</name>
              </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <pubStmt>
              <geogName>Bruxelles et Leipzig</geogName>
              <respStmt>
                <name>C. Muquardt</name>
                <role>publisher</role>
              </respStmt>
              <date when="1846">1846</date>
            </pubStmt>
          </source>
        </sourceDesc>
      </egXML>
      <p>The @decls attribute described in section <ptr target="#"/> Associating Contextual
        Information with a Text may be used to associate parts of the encoded text with the
        bibliographic element from which it derives.</p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="header1.1.8" type="div3">
      <head>Computer files derived from other computer files</head>
      <p>If a computer file (call it B) is derived not from a printed source but from another
        computer file (call it A) which includes an MEI file header, then the source text of
        computer file B is another computer file, A. The four sections of A's file header will need
        to be incorporated into the new header for B in slightly differing ways, as listed
        below:</p>
      <list type="gloss">
        <label><gi>fileDesc</gi></label>
        <item>A's file description should be copied into the sourceDesc section of B's file
          description, enclosed within a biblFull element</item>
        <label><gi>workDesc</gi></label>
        <item>A's workDesc should be copied into B's, in principle unchanged; it may however be
          expanded by project-specific information relating to B.</item>
        <label><gi>encodingDesc</gi></label>
        <item>A's encoding practice may or (more likely) may not be the same as B's. Since the
          object of the encoding description is to define the relationship between the current file
          and its source, in principle only changes in encoding practice between A and B need be
          documented in B. The relationship between A and its source(s) is then only recoverable
          from the original header of A. In practice it may be more convenient to create a new
          complete encodingDesc for B based on A's.</item>
        <label><gi>revisionDesc</gi></label>
        <item>B is a new computer file, and should therefore have a new revision description. If,
          however, it is felt useful to include some information from A's revisionDesc, for example
          dates of major updates or versions, such information must be clearly marked as relating to
          A rather than to B.</item>
      </list>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="header1.2" type="div2">
    <head>Encoding description</head>
    <p>The <gi>encodingDesc</gi> element is the second major subdivision of the MEI header. It
      specifies the methods and editorial principles which governed the transcription or encoding of
      the source material. Though not formally required, its use is highly recommended.</p>
    <p>
      <specDesc key="encodingDesc"/>
    </p>
    <p>The encoding description may contain elements taken from the model.encodingPart class. By
      default, this class makes available the following elements:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="appInfo"/>
        <specDesc key="editorialDecl"/>
        <specDesc key="projectDesc"/>
        <specDesc key="samplingDecl"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>Each of these elements is further described in the appropriate section below.</p>
    <div xml:id="header1.2.1" type="div3">
      <head>Application information</head>
      <p>It is sometimes convenient to store information relating to the processing of an encoded
        resource within its header. Typical uses for such information might be:</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <item>to allow an application to discover that it has previously opened or edited a file,
          and what version of itself was used to do that;</item>
        <item>to show (through a date) which application last edited the file to allow for diagnosis
          of any problems that might have been caused by that application;</item>
        <item>to allow users to discover information about an application used to edit the
          file</item>
        <item>to allow the application to declare an interest in elements of the file which it has
          edited, so that other applications or human editors may be more wary of making changes to
          those sections of the file.</item>
      </list>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="appInfo"/>
          <specDesc key="application" atts="version"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>Each <gi>application</gi> element identifies the current state of one software application
        with regard to the current file. This element is a member of the att.datable class, which
        provides a variety of attributes for associating this state with a date and time, or a
        temporal range. The @xml:id and @version attributes should be used to uniquely identify the
        application and its major version number (for example, 'ImageMarkupTool 1.5'). It is not
        intended that a software application should add a new <gi>application</gi> element each time
        it touches the file.</p>
      <p>The following example shows how these elements might be used to document the fact that
        version 1.5 of an application called ‘Image Markup Tool’ has an interest in two parts of a
        document which was last saved on June 6 2006. The parts concerned are accessible at the URLs
        given as target for the two <gi>ptr</gi> elements.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <appInfo>
          <application xml:id="ImageMarkupTool" version="1.5" notAfter="2006-06-01">
            <name>Image Markup Tool</name>
            <ptr target="#P1"/>
            <ptr target="#P2"/>
          </application>
        </appInfo>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="header1.2.2" type="div3">
      <head>Declaration of editorial principles</head>
      <p>The <gi>editorialDecl</gi> element is used to provide details of the editorial practices
        applied during the encoding of a musical text.</p>
      <p>It may contain a prose description only, or one or more of a set of specialized elements,
        members of the MEI model.editorialDeclPart class. Where an encoder wishes to record an
        editorial policy not specified above, this may be done by adding a new element to this
        class, using the mechanisms discussed in chapter <ptr target="#"/> Personalization and
        Customization.</p>
      <p>Some of these policy elements carry attributes to support automated processing of certain
        well-defined editorial decisions; all of them contain a prose description of the editorial
        principles adopted with respect to the particular feature concerned. Examples of the kinds
        of questions which these descriptions are intended to answer are given in the list
        below.</p>
      <list type="gloss">
        <label>correction</label>
        <item>
          <specDesc key="correction" atts="corrlevel"/>
          <p>@method indicates the method adopted to indicate normalizations within the text.</p>
          <p>Was the text corrected during or after data capture? If so, were corrections made
            silently or are they marked using the tags described in section <ptr target="#"/> Simple
            Editorial Changes? What principles have been adopted with respect to omissions,
            truncations, dubious corrections, alternate readings, false starts, repetitions,
            etc.?</p></item>
        <label>interpretation</label>
        <item>
          <specDesc key="interpretation"/>
          <p>Has any analytic or ‘interpretive’ information been provided — that is, information
            which is felt to be non-obvious, or potentially contentious? If so, how was it
            generated? How was it encoded?</p></item>
        <label>normalization</label>
        <item>
          <specDesc key="normalization"/>
          <p>@method indicates the method adopted to indicate normalizations within the text.</p>
          <p>Was the text normalized, for example by regularizing any non-standard spellings,
            dialect forms, etc.? If so, were normalizations performed silently or are they marked
            using the tags described in section <ptr target="#"/> Simple Editorial Changes? What
            authority was used for the regularization? Also, what principles were used when
            normalizing numbers to provide the standard values for the @value attribute described in
            section <ptr target="#"/> Numbers and Measures and what format used for them?</p></item>
        <label>segmentation</label>
        <item>
          <specDesc key="segmentation"/>
          <p>How is the musical text segmented? If mdiv and/or section elements have been used to
            divide up the music for analysis, how are they marked and how was the segmentation
            arrived at?</p></item>
        <label>stdVals</label>
        <item>
          <specDesc key="stdVals"/>
          <p>In most cases, attributes bearing standardized values should conform to a defined
            datatype. In cases where this is not appropriate, this element may be used to describe
            the standardization methods underlying the values supplied.</p></item>
      </list>
      <p>Any information about the editorial principles applied not falling under one of the above
        headings should be recorded in a distinct list of items. Experience shows that a full record
        should be kept of decisions relating to editorial principles and encoding practice, both for
        future users of the text and for the project which produced the text in the first instance.
        Some simple examples follow:</p>
      <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <editorialDecl>
      <segmentation>
      <p>
      <gi>s</gi> elements mark orthographic sentences and are numbered sequentially within
      their parent <gi>div</gi> element</p>
      </segmentation>
      <interpretation>
      <p>The part of speech analysis applied throughout section 4 was added by hand and has
      not been checked.</p>
      </interpretation>
      <correction>
      <p>Errors in transcription controlled by using the WordPerfect spelling checker.</p>
      </correction>
      <normalization source="http://szotar.sztaki.hu/webster/">
      <p>All words converted to Modern American spelling following Webster’s 9th Collegiate
      dictionary.</p>
      </normalization>
      <quotation marks="all" form="std">
      <p>All opening quotation marks represented by entity reference <ident type="ge"
      >odq</ident>; all closing quotation marks represented by entity reference <ident
      type="ge">cdq</ident>.</p>
      </quotation>
      </editorialDecl></egXML>-->
      <p>An editorial practices declaration which applies to more than one text or division of a
        text need not be repeated in the header of each text or division. Instead, the @decls
        attribute of each text (or subdivision of the text) to which it applies may be used to
        supply a cross-reference to the declaration, as further described in section <ptr target="#"
        /> Associating Contextual Information with a Text.</p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="header1.2.3" type="div3">
      <head>Project description</head>
      <p>The <gi>projectDesc</gi> element may be used to describe, in prose, the purpose for which a
        digital resource was created, together with any other relevant information concerning the
        process by which it was assembled or collected. This is of particular importance for corpora
        or miscellaneous collections, but may be of use for any text, for example to explain why one
        kind of encoding practice has been followed rather than another.</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="projectDesc"/>
      </p>
      <p>For example:</p>
      <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
      <p>Texts collected for use in the Claremont Shakespeare Clinic, June 1990.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc></egXML>-->
    </div>
    <div xml:id="header1.2.4" type="div3">
      <head>Sampling Declaration</head>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="header1.3" type="div2">
    <head>Work Description</head>
    <p>The <gi>workDesc</gi> element is the third major subdivision of the MEI Header. It is an
      optional element, the purpose of which is to enable information characterizing various
      descriptive aspects of a text or a corpus to be recorded within a single unified framework. </p>
    <p>
      <specDesc key="workDesc"/>
    </p>
    <p>The <gi>workDesc</gi> element contains elements taken from the macro.workPart class. In the
      simplest case, this means it may contain the following elements:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="history"/>
        <specDesc key="langUsage"/>
        <specDesc key="key"/>
        <specDesc key="tempo"/>
        <specDesc key="meter"/>
        <specDesc key="perfMedium"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <div>
      <head>Title statement</head>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>History</head>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>Language usage</head>
      <p>The <gi>langUsage</gi> element is used within the <gi>workDesc</gi> element to describe the
        languages, sublanguages, registers, dialects, etc. represented within a text. It contains
        one or more language elements, each of which provides information about a single language,
        notably the quantity of that language present in the text.
        <!--Note that this element should not be used
          to supply information about any non-standard characters or glyphs used by this language;
          such information should be recorded in the charDecl element in the encoding description
          (see further Representation of Non-standard Characters and Glyphs).--></p>
      <p><gi>langUsage</gi> (language usage) describes the languages, sublanguages, registers,
        dialects, etc. represented within a text.</p>
      <p><gi>language</gi> characterizes a single language or sublanguage used within a text.@usage
        specifies the approximate percentage (by volume) of the text which uses this language.</p>
      <p>@ident (identifier) Supplies a language code constructed as defined in BCP 47 which is used
        to identify the language documented by this element, and which is referenced by the global
        @xml:lang attribute.</p>
      <p>A language element may be supplied for each different language used in a document. If used,
        its @ident attribute should specify an appropriate language identifier, as further discussed
        in section vi.1. Language identification. This is particularly important if extended
        language identifiers have been used as the value of @xml:lang attributes elsewhere in the
        document.</p>
      <p>Here is an example of the use of this element:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <langUsage>
          <language ident="fr-CA" usage="60">Québecois</language>
          <language ident="en-CA" usage="20">Canadian business English</language>
          <language ident="en-GB" usage="20">British English</language>
        </langUsage></egXML>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>Key, tempo, and meter</head>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>Performance medium</head>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>Notes statement</head>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>Classification</head>
      <p>The second component of the core <gi>workDesc</gi> element is the <gi>classification</gi>
        element. This element is used to classify a text according to one or more of the following
        methods:</p>
      <list type="simple">
        <item>by reference to a recognized international classification such as the Dewey Decimal
          Classification, the Universal Decimal Classification, the Colon Classification, the
          Library of Congress Classification, or any other system widely used in library and
          documentation work</item>
        <item>by providing a set of keywords, as provided for example by British Library or Library
          of Congress Cataloguing in Publication data</item>
        <item>by referencing any other taxonomy of text categories recognized in the field
          concerned, or peculiar to the material in hand; this may include one based on recurring
          sets of values for the situational parameters defined in section <ptr target="#"/> The
          Text Description, or the demographic elements described in section <ptr target="#"/> The
          Participant Description</item>
      </list>
      <p>The last of these may be particularly important for dealing with existing corpora or
        collections, both as a means of avoiding the expense or inconvenience of reclassification
        and as a means of documenting the organizing principles of such materials.</p>
      <p>The following elements are provided for this purpose:</p>
      <p><gi>keywords</gi> contains a list of keywords or phrases identifying the topic or nature of
        a text.@scheme identifies the controlled vocabulary within which the set of keywords
        concerned is defined.</p>
      <p><gi>classCode</gi> (classification code) contains the classification code used for this
        text in some standard classification system.@scheme identifies the classification system or
        taxonomy in use.</p>
      <p><gi>catRef</gi> (category reference) specifies one or more defined categories within some
        taxonomy or text typology.</p>
      <p>The keywords element simply categorizes an individual text by supplying a list of keywords
        which may describe its topic or subject matter, its form, date, etc. In some schemes, the
        order of items in the list is significant, for example, from major topic to minor; in
        others, the list has an organized substructure of its own. No recommendations are made here
        as to which method is to be preferred. Wherever possible, such keywords should be taken from
        a recognized source, such as the British Library/Library of Congress Cataloguing in
        Publication data in the case of printed books, or a published thesaurus appropriate to the
        field.</p>
      <p>The @scheme attribute should be used to indicate the source of the keywords used. If the
        keywords are taken from some externally defined authority which is available online, this
        attribute should point directly to it, as in the following examples:</p>
      <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <keywords scheme="http://classificationweb.net">
        <term>Babbage, Charles</term>
        <term>Mathematicians - Great Britain - Biography</term>
        </keywords></egXML>-->
      <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <keywords scheme="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">
        <term>English literature -\- History and criticism -\- Data processing.</term>
        <term>English literature -\- History and criticism -\- Theory, etc.</term>
        <term>English language -\- Style -\- Data processing.</term>
        <term>Style, Literary -\- Data processing.</term>
        </keywords></egXML>-->
      <p>If the authority file is not available online, but is generally recognized and commonly
        cited, a bibliographic description for it should be supplied within the taxonomy element
        described in section <ptr target="#"/> The Classification Declaration; the @scheme attribute
        may then reference that taxonomy element by means of its identifier in the usual way:</p>
      <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <keywords scheme="#welch">
        <term>ceremonials</term>
        <term>fairs</term>
        <term>street life</term>
        </keywords>
        <!-\- elsewhere in the document -\->
        <taxonomy xml:id="welch">
        <bibl>
        <title>Notes on London Municipal Literature, and a Suggested Scheme for Its
        Classification</title>
        <author>Charles Welch</author>
        <edition>1895</edition>
        </bibl>
        </taxonomy></egXML>-->
      <p>Alternatively, if the keyword vocabulary itself is locally defined, the @scheme attribute
        will point to the local definition, which will typically be held in a taxonomy element
        within the classDecl part of the encoding description (see section <ptr target="#"/> The
        Classification Declaration).</p>
      <p>The <gi>classCode</gi> element also categorizes an individual text, by supplying a
        numerical or other code rather than descriptive terms. Such codes constitute a recognized
        classification scheme, such as the Dewey Decimal Classification. The @scheme attribute is
        used to indicate the source of the classification scheme in the same way as for keywords:
        this may be a pointer of any kind, either to an MEI element, possibly in the current
        document, as in the keywords examples above, or to some canonical source for the scheme, as
        in the following example:</p>
      <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <classCode scheme="http://www.udcc.org/udcsummary/php/index.php">005.756</classCode>
        </egXML>-->
      <!--<p>The catRef element categorizes an individual text by pointing to one or more category
        elements using the @target attribute, which it inherits from the att.pointing class. The
        category element (which is fully described in section <ptr target="#"/> The Classification
        Declaration) holds information about a particular classification or category within a
        given taxonomy. Each such category must have a unique identifier, which may be supplied as
        the value of the @target attribute for catRef elements which are regarded as falling
        within the category indicated.</p>-->
      <!--<p>A text may, of course, fall into more than one category, in which case more than one
        identifier will be supplied as the value for the @target attribute on the catRef element,
        as in the following example:</p>-->
      <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <catRef target="#b.a4 #b.d2"/></egXML>-->
      <p>The @scheme attribute may be supplied to specify the taxonomy to which the categories
        identified by the target attribute belong, if this is not adequately conveyed by the
        resource pointed to. For example,</p>
      <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <catRef target="#b.a4 #b.d2" scheme="http://www.example.com/browncorpus"/>
        <catRef target="http://www.example.com/SUC/#A45"/>
        </egXML>-->
      <p>Here the same text has been classified as of categories 'b.a4' and 'b.d2' within the Brown
        classification scheme (presumed to be available from http://www.example.com/browncorpus),
        and as of category ‘A45’ within the SUC classification scheme documented at the URL
        given.</p>
      <!--<p>The distinction between the catRef and classCode elements is that the values used as
        identifying codes are exhaustively enumerated, typically with the header, for the former,
        while the latter may be used to indicate a more open ended or descriptive classification
        system.</p>-->
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>Cast list</head>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>Incipit</head>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>Contents note</head>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>Related item</head>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="header1.4" type="div2">
    <head>Revision description</head>
    <p>The final sub-element of the MEI header, the <gi>revisionDesc</gi> element, provides a
      detailed change log in which each change made to a text may be recorded. Its use is optional
      but highly recommended. It provides essential information for the administration of large
      numbers of files which are being updated, corrected, or otherwise modified as well as
      extremely useful documentation for files being passed from researcher to researcher or system
      to system. Without change logs, it is easy to confuse different versions of a file, or to
      remain unaware of small but important changes made in the file by some earlier link in the
      chain of distribution. No change should be made in any MEI-conformant file without
      corresponding entries being made in the change log.</p>
    <p><gi>revisionDesc</gi> (revision description) summarizes the revision history for a file.</p>
    <p><gi>change</gi> summarizes a particular change or correction made to a particular version of
      an electronic text which is shared between several researchers.</p>
    <p>The main purpose of the revision description is to record changes in the text to which a
      header is prefixed. However, it is recommended MEI practice to include entries also for
      significant changes in the header itself (other than the revision description itself, of
      course). At the very least, an entry should be supplied indicating the date of creation of the
      header.</p>
    <p>The log consists of a list of entries, one for each change. This may be encoded using either
      the regular list element, as described in section <ptr target="#"/> Lists or as a series of
      special purpose change elements, each of which contains a more detailed description of the
      changes made. The attributes @when and @who are used to indicate the date of the change and
      the person responsible for it respectively. The description of the change itself can range
      from a simple phrase to a series of paragraphs. If a number is to be associated with one or
      more changes (for example, a revision number), the global @n attribute may be used to indicate
      it.</p>
    <p>It is recommended to give changes in reverse chronological order, most recent first.</p>
    <p>For example:</p>
    <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <revisionDesc>
      <change n="RCS:1.39" when="2007-08-08" who="#jwernimo.lrv">Changed <val>drama.verse</val>
      <gi>lg</gi>s to <gi>p</gi>s. <note>we have opened a discussion about the need for a new
      value for <att>type</att> of <gi>lg</gi>, <val>drama.free.verse</val>, in order to
      address the verse of Behn which is not in regular iambic pentameter. For the time
      being these instances are marked with a comment note until we are able to fully
      consider the best way to encode these instances.</note>
      </change>
      <change n="RCS:1.33" when="2007-06-28" who="#pcaton.xzc">Added <att>key</att> and
      <att>reg</att> to <gi>name</gi>s.</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.31" when="2006-12-04" who="#wgui.ner">Completed renovation.
      Validated.</change>
      </revisionDesc></egXML>-->
    <p>In the above example, the @who attributes point to respStmt elements which have been included
      earlier in the titleStmt of the same header:</p>
    <!--<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <titleStmt>
      <title>The Amorous Prince, or, the Curious Husband, 1671</title>
      <author>
      <persName ref="#abehn.aeh">Behn, Aphra</persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt xml:id="pcaton.xzc">
      <persName>Caton, Paul</persName>
      <resp>electronic publication editor</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt xml:id="wgui.ner">
      <persName>Gui, Weihsin</persName>
      <resp>encoder</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt xml:id="jwernimo.lrv">
      <persName>Wernimont, Jacqueline</persName>
      <resp>encoder</resp>
      </respStmt>
      </titleStmt></egXML>-->
    <p>There is however no requirement that the <gi>respStmt</gi> be used for this person, or that
      the elements indicated be contained within the same document. A project might for example
      maintain a separate document listing all of its personnel in which they were represented using
      the person element described in <ptr target="#"/> The Participant Description.</p>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="header1.5" type="div2">
    <head>Minimal and recommended header information</head>
    <p>The MEI header allows for the provision of a very large amount of information concerning the
      text itself, its source, its encodings, and revisions of it, as well as a wealth of
      descriptive information such as the languages it uses and the situation(s) in which it was
      produced, together with the setting and identity of participants within it. This diversity and
      richness reflects the diversity of uses to which it is envisaged that electronic texts
      conforming to these Guidelines will be put. It is emphatically not intended that all of the
      elements described above should be present in every MEI Header.</p>
    <p>The amount of encoding in a header will depend both on the nature and the intended use of the
      text. At one extreme, an encoder may expect that the header will be needed only to provide a
      bibliographic identification of the text adequate to local needs. At the other, wishing to
      ensure that their texts can be used for the widest range of applications, encoders will want
      to document as explicitly as possible both bibliographic and descriptive information, in such
      a way that no prior or ancillary knowledge about the text is needed in order to process it.
      The header in such a case will be very full, approximating to the kind of documentation often
      supplied in the form of a manual. Most texts will lie somewhere between these extremes;
      textual corpora in particular will tend more to the latter extreme. In the remainder of this
      section we demonstrate first the minimal, and next a commonly recommended, level of encoding
      for the bibliographic information held by the MEI header.</p>
    <p>Supplying only the minimal level of encoding required, the MEI header of a single text might
      look like the following example:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <meiHead>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Paine: Common sense, a machine-readable transcript</title>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>compiled by</resp>
              <name>Jon K Adams</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>Oxford Text Archive</distributor>
          </publicationStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>The complete writings of Thomas Paine, collected and edited by Phillip S. Foner
              (New York, Citadel Press, 1945)</bibl>
          </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
      </meiHead>
    </egXML>
    <p>The only mandatory component of the MEI Header is the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element. Within this,
        <gi>titleStmt</gi> and <gi>publicationStmt</gi> are required constituents. Within the title
      statement, a title is required, and an author should be specified, even if it is unknown, as
      should some additional statement of responsibility, here given by the respStmt element. Within
      the <gi>publicationStmt</gi>, a publisher, distributor, or other agency responsible for the
      file should be specified. Finally, the source description should contain at the least a
      loosely structured bibliographic citation identifying the source of the electronic text if (as
      is usually the case) there is one.</p>
    <p>We now present the same example header, expanded to include additionally recommended
      information, adequate for most bibliographic purposes, in particular to allow for the creation
      of an AACR2-conformant bibliographic record. We have also added information about the encoding
      principles used in this (imaginary) encoding, about the text itself (in the form of Library of
      Congress subject headings), and about the revision of the file.</p>
    <p><!--[Fuller MEI head example here]--></p>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="header1.6" type="div2"/>
  <div xml:id="header1.7" type="div2">
    <head>The MEI header module</head>
    <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:</p>
    <p>Module header: The MEI Header</p>
    <p>Elements defined: [list of MEI elements]</p>
    <p>The selection and combination of modules to form an MEI schema is described in <ptr
        target="#"/> Defining an MEI Schema.</p>
  </div>
</div>
