<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  © 2010 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs Unported License, 
  Version 3.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/.
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="header" n="0">
  <head>The MEI Header</head>
  <p>This chapter addresses the description of an encoded work so that the text itself, its source,
    its encoding, and its revisions are all thoroughly documented. Such documentation is necessary
    for scholars using the texts, for software processing them, and for catalogers in libraries and
    archives. Together these descriptions and declarations provide an electronic analog to the title
    page attached to a printed work. They also constitute an equivalent for the content of the code
    books or introductory manuals customarily accompanying electronic data sets.</p>
  <p>Every MEI-conformant text must carry such a set of descriptions, prefixed to it and encoded as
    described in this chapter. The set is known as the MEI header, tagged meiHead, and has four
    major parts: </p>
  <p>1. a file description, tagged fileDesc, containing a full bibliographical description of the
    computer file itself, from which a user of the text could derive a proper bibliographic
    citation, or which a librarian or archivist could use in creating a catalogue entry recording
    its presence within a library or archive. The term computer file here is to be understood as
    referring to the whole entity or document described by the header, even when this is stored in
    several distinct operating system files. The file description also includes information about
    the source or sources from which the electronic document was derived. The MEI elements used to
    encode the file description are described in section 2.2 The File Description below. </p>
  <p>2. an encoding description, tagged encodingDesc, which describes the relationship between an
    electronic text and its source or sources. It allows for detailed description of whether (or
    how) the text was normalized during transcription, how the encoder resolved ambiguities in the
    source, what levels of encoding or analysis were applied, and similar matters. The MEI elements
    used to encode the encoding description are described in section 2.3 The Encoding Description
    below. </p>
  <p>3. a text profile, tagged workDesc, containing classification and contextual information about
    the text, such as its subject matter, the situation in which it was produced, the individuals
    described by or participating in producing it, and so forth. Such a text profile is of
    particular use in highly structured composite texts such as corpora or language collections,
    where it is often highly desirable to enforce a controlled descriptive vocabulary or to perform
    retrievals from a body of text in terms of text type or origin. The text profile may however be
    of use in any form of automatic text processing. The MEI elements used to encode the work
    description are described in section 2.4 The Work Description below. </p>
  <p>4. a revision history, tagged revisionDesc, which allows the encoder to provide a history of
    changes made during the development of the electronic text. The revision history is important
    for version control and for resolving questions about the history of a file. The MEI elements
    used to encode the revision description are described in section 2.5 The Revision Description
    below.</p>
  <p>An MEI header can be a very large and complex object, or it may be a very simple one. Some
    application areas (for example, the construction of language corpora and the transcription of
    spoken texts) may require more specialized and detailed information than others. The present
    proposals therefore define both a core set of elements (all of which may be used without
    formality in any MEI header) and some additional elements which become available within the
    header as the result of including additional specialized modules within the schema. When the
    module for language corpora (described in chapter 15 Language Corpora) is in use, for example,
    several additional elements are available, as further detailed in that chapter. </p>
  <p>The next section of the present chapter briefly introduces the overall structure of the header
    and the kinds of data it may contain. This is followed by a detailed description of all the
    constituent elements which may be used in the core header. Section 2.6 Minimal and Recommended
    Headers, at the end of the present chapter, discusses the recommended content of a minimal MEI
    header and its relation to standard library cataloging practices.</p>
  <p>3.1 Organization</p>
  <p>3.1.1 Components</p>
  <p>The meiHead element should be clearly distinguished from the front matter of the text itself
    (for which see section 4.5 Front Matter). A composite text, such as a corpus or collection, may
    contain several headers, as further discussed below. In the general case, however, an
    MEI-conformant text will contain a single meiHead element, followed by a single text or
    facsimile element, or both. </p>
  <p>The header element has the following description: </p>
  <p>&lt;meiHead&gt; (MEI Header) supplies the descriptive and declarative information making up an
    electronic title page prefixed to every MEI-conformant text.@type specifies the kind of document
    to which the header is attached, for example whether it is a corpus or individual text. </p>
  <p>As discussed above, the meiHead element has four principal components: </p>
  <p>&lt;fileDesc&gt; (file description) contains a bibliographic description of an electronic
    file.</p>
  <p>&lt;encodingDesc&gt; (encoding description) documents the relationship between an electronic
    text and the source or sources from which it was derived.</p>
  <p>&lt;workDesc&gt; (text-work description) provides a detailed description of non-bibliographic
    aspects of a text, specifically the languages and sublanguages used, the situation in which it
    was produced, the participants and their setting.</p>
  <p>&lt;revisionDesc&gt; (revision description) summarizes the revision history for a file.</p>
  <p>Of these, only the fileDesc element is required in all MEI headers; the others are optional.
    Only one of the four components of the MEI header (the fileDesc) is mandatory, and it also has
    some mandatory components, as further discussed in 2.2 The File Description below. The smallest
    possible valid MEI Header thus looks like this: </p>
  <p>&lt;meiHead&gt; &lt;fileDesc&gt; &lt;titleStmt&gt; &lt;title&gt;&lt;!-- title of the
    resource... --&gt; &lt;/title&gt; &lt;/titleStmt&gt; &lt;publicationStmt&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Information about distribution of the resource)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/publicationStmt&gt;
    &lt;sourceDesc&gt; &lt;p&gt;(Information about source from which the resource derives)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/sourceDesc&gt; &lt;/fileDesc&gt;&lt;/meiHead&gt;</p>
  <p>The content of the elements making up an MEI Header may be given in any language, not
    necessarily that of the text to which the header applies, and not necessarily English. As
    elsewhere, the @xml:lang attribute should be used at an appropriate level to specify the
    language. For example, in the following schematic example, an English text has been given a
    French header: </p>
  <p>&lt;MEI&gt; &lt;meiHead xml:lang="fra"&gt;&lt;!-- ... --&gt; &lt;/meiHead&gt; &lt;text
    xml:lang="eng"&gt;&lt;!-- ... --&gt; &lt;/text&gt;&lt;/MEI&gt;</p>
  <p>In the case of language corpora or collections, it may be desirable to record header
    information either at the level of the individual components in the corpus or collection, or at
    the level of the corpus or collection itself (more details concerning the tagging of composite
    texts are given in section 15 Language Corpora, which should be read in conjunction with the
    current chapter). The @type attribute may be used to indicate whether the header applies to a
    corpus or a single text. A corpus may thus take the form: </p>
  <p>&lt;meiCorpus&gt; &lt;meiHead type="corpus"&gt;&lt;!-- corpus-level metadata here --&gt;
    &lt;/meiHead&gt; &lt;MEI&gt; &lt;meiHead type="text"&gt;&lt;!-- metadata specific to this text
    here --&gt; &lt;/meiHead&gt; &lt;text&gt;&lt;!-- ... --&gt; &lt;/text&gt; &lt;/MEI&gt;
    &lt;MEI&gt; &lt;meiHead type="text"&gt;&lt;!-- metadata specific to this text here --&gt;
    &lt;/meiHead&gt; &lt;text&gt;&lt;!-- ... --&gt; &lt;/text&gt; &lt;/MEI&gt;&lt;/meiCorpus&gt;</p>
  <p>3.1.2 Types of header content</p>
  <p>The elements occurring within the MEI header may contain several types of content; the
    following list indicates how these types of content are described in the following sections: </p>
  <p>free prose </p>
  <p>Most elements contain simple running prose at some level. Many elements may contain either
    prose (possibly organized into paragraphs) or more specific elements, which themselves contain
    prose. In this chapter's descriptions of element content, the phrase prose description should be
    understood to imply a series of paragraphs, each marked as a p element. The word phrase, by
    contrast, should be understood to imply character data, interspersed as need be with
    phrase-level elements, but not organized into paragraphs. For more information on paragraphs,
    highlighted phrases, lists, etc., see section 3.1 Paragraphs. </p>
  <p>grouping elements </p>
  <p>Elements whose names end with the suffix Stmt (e.g. editionStmt, titleStmt) usually enclose a
    group of specialized elements recording some structured information. In the case of the
    bibliographic elements, the suffix Stmt is used in names of elements corresponding to the
    ‘areas’ of the International Standard Bibliographic Description.4 In most cases grouping
    elements may contain prose descriptions as an alternative to the set of specialized elements,
    thus allowing the encoder to choose whether or not the information concerned should be presented
    in a structured form or in prose. </p>
  <p>declarations </p>
  <p>Elements whose names end with the suffix Decl (e.g. tagsDecl, refsDecl) enclose information
    about specific encoding practices applied in the electronic text; often these practices are
    described in coded form. Typically, such information takes the form of a series of declarations,
    identifying a code with some more complex structure or description. A declaration which applies
    to more than one text or division of a text need not be repeated in the header of each such text
    or subdivision. Instead, the @decls attribute of each text (or subdivision of the text) to which
    the declaration applies may be used to supply a cross-reference to it, as further described in
    section 15.3 Associating Contextual Information with a Text. </p>
  <p>descriptions </p>
  <p>Elements whose names end with the suffix Desc (e.g. settingDesc, projectDesc) contain a prose
    description, possibly, but not necessarily, organized under some specific headings by suggested
    sub-elements.</p>
  <p>3.1.3 Model classes</p>
  <p>The MEI Header provides a very rich collection of metadata categories, but makes no claim to be
    exhaustive. It is certainly the case that individual projects may wish to record specialized
    metadata which either does not fit within one of the predefined categories identified by the MEI
    Header or requires a more specialized element structure than is proposed here. To overcome this
    problem, the encoder may elect to define additional elements using the customization methods
    discussed in 23.2 Personalization and Customization. The MEI class system makes such
    customizations simpler to effect and easier to use in interchange. </p>
  <p>These classes are specific to parts of the header: </p>
  <p>[MEI classes used in the header using the following example as a guide]</p>
  <p>
    <hi rend="strikethrough">model.applicationLike groups elements used to record
      application-specific information about a document in its header.</hi>
  </p>
  <p>3.2 File description</p>
  <p>This section describes the fileDesc element, which is the first component of the meiHead
    element. </p>
  <p>The bibliographic description of a machine-readable or digital text resembles in structure that
    of a book, an article, or any other kind of textual object. The file description element of the
    MEI header has therefore been closely modeled on existing standards in library cataloging; it
    should thus provide enough information to allow users to give standard bibliographic references
    to the electronic text, and to allow cataloguers to catalogue it. Bibliographic citations
    occurring elsewhere in the header, and also in the text itself, are derived from the same model
    (on bibliographic citations in general, see further section 3.11 Bibliographic Citations and
    References). See further section 2.7 Note for Library Cataloguers. </p>
  <p>The bibliographic description of an electronic text should be supplied by the mandatory
    fileDesc element: </p>
  <p>&lt;fileDesc&gt; (file description) contains a full bibliographic description of an electronic
    file.</p>
  <p>The fileDesc element contains three mandatory elements and four optional elements, each of
    which is described in more detail in sections 2.2.1 The Title Statement to 2.2.6 The Notes
    Statement below. These elements are listed below in the order in which they must be given within
    the fileDesc element. </p>
  <p>&lt;titleStmt&gt; (title statement) groups information about the title of a work and those
    responsible for its intellectual content.</p>
  <p>&lt;editionStmt&gt; (edition statement) groups information relating to one edition of a
    text.</p>
  <p>&lt;extent&gt; describes the approximate size of a text as stored on some carrier medium,
    whether digital or non-digital, specified in any convenient units.</p>
  <p>&lt;publicationStmt&gt; (publication statement) groups information concerning the publication
    or distribution of an electronic or other text. </p>
  <p>&lt;seriesStmt&gt; (series statement) groups information about the series, if any, to which a
    publication belongs.</p>
  <p>&lt;notesStmt&gt; (notes statement) collects together any notes providing information about a
    text additional to that recorded in other parts of the bibliographic description.</p>
  <p>&lt;sourceDesc&gt; (source description) describes the source from which an electronic text was
    derived or generated, typically a bibliographic description in the case of a digitized text, or
    a phrase such as "born digital" for a text which has no previous existence.</p>
  <p>A complete file description containing all possible sub-elements might look like this: </p>
  <p>&lt;meiHead&gt; &lt;fileDesc&gt; &lt;titleStmt&gt; &lt;title&gt;&lt;!-- title of the resource
    --&gt; &lt;/title&gt; &lt;/titleStmt&gt; &lt;editionStmt&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- information about
    the edition of the resource --&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/editionStmt&gt; &lt;extent&gt;&lt;!--
    description of the size of the resource --&gt; &lt;/extent&gt; &lt;publicationStmt&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- information about the distribution of the resource --&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/publicationStmt&gt; &lt;seriesStmt&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- information about any series to
    which the resource belongs --&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/seriesStmt&gt; &lt;notesStmt&gt;
    &lt;note&gt;&lt;!-- notes on other aspects of the resource --&gt; &lt;/note&gt;
    &lt;/notesStmt&gt; &lt;sourceDesc&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- information about the source from which
    the resource was derived --&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/sourceDesc&gt;
    &lt;/fileDesc&gt;&lt;/meiHead&gt;</p>
  <p>Of these elements, only the titleStmt, publicationStmt, and sourceDesc are required; the others
    may be omitted unless considered useful.</p>
  <p>3.2.1 Title statement</p>
  <p>The titleStmt element is the first component of the fileDesc element, and is mandatory: </p>
  <p>&lt;titleStmt&gt; (title statement) groups information about the title of a work and those
    responsible for its intellectual content.</p>
  <p>It contains the title given to the electronic work, together with one or more optional
    statements of responsibility which identify the encoder, editor, author, compiler, or other
    parties responsible for it: </p>
  <p>&lt;title&gt; contains a title for any kind of work.</p>
  <p>&lt;author&gt; in a bibliographic reference, contains the name(s) of the author(s), personal or
    corporate, of a work; for example in the same form as that provided by a recognized
    bibliographic name authority. </p>
  <p>&lt;editor&gt; secondary statement of responsibility for a bibliographic item, for example the
    name of an individual, institution or organization, (or of several such) acting as editor,
    compiler, translator, etc. </p>
  <p>&lt;sponsor&gt; specifies the name of a sponsoring organization or institution.</p>
  <p>&lt;funder&gt; (funding body) specifies the name of an individual, institution, or organization
    responsible for the funding of a project or text.</p>
  <p>&lt;principal&gt; (principal researcher) supplies the name of the principal researcher
    responsible for the creation of an electronic text.</p>
  <p>&lt;respStmt&gt; (statement of responsibility) supplies a statement of responsibility for the
    intellectual content of a text, edition, recording, or series, where the specialized elements
    for authors, editors, etc. do not suffice or do not apply.</p>
  <p>&lt;resp&gt; (responsibility) contains a phrase describing the nature of a person's
    intellectual responsibility.</p>
  <p>&lt;name&gt; (name, proper noun) contains a proper noun or noun phrase.</p>
  <p>The title element contains the chief name of the electronic work, including any alternative
    title or subtitles it may have. It may be repeated, if the work has more than one title (perhaps
    in different languages) and takes whatever form is considered appropriate by its creator. Where
    the electronic work is derived from an existing source text, it is strongly recommended that the
    title for the former should be derived from the latter, but clearly distinguishable from it, for
    example by the addition of a phrase such as ‘: an electronic transcription’ or ‘a digital
    edition’. This will distinguish the electronic work from the source text in citations and in
    catalogues which contain descriptions of both types of material. </p>
  <p>The electronic work will also have an external name (its ‘filename’ or ‘data set name’) or
    reference number on the computer system where it resides at any time. This name is likely to
    change frequently, as new copies of the file are made on the computer system. Its form is
    entirely dependent on the particular computer system in use and thus cannot always easily be
    transferred from one system to another. Moreover, a given work may be composed of many files.
    For these reasons, these Guidelines strongly recommend that such names should not be used as the
    title for any electronic work. </p>
  <p>Helpful guidance on the formulation of useful descriptive titles in difficult cases may be
    found in the Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules (Gorman and Winkler, 1978, chapter 25) or in
    equivalent national-level bibliographical documentation. </p>
  <p>The elements author, editor, sponsor, funder, and principal, are specializations of the more
    general respStmt element. These elements are used to provide the statements of responsibility
    which identify the person(s) responsible for the intellectual or artistic content of an item and
    any corporate bodies from which it emanates. </p>
  <p>Any number of such statements may occur within the title statement. At a minimum, identify the
    author of the text and (where appropriate) the creator of the file. If the bibliographic
    description is for a corpus, identify the creator of the corpus. Optionally include also names
    of others involved in the transcription or elaboration of the text, sponsors, and funding
    agencies. The name of the person responsible for physical data input need not normally be
    recorded, unless that person is also intellectually responsible for some aspect of the creation
    of the file. </p>
  <p>Where the person whose responsibility is to be documented is not an author, sponsor, funding
    body, or principal researcher, the respStmt element should be used. This has two subcomponents:
    a name element identifying a responsible individual or organization, and a resp element
    indicating the nature of the responsibility. No specific recommendations are made at this time
    as to appropriate content for the resp: it should make clear the nature of the responsibility
    concerned, as in the examples below. </p>
  <p>Names given may be personal names or corporate names. Give all names in the form in which the
    persons or bodies wish to be publicly cited. This would usually be the fullest form of the name,
    including first names.5 </p>
  <p>Examples: </p>
  <p>&lt;titleStmt&gt; &lt;title&gt;Capgrave's Life of St. John Norbert: a machine-readable
    transcription&lt;/title&gt; &lt;respStmt&gt; &lt;resp&gt;compiled by&lt;/resp&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;P.J. Lucas&lt;/name&gt; &lt;/respStmt&gt;&lt;/titleStmt&gt;</p>
  <p>&lt;titleStmt&gt; &lt;title&gt;Two stories by Edgar Allen Poe: electronic version&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;author&gt;Poe, Edgar Allen (1809-1849)&lt;/author&gt; &lt;respStmt&gt; &lt;resp&gt;compiled
    by&lt;/resp&gt; &lt;name&gt;James D. Benson&lt;/name&gt; &lt;/respStmt&gt;&lt;/titleStmt&gt;</p>
  <p>&lt;titleStmt&gt; &lt;title&gt;Yogadarśanam (arthāt yogasūtrapūṭhaḥ): a digital
    edition.&lt;/title&gt; &lt;title&gt;The Yogasūtras of Patañjali: a digital
    edition.&lt;/title&gt; &lt;funder&gt;Wellcome Institute for the History of
    Medicine&lt;/funder&gt; &lt;principal&gt;Dominik Wujastyk&lt;/principal&gt; &lt;respStmt&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;Wieslaw Mical&lt;/name&gt; &lt;resp&gt;data entry and proof correction&lt;/resp&gt;
    &lt;/respStmt&gt; &lt;respStmt&gt; &lt;name&gt;Jan Hajic&lt;/name&gt; &lt;resp&gt;conversion to
    MEI-conformant markup&lt;/resp&gt; &lt;/respStmt&gt;&lt;/titleStmt&gt;</p>
  <p>3.2.2 Edition statement</p>
  <p>The editionStmt element is the second component of the fileDesc element. It is optional but
    recommended. </p>
  <p>&lt;editionStmt&gt; (edition statement) groups information relating to one edition of a
    text.</p>
  <p>It contains either phrases or more specialized elements identifying the edition and those
    responsible for it: </p>
  <p>&lt;edition&gt; (edition) describes the particularities of one edition of a text.</p>
  <p>&lt;respStmt&gt; (statement of responsibility) supplies a statement of responsibility for the
    intellectual content of a text, edition, recording, or series, where the specialized elements
    for authors, editors, etc. do not suffice or do not apply.</p>
  <p>&lt;name&gt; (name, proper noun) contains a proper noun or noun phrase.</p>
  <p>&lt;resp&gt; (responsibility) contains a phrase describing the nature of a person's
    intellectual responsibility.</p>
  <p>For printed texts, the word edition applies to the set of all the identical copies of an item
    produced from one master copy and issued by a particular publishing agency or a group of such
    agencies. A change in the identity of the distributing body or bodies does not normally
    constitute a change of edition, while a change in the master copy does. </p>
  <p>For electronic texts, the notion of a ‘master copy’ is not entirely appropriate, since they are
    far more easily copied and modified than printed ones; nonetheless the term edition may be used
    for a particular state of a machine-readable text at which substantive changes are made and
    fixed. Synonymous terms used in these Guidelines are version, level, and release. The words
    revision and update, by contrast, are used for minor changes to a file which do not amount to a
    new edition. </p>
  <p>No simple rule can specify how ‘substantive’ changes have to be before they are regarded as
    producing a new edition, rather than a simple update. The general principle proposed here is
    that the production of a new edition entails a significant change in the intellectual content of
    the file, rather than its encoding or appearance. The addition of analytic coding to a text
    would thus constitute a new edition, while automatic conversion from one coded representation to
    another would not. Changes relating to the character code or physical storage details,
    corrections of misspellings, simple changes in the arrangement of the contents and changes in
    the output format do not normally constitute a new edition, whereas the addition of new
    information (e.g. a linguistic analysis expressed in part-of-speech tagging, sound or graphics,
    referential links to external data sets) almost always does. </p>
  <p>Clearly, there will always be borderline cases and the matter is somewhat arbitrary. The
    simplest rule is: if you think that your file is a new edition, then call it such. An edition
    statement is optional for the first release of a computer file; it is mandatory for each later
    release, though this requirement cannot be enforced by the parser. </p>
  <p>Note that all changes in a file, whether or not they are regarded as constituting a new edition
    or simply a new revision, should be independently noted in the revision description section of
    the file header (see section 2.5 The Revision Description). </p>
  <p>The edition element should contain phrases describing the edition or version, including the
    word edition, version, or equivalent, together with a number or date, or terms indicating
    difference from other editions such as new edition, revised edition etc. Any dates that occur
    within the edition statement should be marked with the date element. The @n attribute of the
    edition element may be used as elsewhere to supply any formal identification (such as a version
    number) for the edition. </p>
  <p>One or more respStmt elements may also be used to supply statements of responsibility for the
    edition in question. These may refer to individuals or corporate bodies and can indicate
    functions such as that of a reviser, or can name the person or body responsible for the
    provision of supplementary matter, of appendices, etc., in a new edition. For further detail on
    the respStmt element, see section 3.11 Bibliographic Citations and References.</p>
  <p>Some examples follow: </p>
  <p>&lt;editionStmt&gt; &lt;edition n="P2"&gt;Second draft, substantially extended, revised, and
    corrected.&lt;/edition&gt;&lt;/editionStmt&gt;</p>
  <p>&lt;editionStmt&gt; &lt;edition&gt;Student's edition, &lt;date&gt;June 1987&lt;/date&gt;
    &lt;/edition&gt; &lt;respStmt&gt; &lt;resp&gt;New annotations by&lt;/resp&gt; &lt;name&gt;George
    Brown&lt;/name&gt; &lt;/respStmt&gt;&lt;/editionStmt&gt;</p>
  <p>3.2.3 Physical description of the file</p>
  <p>The extent element is the third component of the fileDesc element. It is optional. </p>
  <p>&lt;extent&gt; describes the approximate size of a text as stored on some carrier medium,
    whether digital or non-digital, specified in any convenient units.</p>
  <p>For printed books, information about the carrier, such as the kind of medium used and its size,
    are of great importance in cataloging procedures. The print-oriented rules for bibliographic
    description of an item's medium and extent need some re-interpretation when applied to
    electronic media. An electronic file exists as a distinct entity quite independently of its
    carrier and remains the same intellectual object whether it is stored on a magnetic tape, a
    CD-ROM, a set of floppy disks, or as a file on a mainframe computer. Since, moreover, these
    Guidelines are specifically aimed at facilitating transparent document storage and interchange,
    any purely machine-dependent information should be irrelevant as far as the file header is
    concerned. </p>
  <p>This is particularly true of information about file-type although library-oriented rules for
    cataloging often distinguish two types of computer file: ‘data’ and ‘programs’. This distinction
    is quite difficult to draw in some cases, for example, hypermedia or texts with built in search
    and retrieval software. </p>
  <p>Although it is equally system-dependent, some measure of the size of the computer file may be
    of use for cataloging and other practical purposes. Because the measurement and expression of
    file size is fraught with difficulties, only very general recommendations are possible; the
    element extent is provided for this purpose. It contains a phrase indicating the size or
    approximate size of the computer file in one of the following ways: </p>
  <p>•in bytes of a specified length (e.g. ‘4000 16-bit bytes’)</p>
  <p>•as falling within a range of categories, for example: </p>
  <p>◦less than 1 Mb</p>
  <p>◦between 1 Mb and 5 Mb</p>
  <p>◦between 6 Mb and 10 Mb</p>
  <p>◦over 10 Mb</p>
  <p>•in terms of any convenient logical units (for example, words or sentences, citations,
    paragraphs)</p>
  <p>•in terms of any convenient physical units (for example, blocks, disks, tapes)</p>
  <p>The use of standard abbreviations for units of quantity is recommended where applicable, here
    as elsewhere (see http://physics.nist.gov/cuu/Units/binary.html).</p>
  <p>Examples: </p>
  <p>&lt;extent&gt;between 1 16-bit MB and 2 16-bit MB&lt;/extent&gt;</p>
  <p>&lt;extent&gt;4.2 MiB&lt;/extent&gt;</p>
  <p>&lt;extent&gt;4532 bytes&lt;/extent&gt;</p>
  <p>&lt;extent&gt;3200 sentences&lt;/extent&gt;</p>
  <p>&lt;extent&gt;5 90 mm High Density Diskettes&lt;/extent&gt;</p>
  <p>3.2.4 Publication, Distribution, etc.</p>
  <p>The publicationStmt element is the fourth component of the fileDesc element and is mandatory. </p>
  <p>&lt;publicationStmt&gt; (publication statement) groups information concerning the publication
    or distribution of an electronic or other text. </p>
  <p>It may contain either a simple prose description organized as one or more paragraphs, or one or
    more elements from the model.publicationStmt class. This class groups a number of elements which
    are discussed in order below. </p>
  <p>&lt;publisher&gt; provides the name of the organization responsible for the publication or
    distribution of a bibliographic item.</p>
  <p>&lt;distributor&gt; supplies the name of a person or other agency responsible for the
    distribution of a text.</p>
  <p>&lt;authority&gt; (release authority) supplies the name of a person or other agency responsible
    for making an electronic file available, other than a publisher or distributor.</p>
  <p>The publisher is the person or institution by whose authority a given edition of the file is
    made public. The distributor is the person or institution from whom copies of the text may be
    obtained. Where a text is not considered formally published, but is nevertheless made available
    for circulation by some individual or organization, this person or institution is termed the
    release authority. </p>
  <p>At least one of the above three elements must be present, unless the entire publication
    statement is given as prose. Each may be followed by one or more of the following elements, in
    the following order:6 </p>
  <p>&lt;pubPlace&gt; (publication place) contains the name of the place where a bibliographic item
    was published.</p>
  <p>&lt;address&gt; contains a postal address, for example of a publisher, an organization, or an
    individual.</p>
  <p>&lt;idno&gt; (identifier) supplies any form of identifier used to identify some object, such as
    a bibliographic item, a person, a title, an organization, etc. in a standardized way.@type
    categorizes the identifier, for example as an ISBN, Social Security number, etc. </p>
  <p>&lt;availability&gt; supplies information about the availability of a text, for example any
    restrictions on its use or distribution, its copyright status, etc.@status supplies a code
    identifying the current availability of the text. </p>
  <p>&lt;date&gt; contains a date in any format.</p>
  <p>Note that the dates, places, etc., given in the publication statement relate to the publisher,
    distributor, or release authority most recently mentioned. If the text was created at some date
    other than its date of publication, its date of creation should be given within the workDesc
    element, not in the publication statement. Give any other useful dates (e.g., dates of
    collection of data) in a note. </p>
  <p>Additional detailed elements may be used for the encoding of names, dates, and addresses, as
    further described in section 3.5 Names, Numbers, Dates, Abbreviations, and Addresses when the
    module described in chapter 13 Names, Dates, People, and Places is included in a schema. </p>
  <p>Examples: </p>
  <p>&lt;publicationStmt&gt; &lt;publisher&gt;Oxford University Press&lt;/publisher&gt;
    &lt;pubPlace&gt;Oxford&lt;/pubPlace&gt; &lt;date&gt;1989&lt;/date&gt; &lt;idno
    type="ISBN"&gt;0-19-254705-4&lt;/idno&gt; &lt;availability&gt; &lt;p&gt;Copyright 1989, Oxford
    University Press&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/availability&gt;&lt;/publicationStmt&gt;</p>
  <p>&lt;publicationStmt&gt; &lt;authority&gt;James D. Benson&lt;/authority&gt;
    &lt;pubPlace&gt;London&lt;/pubPlace&gt;
    &lt;date&gt;1984&lt;/date&gt;&lt;/publicationStmt&gt;</p>
  <p>&lt;publicationStmt&gt; &lt;publisher&gt;Sigma Press&lt;/publisher&gt; &lt;address&gt;
    &lt;addrLine&gt;21 High Street,&lt;/addrLine&gt; &lt;addrLine&gt;Wilmslow,&lt;/addrLine&gt;
    &lt;addrLine&gt;Cheshire M24 3DF&lt;/addrLine&gt; &lt;/address&gt; &lt;date&gt;1991&lt;/date&gt;
    &lt;distributor&gt;Oxford Text Archive&lt;/distributor&gt; &lt;idno
    type="ota"&gt;1256&lt;/idno&gt; &lt;availability&gt; &lt;p&gt;Available with prior consent of
    depositor for purposes of academic research and teaching only.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/availability&gt;&lt;/publicationStmt&gt;</p>
  <p>3.2.5 Series statement</p>
  <p>The seriesStmt element is the fifth component of the fileDesc element and is optional. </p>
  <p>&lt;seriesStmt&gt; (series statement) groups information about the series, if any, to which a
    publication belongs.</p>
  <p>In bibliographic parlance, a series may be defined in one of the following ways: </p>
  <p>•A group of separate items related to one another by the fact that each item bears, in addition
    to its own title proper, a collective title applying to the group as a whole. The individual
    items may or may not be numbered.</p>
  <p>•Each of two or more volumes of essays, lectures, articles, or other items, similar in
    character and issued in sequence.</p>
  <p>•A separately numbered sequence of volumes within a series or serial.</p>
  <p>The seriesStmt element may contain a prose description or one or more of the following more
    specific elements: </p>
  <p>&lt;title&gt; contains a title for any kind of work.</p>
  <p>&lt;idno&gt; (identifier) supplies any form of identifier used to identify some object, such as
    a bibliographic item, a person, a title, an organization, etc. in a standardized way.</p>
  <p>&lt;respStmt&gt; (statement of responsibility) supplies a statement of responsibility for the
    intellectual content of a text, edition, recording, or series, where the specialized elements
    for authors, editors, etc. do not suffice or do not apply.</p>
  <p>&lt;resp&gt; (responsibility) contains a phrase describing the nature of a person's
    intellectual responsibility.</p>
  <p>&lt;name&gt; (name, proper noun) contains a proper noun or noun phrase.</p>
  <p>The idno may be used to supply any identifying number associated with the item, including both
    standard numbers such as an ISSN and particular issue numbers. (Arabic numerals separated by
    punctuation are recommended for this purpose: '6.19.33', for example, rather than 'VI/xix:33').
    Its @type attribute is used to categorize the number further, taking the value 'ISSN' for an
    ISSN for example. </p>
  <p>Examples: </p>
  <p>&lt;seriesStmt&gt; &lt;title level="s"&gt;Machine-Readable Texts for the Study of Indian
    Literature&lt;/title&gt; &lt;respStmt&gt; &lt;resp&gt;ed. by&lt;/resp&gt; &lt;name&gt;Jan
    Gonda&lt;/name&gt; &lt;/respStmt&gt; &lt;idno type="vol"&gt;1.2&lt;/idno&gt; &lt;idno
    type="ISSN"&gt;0 345 6789&lt;/idno&gt;&lt;/seriesStmt&gt;</p>
  <p>3.2.6 Notes statement</p>
  <p>The notesStmt element is the sixth component of the fileDesc element and is optional. If used,
    it contains one or more note elements, each containing a single piece of descriptive information
    of the kind treated as ‘general notes’ in traditional bibliographic descriptions. </p>
  <p>&lt;notesStmt&gt; (notes statement) collects together any notes providing information about a
    text additional to that recorded in other parts of the bibliographic description.</p>
  <p>&lt;note&gt; contains a note or annotation.</p>
  <p>Some information found in the notes area in conventional bibliography has been assigned
    specific elements in these Guidelines; in particular the following items should be tagged as
    indicated, rather than as general notes: </p>
  <p>•the nature, scope, artistic form, or purpose of the file; also the genre or other intellectual
    category to which it may belong: e.g. ‘Text types: newspaper editorials and reportage, science
    fiction, westerns, and detective stories’. These should be formally described within the
    workDesc element (section 2.4 The Work Description).</p>
  <p>•summary description providing a factual, non-evaluative account of the subject content of the
    file: e.g. ‘Transcribes interviews on general topics with native speakers of English in 17
    cities during the spring and summer of 1963.’ These should also be formally described within the
    workDesc element (section 2.4 The Work Description).</p>
  <p>•bibliographic details relating to the source or sources of an electronic text: e.g.
    ‘Transcribed from the Norton facsimile of the 1623 Folio’. These should be formally described in
    the sourceDesc element (section 2.2.7 The Source Description).</p>
  <p>•further information relating to publication, distribution, or release of the text, including
    sources from which the text may be obtained, any restrictions on its use or formal terms on its
    availability. These should be placed in the appropriate division of the publicationStmt element
    (section 2.2.4 Publication, Distribution, etc.).</p>
  <p>•publicly documented numbers associated with the file: e.g. ‘ICPSR study number 1803’ or
    ‘Oxford Text Archive text number 1243’. These should be placed in an idno element within the
    appropriate division of the publicationStmt element. International Standard Serial Numbers
    (ISSN), International Standard Book Numbers (ISBN), and other internationally agreed upon
    standard numbers that uniquely identify an item, should be treated in the same way, rather than
    as specialized bibliographic notes.</p>
  <p>Nevertheless, the notesStmt element may be used to record potentially significant details about
    the file and its features, e.g.: </p>
  <p>•dates, when they are relevant to the content or condition of the computer file: e.g. ‘manual
    dated 1983’, ‘Interview wave I: Apr. 1989; wave II: Jan. 1990’</p>
  <p>•names of persons or bodies connected with the technical production, administration, or
    consulting functions of the effort which produced the file, if these are not named in statements
    of responsibility in the title or edition statements of the file description: e.g. ‘Historical
    commentary provided by Mark Cohen’</p>
  <p>•availability of the file in an additional medium or information not already recorded about the
    availability of documentation: e.g. ‘User manual is loose-leaf in eleven paginated sections’</p>
  <p>•language of work and abstract, if not encoded in the langUsage element, e.g. ‘Text in English
    with summaries in French and German’</p>
  <p>•The unique name assigned to a serial by the International Serials Data System (ISDS), if not
    encoded in an idno</p>
  <p>•lists of related publications, either describing the source itself, or concerned with the
    creation or use of the electronic work, e.g. ‘Texts used in Burrows (1987)’</p>
  <p>Each such item of information may be tagged using the general-purpose note element, which is
    described in section 3.8 Notes, Annotation, and Indexing. Groups of notes are contained within
    the notesStmt element, as in the following example: </p>
  <p>&lt;notesStmt&gt; &lt;note&gt;Historical commentary provided by Mark Cohen.&lt;/note&gt;
    &lt;note&gt;OCR scanning done at University of Toronto.&lt;/note&gt;&lt;/notesStmt&gt;</p>
  <p>There are advantages, however, to encoding such information with more precise elements
    elsewhere in the MEI header, when such elements are available. For example, the notes above
    might be encoded as follows: </p>
  <p>&lt;titleStmt&gt; &lt;title&gt;…&lt;/title&gt; &lt;respStmt&gt; &lt;persName&gt;Mark
    Cohen&lt;/persName&gt; &lt;resp&gt;historical commentary&lt;/resp&gt; &lt;/respStmt&gt;
    &lt;respStmt&gt; &lt;orgName&gt;University of Toronto&lt;/orgName&gt; &lt;resp&gt;OCR
    scanning&lt;/resp&gt; &lt;/respStmt&gt;&lt;/titleStmt&gt;</p>
  <p>3.2.7 Source description</p>
  <p>The sourceDesc element is the seventh and final component of the fileDesc element. It is a
    mandatory element and is used to record details of the source or sources from which a computer
    file is derived. This might be a printed text or manuscript, another computer file, an audio or
    video recording of some kind, or a combination of these. An electronic file may also have no
    source, if what is being catalogued is an original text created in electronic form. </p>
  <p>&lt;sourceDesc&gt; (source description) describes the source from which an electronic text was
    derived or generated, typically a bibliographic description in the case of a digitized text, or
    a phrase such as "born digital" for a text which has no previous existence.</p>
  <p>The sourceDesc element may contain little more than a simple prose description, or a brief note
    stating that the document has no source: </p>
  <p>&lt;sourceDesc&gt; &lt;p&gt;Born digital.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/sourceDesc&gt;Alternatively, it may
    contain elements drawn from the following three classes: </p>
  <p>model.biblLike groups elements containing a bibliographic description. </p>
  <p>model.sourceDescPart groups elements which may be used inside sourceDesc and appear multiple
    times.</p>
  <p>model.listLike groups list-like elements.</p>
  <p>These classes make available by default a range of ways of providing bibliographic citations
    which specify the provenance of the text. For written or printed sources, the source may be
    described in the same way as any other bibliographic citation, using one of the following
    elements: </p>
  <p>&lt;bibl&gt; (bibliographic citation) contains a loosely-structured bibliographic citation of
    which the sub-components may or may not be explicitly tagged. </p>
  <p>&lt;biblStruct&gt; (structured bibliographic citation) contains a structured bibliographic
    citation, in which only bibliographic sub-elements appear and in a specified order. </p>
  <p>&lt;listBibl&gt; (citation list) contains a list of bibliographic citations of any kind. </p>
  <p>These elements are described in more detail in section 3.11 Bibliographic Citations and
    References. Using them, a source might be described in very simple terms: </p>
  <p>&lt;sourceDesc&gt; &lt;bibl&gt;The first folio of Shakespeare, prepared by Charlton Hinman (The
    Norton Facsimile, 1968)&lt;/bibl&gt;&lt;/sourceDesc&gt;or with more elaboration: </p>
  <p>&lt;sourceDesc&gt; &lt;biblStruct xml:lang="fr"&gt; &lt;monogr&gt; &lt;author&gt;Eugène
    Sue&lt;/author&gt; &lt;title&gt;Martin, l'enfant trouvé&lt;/title&gt; &lt;title
    type="sub"&gt;Mémoires d'un valet de chambre&lt;/title&gt; &lt;imprint&gt;
    &lt;pubPlace&gt;Bruxelles et Leipzig&lt;/pubPlace&gt; &lt;publisher&gt;C.
    Muquardt&lt;/publisher&gt; &lt;date when="1846"&gt;1846&lt;/date&gt; &lt;/imprint&gt;
    &lt;/monogr&gt; &lt;/biblStruct&gt;&lt;/sourceDesc&gt;When the header describes a text derived
    from some pre-existing MEI-conformant or other digital document, it may be simpler to use the
    following element: </p>
  <p>&lt;biblFull&gt; (fully-structured bibliographic citation) contains a fully-structured
    bibliographic citation, in which all components of the MEI file description are present.</p>
  <p>since this is designed specifically for documents derived from texts which were ‘born digital’,
    as further discussed in section 2.2.8 Computer Files Derived from Other Computer Files .</p>
  <p>When the module for manuscript description is included in a schema, this class also makes
    available the following element: </p>
  <p>&lt;msDesc&gt; (manuscript description) contains a description of a single identifiable
    manuscript or other text-bearing object.</p>
  <p>which enables the encoder to record very detailed information about one or more manuscript or
    analogous sources, as further discussed in 10 Manuscript Description.</p>
  <p>The model.sourceDescPart class also makes available additional elements when additional modules
    are included. For example, when the spoken module is included, the sourceDesc element may also
    include the following special-purpose elements, intended for cases where an electronic text is
    derived from a spoken text rather than a written one: </p>
  <p>&lt;scriptStmt&gt; (script statement) contains a citation giving details of the script used for
    a spoken text.</p>
  <p>&lt;recordingStmt&gt; (recording statement) describes a set of recordings used as the basis for
    transcription of a spoken text.</p>
  <p>Full descriptions of these elements and their contents are given in section 8.2 Documenting the
    Source of Transcribed Speech.</p>
  <p>A single electronic text may be derived from multiple source documents, in whole or in part.
    The sourceDesc may therefore contain a listBibl element grouping together bibl, biblStruct, or
    msDesc elements for each of the sources concerned. It is also possible to repeat the sourceDesc
    element in such a case. The @decls attribute described in section 15.3 Associating Contextual
    Information with a Text may be used to associate parts of the encoded text with the
    bibliographic element from which it derives in either case. </p>
  <p>The source description may also include lists of names, persons, places, etc. when these are
    considered to form part of the source for an encoded document. When such information is recorded
    using the specialized elements discussed in the namesdates module (13 Names, Dates, People, and
    Places), the class model.listLike makes available the following elements to hold such
    information: </p>
  <p>&lt;listNym&gt; (list of canonical names) contains a list of nyms, that is, standardized names
    for any thing. </p>
  <p>&lt;listOrg&gt; (list of organizations) contains a list of elements, each of which provides
    information about an identifiable organization. </p>
  <p>&lt;listPerson&gt; (list of persons) contains a list of descriptions, each of which provides
    information about an identifiable person or a group of people, for example the participants in a
    language interaction, or the people referred to in a historical source. </p>
  <p>&lt;listPlace&gt; (list of places) contains a list of places, optionally followed by a list of
    relationships (other than containment) defined amongst them.</p>
  <p>3.2.8 Computer files derived from other computer files</p>
  <p>If a computer file (call it B) is derived not from a printed source but from another computer
    file (call it A) which includes an MEI file header, then the source text of computer file B is
    another computer file, A. The four sections of A's file header will need to be incorporated into
    the new header for B in slightly differing ways, as listed below: </p>
  <p>fileDesc</p>
  <p>A's file description should be copied into the sourceDesc section of B's file description,
    enclosed within a biblFull element </p>
  <p>workDesc</p>
  <p>A's workDesc should be copied into B's, in principle unchanged; it may however be expanded by
    project-specific information relating to B. </p>
  <p>encodingDesc</p>
  <p>A's encoding practice may or (more likely) may not be the same as B's. Since the object of the
    encoding description is to define the relationship between the current file and its source, in
    principle only changes in encoding practice between A and B need be documented in B. The
    relationship between A and its source(s) is then only recoverable from the original header of A.
    In practice it may be more convenient to create a new complete encodingDesc for B based on A's. </p>
  <p>revisionDesc</p>
  <p>B is a new computer file, and should therefore have a new revision description. If, however, it
    is felt useful to include some information from A's revisionDesc, for example dates of major
    updates or versions, such information must be clearly marked as relating to A rather than to B. </p>
  <p>This concludes the discussion of the fileDesc element and its contents.</p>
  <p>3.3 Encoding description</p>
  <p>The encodingDesc element is the second major subdivision of the MEI header. It specifies the
    methods and editorial principles which governed the transcription or encoding of the text in
    hand and may also include sets of coded definitions used by other components of the header.
    Though not formally required, its use is highly recommended. </p>
  <p>&lt;encodingDesc&gt; (encoding description) documents the relationship between an electronic
    text and the source or sources from which it was derived.</p>
  <p>The encoding description may contain any combination of paragraphs of text, marked up using the
    p element, along with more specialized elements taken from the model.encodingDescPart class. By
    default, this class makes available the following elements: </p>
  <p>&lt;projectDesc&gt; (project description) describes in detail the aim or purpose for which an
    electronic file was encoded, together with any other relevant information concerning the process
    by which it was assembled or collected.</p>
  <p>&lt;samplingDecl&gt; (sampling declaration) contains a prose description of the rationale and
    methods used in sampling texts in the creation of a corpus or collection.</p>
  <p>&lt;editorialDecl&gt; (editorial practice declaration) provides details of editorial principles
    and practices applied during the encoding of a text.</p>
  <p>&lt;tagsDecl&gt; (tagging declaration) provides detailed information about the tagging applied
    to a document.</p>
  <p>&lt;refsDecl&gt; (references declaration) specifies how canonical references are constructed
    for this text.</p>
  <p>&lt;classDecl&gt; (classification declarations) contains one or more taxonomies defining any
    classificatory codes used elsewhere in the text.</p>
  <p>&lt;appInfo&gt; (application information) records information about an application which has
    edited the MEI file. </p>
  <p>Each of these elements is further described in the appropriate section below. Other modules
    have the ability to extend this class; examples are noted in section 2.3.8 Module-Specific
    Declarations</p>
  <p>3.3.1 Project description</p>
  <p>The projectDesc element may be used to describe, in prose, the purpose for which a digital
    resource was created, together with any other relevant information concerning the process by
    which it was assembled or collected. This is of particular importance for corpora or
    miscellaneous collections, but may be of use for any text, for example to explain why one kind
    of encoding practice has been followed rather than another. </p>
  <p>&lt;projectDesc&gt; (project description) describes in detail the aim or purpose for which an
    electronic file was encoded, together with any other relevant information concerning the process
    by which it was assembled or collected.</p>
  <p>For example: </p>
  <p>&lt;encodingDesc&gt; &lt;projectDesc&gt; &lt;p&gt;Texts collected for use in the Claremont
    Shakespeare Clinic, June 1990.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/projectDesc&gt;&lt;/encodingDesc&gt;</p>
  <p>3.3.2 Declaration of editorial principles</p>
  <p>The editorialDecl element is used to provide details of the editorial practices applied during
    the encoding of a text. </p>
  <p>&lt;editorialDecl&gt; (editorial practice declaration) provides details of editorial principles
    and practices applied during the encoding of a text.</p>
  <p>It may contain a prose description only, or one or more of a set of specialized elements,
    members of the MEI model.editorialDeclPart class. Where an encoder wishes to record an editorial
    policy not specified above, this may be done by adding a new element to this class, using the
    mechanisms discussed in chapter 23.2 Personalization and Customization.</p>
  <p>Some of these policy elements carry attributes to support automated processing of certain
    well-defined editorial decisions; all of them contain a prose description of the editorial
    principles adopted with respect to the particular feature concerned. Examples of the kinds of
    questions which these descriptions are intended to answer are given in the list below.</p>
  <p>correction</p>
  <p>&lt;correction&gt; (correction principles) states how and under what circumstances corrections
    have been made in the text.@status indicates the degree of correction applied to the text. </p>
  <p>@method indicates the method adopted to indicate corrections within the text. </p>
  <p>Was the text corrected during or after data capture? If so, were corrections made silently or
    are they marked using the tags described in section 3.4 Simple Editorial Changes? What
    principles have been adopted with respect to omissions, truncations, dubious corrections,
    alternate readings, false starts, repetitions, etc.?</p>
  <p>normalization</p>
  <p>&lt;normalization&gt; indicates the extent of normalization or regularization of the original
    source carried out in converting it to electronic form.@source indicates the authority for any
    normalization carried out. </p>
  <p>@method indicates the method adopted to indicate normalizations within the text. </p>
  <p>Was the text normalized, for example by regularizing any non-standard spellings, dialect forms,
    etc.? If so, were normalizations performed silently or are they marked using the tags described
    in section 3.4 Simple Editorial Changes? What authority was used for the regularization? Also,
    what principles were used when normalizing numbers to provide the standard values for the @value
    attribute described in section 3.5.3 Numbers and Measures and what format used for them?</p>
  <p>quotation</p>
  <p>&lt;quotation&gt; specifies editorial practice adopted with respect to quotation marks in the
    original. @marks (quotation marks) indicates whether or not quotation marks have been retained
    as content within the text. </p>
  <p>@form specifies how quotation marks are indicated within the text. </p>
  <p>How were quotation marks processed? Are apostrophes and quotation marks distinguished? How? Are
    quotation marks retained as content in the text or replaced by markup? Are there any special
    conventions regarding for example the use of single or double quotation marks when nested? Is
    the file consistent in its practice or has this not been checked?</p>
  <p>hyphenation</p>
  <p>&lt;hyphenation&gt; summarizes the way in which hyphenation in a source text has been treated
    in an encoded version of it.@eol (end-of-line) indicates whether or not end-of-line hyphenation
    has been retained in a text. </p>
  <p>Does the encoding distinguish ‘soft’ and ‘hard’ hyphens? What principle has been adopted with
    respect to end-of-line hyphenation where source lineation has not been retained? Have soft
    hyphens been silently removed, and if so what is the effect on lineation and pagination?</p>
  <p>segmentation</p>
  <p>&lt;segmentation&gt; describes the principles according to which the text has been segmented,
    for example into sentences, tone-units, graphemic strata, etc.</p>
  <p>How is the text segmented? If s or seg segmentation units have been used to divide up the text
    for analysis, how are they marked and how was the segmentation arrived at?</p>
  <p>stdVals</p>
  <p>&lt;stdVals&gt; (standard values) specifies the format used when standardized date or number
    values are supplied.</p>
  <p>In most cases, attributes bearing standardized values (such as the @when or @when-iso attribute
    on dates) should conform to a defined W3C or ISO datatype. In cases where this is not
    appropriate, this element may be used to describe the standardization methods underlying the
    values supplied. </p>
  <p>interpretation</p>
  <p>&lt;interpretation&gt; describes the scope of any analytic or interpretive information added to
    the text in addition to the transcription. </p>
  <p>Has any analytic or ‘interpretive’ information been provided — that is, information which is
    felt to be non-obvious, or potentially contentious? If so, how was it generated? How was it
    encoded? If feature-structure analysis has been used, are fsdDecl elements (section 18.11
    Feature System Declaration) present?</p>
  <p>Any information about the editorial principles applied not falling under one of the above
    headings should be recorded in a distinct list of items. Experience shows that a full record
    should be kept of decisions relating to editorial principles and encoding practice, both for
    future users of the text and for the project which produced the text in the first instance. Some
    simple examples follow: </p>
  <p>&lt;editorialDecl&gt; &lt;segmentation&gt; &lt;p&gt; &lt;gi&gt;s&lt;/gi&gt; elements mark
    orthographic sentences and are numbered sequentially within their parent
    &lt;gi&gt;div&lt;/gi&gt; element &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/segmentation&gt; &lt;interpretation&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The part of speech analysis applied throughout section 4 was added by hand and has not
    been checked.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/interpretation&gt; &lt;correction&gt; &lt;p&gt;Errors in
    transcription controlled by using the WordPerfect spelling checker.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/correction&gt; &lt;normalization source="http://szotar.sztaki.hu/webster/"&gt; &lt;p&gt;All
    words converted to Modern American spelling following Webster’s 9th Collegiate
    dictionary.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/normalization&gt; &lt;quotation marks="all" form="std"&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All opening quotation marks represented by entity reference &lt;ident
    type="ge"&gt;odq&lt;/ident&gt;; all closing quotation marks represented by entity reference
    &lt;ident type="ge"&gt;cdq&lt;/ident&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/quotation&gt;&lt;/editorialDecl&gt;</p>
  <p>An editorial practices declaration which applies to more than one text or division of a text
    need not be repeated in the header of each such text. Instead, the @decls attribute of each text
    (or subdivision of the text) to which it applies may be used to supply a cross-reference to it,
    as further described in section 15.3 Associating Contextual Information with a Text. </p>
  <p>3.3.3 Application information</p>
  <p>It is sometimes convenient to store information relating to the processing of an encoded
    resource within its header. Typical uses for such information might be: </p>
  <p>•to allow an application to discover that it has previously opened or edited a file, and what
    version of itself was used to do that;</p>
  <p>•to show (through a date) which application last edited the file to allow for diagnosis of any
    problems that might have been caused by that application;</p>
  <p>•to allow users to discover information about an application used to edit the file</p>
  <p>•to allow the application to declare an interest in elements of the file which it has edited,
    so that other applications or human editors may be more wary of making changes to those sections
    of the file.</p>
  <p>The class model.applicationLike provides an element, application, which may be used to record
    such information within the appInfo element.</p>
  <p>&lt;appInfo&gt; (application information) records information about an application which has
    edited the MEI file. </p>
  <p>&lt;application&gt; provides information about an application which has acted upon the
    document.@ident Supplies an identifier for the application, independent of its version number or
    display name. </p>
  <p>@version Supplies a version number for the application, independent of its identifier or
    display name. </p>
  <p>Each application element identifies the current state of one software application with regard
    to the current file. This element is a member of the att.datable class, which provides a variety
    of attributes for associating this state with a date and time, or a temporal range. The @ident
    and @version attributes should be used to uniquely identify the application and its major
    version number (for example, 'ImageMarkupTool 1.5'). It is not intended that an application
    should add a new application each time it touches the file.</p>
  <p>The following example shows how these elements might be used to document the fact that version
    1.5 of an application called ‘Image Markup Tool’ has an interest in two parts of a document
    which was last saved on June 6 2006. The parts concerned are accessible at the URLs given as
    target for the two ptr elements. </p>
  <p>&lt;appInfo&gt; &lt;application version="1.5" ident="ImageMarkupTool" notAfter="2006-06-01"&gt;
    &lt;label&gt;Image Markup Tool&lt;/label&gt; &lt;ptr target="#P1"/&gt; &lt;ptr target="#P2"/&gt;
    &lt;/application&gt;&lt;/appInfo&gt;</p>
  <p>3.4 Work description</p>
  <p>The workDesc element is the third major subdivision of the MEI Header. It is an optional
    element, the purpose of which is to enable information characterizing various descriptive
    aspects of a text or a corpus to be recorded within a single unified framework. </p>
  <p>&lt;workDesc&gt; (text-work description) provides a detailed description of non-bibliographic
    aspects of a text, specifically the languages and sublanguages used, the situation in which it
    was produced, the participants and their setting.</p>
  <p>In principle, almost any component of the header might be of importance as a means of
    characterizing a text. The author of a written text, its title or its date of publication, may
    all be regarded as characterizing it at least as strongly as any of the parameters discussed in
    this section. The rule of thumb applied has been to exclude from discussion here most of the
    information which generally forms part of a standard bibliographic style description, if only
    because such information has already been included elsewhere in the MEI header. </p>
  <p>The workDesc element contains an optional creation element, followed by any number of
    additional elements taken from the model.workDesc class. In the simplest case, this means it may
    contain the following elements:</p>
  <p>3.4.1 Title statement</p>
  <p>3.4.2 History</p>
  <p>3.4.3 Language usage</p>
  <p>The langUsage element is used within the workDesc element to describe the languages,
    sublanguages, registers, dialects, etc. represented within a text. It contains one or more
    language elements, each of which provides information about a single language, notably the
    quantity of that language present in the text. Note that this element should not be used to
    supply information about any non-standard characters or glyphs used by this language; such
    information should be recorded in the charDecl element in the encoding description (see further
    5 Representation of Non-standard Characters and Glyphs). </p>
  <p>&lt;langUsage&gt; (language usage) describes the languages, sublanguages, registers, dialects,
    etc. represented within a text.</p>
  <p>&lt;language&gt; characterizes a single language or sublanguage used within a text.@usage
    specifies the approximate percentage (by volume) of the text which uses this language. </p>
  <p>@ident (identifier) Supplies a language code constructed as defined in BCP 47 which is used to
    identify the language documented by this element, and which is referenced by the global
    @xml:lang attribute. </p>
  <p>A language element may be supplied for each different language used in a document. If used, its
    @ident attribute should specify an appropriate language identifier, as further discussed in
    section vi.1. Language identification. This is particularly important if extended language
    identifiers have been used as the value of @xml:lang attributes elsewhere in the document. </p>
  <p>Here is an example of the use of this element: </p>
  <p>&lt;langUsage&gt; &lt;language ident="fr-CA" usage="60"&gt;Québecois&lt;/language&gt;
    &lt;language ident="en-CA" usage="20"&gt;Canadian business English&lt;/language&gt; &lt;language
    ident="en-GB" usage="20"&gt;British English&lt;/language&gt;&lt;/langUsage&gt;</p>
  <p>3.4.4 Key, tempo, and meter</p>
  <p>3.4.5 Performance medium</p>
  <p>3.4.6 Notes statement</p>
  <p>3.4.7 Classification</p>
  <p>The second component of the core workDesc element is the textClass element. This element is
    used to classify a text according to one or more of the following methods: </p>
  <p>•by reference to a recognized international classification such as the Dewey Decimal
    Classification, the Universal Decimal Classification, the Colon Classification, the Library of
    Congress Classification, or any other system widely used in library and documentation work</p>
  <p>•by providing a set of keywords, as provided for example by British Library or Library of
    Congress Cataloguing in Publication data</p>
  <p>•by referencing any other taxonomy of text categories recognized in the field concerned, or
    peculiar to the material in hand; this may include one based on recurring sets of values for the
    situational parameters defined in section 15.2.1 The Text Description, or the demographic
    elements described in section 15.2.2 The Participant Description</p>
  <p>The last of these may be particularly important for dealing with existing corpora or
    collections, both as a means of avoiding the expense or inconvenience of reclassification and as
    a means of documenting the organizing principles of such materials.</p>
  <p>The following elements are provided for this purpose: </p>
  <p>&lt;keywords&gt; contains a list of keywords or phrases identifying the topic or nature of a
    text.@scheme identifies the controlled vocabulary within which the set of keywords concerned is
    defined. </p>
  <p>&lt;classCode&gt; (classification code) contains the classification code used for this text in
    some standard classification system.@scheme identifies the classification system or taxonomy in
    use. </p>
  <p>&lt;catRef/&gt; (category reference) specifies one or more defined categories within some
    taxonomy or text typology.</p>
  <p>The keywords element simply categorizes an individual text by supplying a list of keywords
    which may describe its topic or subject matter, its form, date, etc. In some schemes, the order
    of items in the list is significant, for example, from major topic to minor; in others, the list
    has an organized substructure of its own. No recommendations are made here as to which method is
    to be preferred. Wherever possible, such keywords should be taken from a recognized source, such
    as the British Library/Library of Congress Cataloguing in Publication data in the case of
    printed books, or a published thesaurus appropriate to the field.</p>
  <p>The @scheme attribute should be used to indicate the source of the keywords used. If the
    keywords are taken from some externally defined authority which is available online, this
    attribute should point directly to it, as in the following examples: </p>
  <p>&lt;keywords scheme="http://classificationweb.net"&gt; &lt;term&gt;Babbage,
    Charles&lt;/term&gt; &lt;term&gt;Mathematicians - Great Britain -
    Biography&lt;/term&gt;&lt;/keywords&gt;</p>
  <p>&lt;keywords scheme="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh"&gt; &lt;term&gt;English
    literature -- History and criticism -- Data processing.&lt;/term&gt; &lt;term&gt;English
    literature -- History and criticism -- Theory, etc.&lt;/term&gt; &lt;term&gt;English language --
    Style -- Data processing.&lt;/term&gt; &lt;term&gt;Style, Literary -- Data
    processing.&lt;/term&gt;&lt;/keywords&gt;</p>
  <p>If the authority file is not available online, but is generally recognized and commonly cited,
    a bibliographic description for it should be supplied within the taxonomy element described in
    section 2.3.6 The Classification Declaration; the @scheme attribute may then reference that
    taxonomy element by means of its identifier in the usual way: </p>
  <p>&lt;keywords scheme="#welch"&gt; &lt;term&gt;ceremonials&lt;/term&gt;
    &lt;term&gt;fairs&lt;/term&gt; &lt;term&gt;street life&lt;/term&gt;&lt;/keywords&gt;&lt;!--
    elsewhere in the document --&gt;&lt;taxonomy xml:id="welch"&gt; &lt;bibl&gt; &lt;title&gt;Notes
    on London Municipal Literature, and a Suggested Scheme for Its Classification&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;author&gt;Charles Welch&lt;/author&gt; &lt;edition&gt;1895&lt;/edition&gt;
    &lt;/bibl&gt;&lt;/taxonomy&gt;</p>
  <p>Alternatively, if the keyword vocabulary itself is locally defined, the @scheme attribute will
    point to the local definition, which will typically be held in a taxonomy element within the
    classDecl part of the encoding description (see section 2.3.6 The Classification Declaration). </p>
  <p>The classCode element also categorizes an individual text, by supplying a numerical or other
    code rather than descriptive terms. Such codes constitute a recognized classification scheme,
    such as the Dewey Decimal Classification. The @scheme attribute is used to indicate the source
    of the classification scheme in the same way as for keywords: this may be a pointer of any kind,
    either to an MEI element, possibly in the current document, as in the keywords examples above,
    or to some canonical source for the scheme, as in the following example: </p>
  <p>&lt;classCode
    scheme="http://www.udcc.org/udcsummary/php/index.php"&gt;005.756&lt;/classCode&gt;</p>
  <p>The catRef element categorizes an individual text by pointing to one or more category elements
    using the @target attribute, which it inherits from the att.pointing class. The category element
    (which is fully described in section 2.3.6 The Classification Declaration) holds information
    about a particular classification or category within a given taxonomy. Each such category must
    have a unique identifier, which may be supplied as the value of the @target attribute for catRef
    elements which are regarded as falling within the category indicated.</p>
  <p>A text may, of course, fall into more than one category, in which case more than one identifier
    will be supplied as the value for the @target attribute on the catRef element, as in the
    following example: </p>
  <p>&lt;catRef target="#b.a4 #b.d2"/&gt;The @scheme attribute may be supplied to specify the
    taxonomy to which the categories identified by the target attribute belong, if this is not
    adequately conveyed by the resource pointed to. For example, </p>
  <p>&lt;catRef target="#b.a4 #b.d2" scheme="http://www.example.com/browncorpus"/&gt;&lt;catRef
    target="http://www.example.com/SUC/#A45"/&gt;Here the same text has been classified as of
    categories 'b.a4' and 'b.d2' within the Brown classification scheme (presumed to be available
    from http://www.example.com/browncorpus), and as of category ‘A45’ within the SUC classification
    scheme documented at the URL given.</p>
  <p>The distinction between the catRef and classCode elements is that the values used as
    identifying codes are exhaustively enumerated, typically with the header, for the former, while
    the latter may be used to indicate a more open ended or descriptive classification system.</p>
  <p>3.4.8 Cast list</p>
  <p>3.4.9 Incipit</p>
  <p>3.4.10 Contents note</p>
  <p>3.4.11 Related item</p>
  <p>3.5 Revision description</p>
  <p>The final sub-element of the MEI header, the revisionDesc element, provides a detailed change
    log in which each change made to a text may be recorded. Its use is optional but highly
    recommended. It provides essential information for the administration of large numbers of files
    which are being updated, corrected, or otherwise modified as well as extremely useful
    documentation for files being passed from researcher to researcher or system to system. Without
    change logs, it is easy to confuse different versions of a file, or to remain unaware of small
    but important changes made in the file by some earlier link in the chain of distribution. No
    change should be made in any MEI-conformant file without corresponding entries being made in the
    change log.</p>
  <p>&lt;revisionDesc&gt; (revision description) summarizes the revision history for a file.</p>
  <p>&lt;change&gt; summarizes a particular change or correction made to a particular version of an
    electronic text which is shared between several researchers.</p>
  <p>The main purpose of the revision description is to record changes in the text to which a header
    is prefixed. However, it is recommended MEI practice to include entries also for significant
    changes in the header itself (other than the revision description itself, of course). At the
    very least, an entry should be supplied indicating the date of creation of the header.</p>
  <p>The log consists of a list of entries, one for each change. This may be encoded using either
    the regular list element, as described in section 3.7 Lists or as a series of special purpose
    change elements, each of which contains a more detailed description of the changes made. The
    attributes @when and @who are used to indicate the date of the change and the person responsible
    for it respectively. The description of the change itself can range from a simple phrase to a
    series of paragraphs. If a number is to be associated with one or more changes (for example, a
    revision number), the global @n attribute may be used to indicate it.</p>
  <p>It is recommended to give changes in reverse chronological order, most recent first.</p>
  <p>For example: </p>
  <p>&lt;!-- ... --&gt;&lt;revisionDesc&gt; &lt;change n="RCS:1.39" when="2007-08-08"
    who="#jwernimo.lrv"&gt;Changed &lt;val&gt;drama.verse&lt;/val&gt; &lt;gi&gt;lg&lt;/gi&gt;s to
    &lt;gi&gt;p&lt;/gi&gt;s. &lt;note&gt;we have opened a discussion about the need for a new value
    for &lt;att&gt;type&lt;/att&gt; of &lt;gi&gt;lg&lt;/gi&gt;,
    &lt;val&gt;drama.free.verse&lt;/val&gt;, in order to address the verse of Behn which is not in
    regular iambic pentameter. For the time being these instances are marked with a comment note
    until we are able to fully consider the best way to encode these instances.&lt;/note&gt;
    &lt;/change&gt; &lt;change n="RCS:1.33" when="2007-06-28" who="#pcaton.xzc"&gt;Added
    &lt;att&gt;key&lt;/att&gt; and &lt;att&gt;reg&lt;/att&gt; to
    &lt;gi&gt;name&lt;/gi&gt;s.&lt;/change&gt; &lt;change n="RCS:1.31" when="2006-12-04"
    who="#wgui.ner"&gt;Completed renovation. Validated.&lt;/change&gt;&lt;/revisionDesc&gt;</p>
  <p>In the above example, the @who attributes point to respStmt elements which have been included
    earlier in the titleStmt of the same header: </p>
  <p>&lt;titleStmt&gt; &lt;title&gt;The Amorous Prince, or, the Curious Husband, 1671&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;author&gt; &lt;persName ref="#abehn.aeh"&gt;Behn, Aphra&lt;/persName&gt; &lt;/author&gt;
    &lt;respStmt xml:id="pcaton.xzc"&gt; &lt;persName&gt;Caton, Paul&lt;/persName&gt;
    &lt;resp&gt;electronic publication editor&lt;/resp&gt; &lt;/respStmt&gt; &lt;respStmt
    xml:id="wgui.ner"&gt; &lt;persName&gt;Gui, Weihsin&lt;/persName&gt;
    &lt;resp&gt;encoder&lt;/resp&gt; &lt;/respStmt&gt; &lt;respStmt xml:id="jwernimo.lrv"&gt;
    &lt;persName&gt;Wernimont, Jacqueline&lt;/persName&gt; &lt;resp&gt;encoder&lt;/resp&gt;
    &lt;/respStmt&gt;&lt;/titleStmt&gt;</p>
  <p>There is however no requirement that the respStmt be used for this person, or that the elements
    indicated be contained within the same document. A project might for example maintain a separate
    document listing all of its personnel in which they were represented using the person element
    described in 15.2.2 The Participant Description.</p>
  <p>3.6 Minimal and recommended header information</p>
  <p>The MEI header allows for the provision of a very large amount of information concerning the
    text itself, its source, its encodings, and revisions of it, as well as a wealth of descriptive
    information such as the languages it uses and the situation(s) in which it was produced,
    together with the setting and identity of participants within it. This diversity and richness
    reflects the diversity of uses to which it is envisaged that electronic texts conforming to
    these Guidelines will be put. It is emphatically not intended that all of the elements described
    above should be present in every MEI Header. </p>
  <p>The amount of encoding in a header will depend both on the nature and the intended use of the
    text. At one extreme, an encoder may expect that the header will be needed only to provide a
    bibliographic identification of the text adequate to local needs. At the other, wishing to
    ensure that their texts can be used for the widest range of applications, encoders will want to
    document as explicitly as possible both bibliographic and descriptive information, in such a way
    that no prior or ancillary knowledge about the text is needed in order to process it. The header
    in such a case will be very full, approximating to the kind of documentation often supplied in
    the form of a manual. Most texts will lie somewhere between these extremes; textual corpora in
    particular will tend more to the latter extreme. In the remainder of this section we demonstrate
    first the minimal, and next a commonly recommended, level of encoding for the bibliographic
    information held by the MEI header. </p>
  <p>Supplying only the minimal level of encoding required, the MEI header of a single text might
    look like the following example: </p>
  <p>&lt;meiHead&gt; &lt;fileDesc&gt; &lt;titleStmt&gt; &lt;title&gt;Thomas Paine: Common sense, a
    machine-readable transcript&lt;/title&gt; &lt;respStmt&gt; &lt;resp&gt;compiled by&lt;/resp&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;Jon K Adams&lt;/name&gt; &lt;/respStmt&gt; &lt;/titleStmt&gt;
    &lt;publicationStmt&gt; &lt;distributor&gt;Oxford Text Archive&lt;/distributor&gt;
    &lt;/publicationStmt&gt; &lt;sourceDesc&gt; &lt;bibl&gt;The complete writings of Thomas Paine,
    collected and edited by Phillip S. Foner (New York, Citadel Press, 1945)&lt;/bibl&gt;
    &lt;/sourceDesc&gt; &lt;/fileDesc&gt;&lt;/meiHead&gt;The only mandatory component of the MEI
    Header is the fileDesc element. Within this, titleStmt, publicationStmt, and sourceDesc are all
    required constituents. Within the title statement, a title is required, and an author should be
    specified, even if it is unknown, as should some additional statement of responsibility, here
    given by the respStmt element. Within the publicationStmt, a publisher, distributor, or other
    agency responsible for the file must be specified. Finally, the source description should
    contain at the least a loosely structured bibliographic citation identifying the source of the
    electronic text if (as is usually the case) there is one. </p>
  <p>We now present the same example header, expanded to include additionally recommended
    information, adequate to most bibliographic purposes, in particular to allow for the creation of
    an AACR2-conformant bibliographic record. We have also added information about the encoding
    principles used in this (imaginary) encoding, about the text itself (in the form of Library of
    Congress subject headings), and about the revision of the file. </p>
  <p>[MEI head example here]</p>
  <p>Many other examples of recommended usage for the elements discussed in this chapter are
    provided here, in the reference index and in the associated tutorials. </p>
  <p>3.7 The MEI header module</p>
  <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:</p>
  <p>Module header: The MEI Header</p>
  <p>•Elements defined: [list of MEI elements]</p>
  <p>The selection and combination of modules to form an MEI schema is described in 1.2 Defining an
    MEI Schema.</p>
</div>
