<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  © 2010 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs Unported License, 
  Version 3.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/.
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="header" n="2">
  <head>The MEI Header</head>
  <!-- The following paragraph should be displayed prominently! -->
  <p>Note: This chapter draws heavily from its TEI analog. In the interest of quickly producing
    these MEI Guidelines, much has been "borrowed" from those of the TEI. While we anticipate that
    over time the MEI Guidelines will be revised to reduce their reliance on TEI, the editors of
    these Guidelines are extremely grateful and beg forgiveness for such blatant "borrowing".</p>
  <p>This chapter addresses the description of an encoded item so that the musical text, as well as
    its sources, encoding, and revisions are all thoroughly documented. Such documentation is
    necessary for scholars using the texts, for software processing them, and for catalogers in
    libraries and archives. Together these descriptions and declarations provide an electronic
    analog to the title page attached to a printed work. They also constitute an equivalent for the
    content of the code books or introductory manuals customarily accompanying electronic data
    sets.</p>
  <p>Every MEI-conformant text not embedded in another XML carrier that provides for capturing
    metadata, such as TEI or METS, must carry a set of descriptions, prefixed to it and encoded as
    described in this chapter. This set is known as the MEI header, tagged <gi>meiHead</gi>, and has
    five major parts:</p>
  <list type="ordered">
    <item>one or more identifiers, tagged with <gi>altId</gi>, each of which provides an identifying
      name or number associated with the file.</item>
    <item>a <term>file description</term>, tagged <gi>fileDesc</gi>, containing a full bibliographic
      description of the computer file itself, from which a user of the text could derive a proper
      bibliographic citation, or which a librarian or archivist could use in creating a catalog
      entry recording its presence within a library or archive. The term <term>computer file</term>
      here is to be understood as referring to the whole intellectual entity or document described
      by the header, even when this is stored in multiple physical operating system files. The file
      description also includes information about the source or sources from which the electronic
      document was derived. The MEI elements used to encode the file description are described in
      section <ptr target="#filedesc"/> below.</item>
    <item>an <term>encoding description</term>, tagged <gi>encodingDesc</gi>, which describes the
      relationship between an electronic text and its source or sources. It allows for detailed
      description of whether (or how) the text was normalized during transcription, how the encoder
      resolved ambiguities in the source, what levels of encoding or analysis were applied, and
      similar matters. The MEI elements used to encode the encoding description are described in
      section <ptr target="#encodingDescription"/> below.</item>
    <item>a <term>work description</term>, tagged <gi>workDesc</gi>, containing classification and
      contextual information about the work, such as its subject matter, the situation in which it
      was produced, the individuals described by or participating in producing it, and so forth.
      Such a work profile is of particular use in highly structured composite texts such as corpora
      or language collections, where it is often highly desirable to enforce a controlled
      descriptive vocabulary or to perform retrievals from a body of text in terms of text type or
      origin. The work description may however be of use in any form of automatic text processing.
      The MEI elements used to encode the <term>work description</term> are described in section
        <ptr target="#workDescription"/> below.</item>
    <item>a <term>revision history</term>, tagged <gi>revisionDesc</gi>, which allows the encoder to
      provide a history of changes made during the development of the electronic text. The revision
      history is important for <term>version control</term> and for resolving questions about the
      history of a file. The MEI elements used to encode the revision description are described in
      section <ptr target="#revisionDescription"/> below.</item>
  </list>
  <div xml:id="fileDescription" type="div2">
    <head>File Description</head>
    <p>The structure of the bibliographic description of a machine-readable or digital musical text
      resembles that of a book, an article, or other kinds of textual objects. The file description
      element of the MEI header has therefore been closely modeled on existing standards in library
      cataloging; it should thus provide enough information to allow users to give standard
      bibliographic references to the electronic text, and to allow catalogers to catalog it.
      Bibliographic citations occurring elsewhere in the header, and in the text itself, are derived
      from the same model.</p>
    <p>The bibliographic description of an electronic musical text should be supplied by the
      mandatory <gi>fileDesc</gi> element:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="fileDesc"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>The <gi>fileDesc</gi> element contains two mandatory and six optional elements, each of which
      is described in more detail below. These elements are listed below in the order in which they
      must occur within the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element.</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="titleStmt"/>
        <specDesc key="editionStmt"/>
        <specDesc key="extent"/>
        <specDesc key="fingerprint"/>
        <specDesc key="pubStmt"/>
        <specDesc key="seriesStmt"/>
        <specDesc key="notesStmt"/>
        <specDesc key="sourceDesc"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>A complete file description will resemble the following example:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title><!-- title of the resource --></title>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
          <!-- information about the edition of the resource -->
        </editionStmt>
        <extent><!-- description of the size of the resource --></extent>
        <pubStmt>
          <!-- information about the publication and distribution of the resource -->
        </pubStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
          <!-- information about any series to which the resource belongs -->
        </seriesStmt>
        <notesStmt>
          <annot><!-- notes on other aspects of the resource --></annot>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <!-- information about the source(s) from which the resource was derived -->
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    </egXML>
    <div xml:id="titlestmt" type="div3">
      <head>Title Statement</head>
      <p>The <gi>titleStmt</gi> element is the first component of the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element, and
        is mandatory:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="titleStmt"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>It contains the title given to the electronic work, together with one or more optional
        statements of responsibility which identify the encoder, editor, author, compiler, or other
        parties responsible for it:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="title"/>
          <specDesc key="respStmt"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>title</gi> element contains the chief name of the electronic work. Its content
        takes the form considered appropriate by its creator. The element may be repeated, if the
        work has more than one title (perhaps in different languages). Where the electronic work is
        derived from an existing source text, it is strongly recommended that the title for the
        former should be derived from the latter, but clearly distinguishable from it, for example
        by the addition of a phrase such as ‘: an electronic transcription’ or ‘a digital edition’.
        This will distinguish the electronic work from the source text in citations and in catalogs,
        which contain descriptions of both types of material.</p>
      <p>Other alternative titles or subtitles may be encoded in additional title elements with
        values in the <att>type</att> attribute that distinguish them from the chief title. Sample
        values for the <att>type</att> attribute include: main (main title), subordinate (subtitle,
        title of part), abbreviated (abbreviated form of title), alternative (alternate title by
        which the work is also known), translated (translated form of title), uniform (collective
        title). The name of a list from which other values of the <att>type</att> attribute are
        taken may be recorded using the <att>authority</att> attribute.</p>
      <p>The <att>type</att> attribute is provided for convenience in analyzing titles and
        processing them according to their type; where such specialized processing is not necessary,
        there is no need for such analysis, and the entire title, including subtitles and any
        parallel titles, may be enclosed within a single <gi>title</gi> element.</p>
      <p>The electronic work will also have an external name (its ‘filename’ or ‘data set name’) or
        reference number on the computer system where it resides at any time. This name is likely to
        change frequently, as new copies of the file are made on the computer system. Its form is
        entirely dependent on the particular computer system in use and thus cannot always easily be
        transferred from one system to another. Moreover, a given work may be composed of many
        files. For these reasons, these Guidelines strongly recommend that such names should not be
        used as the title for any electronic work.</p>
      <p>Helpful guidance on the formulation of useful descriptive titles in difficult cases may be
        found in the Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules (Gorman and Winkler, 1978, chapter 25) or in
        equivalent national-level bibliographical documentation.</p>
      <p>Any number of responsibility statements may occur within the title statement. The
          <gi>respStmt</gi> element has two subcomponents: a <gi>name</gi> element identifying a
        responsible individual or organization, and a <gi>resp</gi> element indicating the nature of
        the responsibility. All names should be stated in the form in which the persons or bodies
        wish to be publicly cited. This will usually be the fullest form of the name, including
        first names. No specific recommendations are made at this time as to appropriate content for
          <gi>resp</gi>. However, it should make clear the nature of the responsibility concerned,
        as in the examples below.</p>
      <p>At a minimum, the author of the text and (where appropriate) the creator of the file should
        be identified. If the bibliographic description is for a corpus, identify the creator of the
        corpus. Optionally also include the names of others involved in the transcription or
        elaboration of the text, sponsors, and funding agencies. The name of the person responsible
        for physical data input need not normally be recorded, unless that person is also
        intellectually responsible for some aspect of the creation of the file.</p>
      <p>When the MEI.namesdates module is enabled, two additional elements are permitted within
          <gi>respStmt</gi>:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="corpName"/>
          <specDesc key="persName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>These elements allow for more precise identification of the entity associated with the name
        than is permitted by the simpler <gi>name</gi> element.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Symphony No. 5 in C Minor : an electronic transcription</title>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Composed by: </resp>
            <persName>Ludwig van Beethoven</persName>
            <resp>Machine-readable transcription by: </resp>
            <persName>Maja Hartwig</persName>
            <persName>Kristina Richts</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
      </egXML>
      <p>In addition to, or instead of the <gi>resp</gi> element, the <att>role</att> attribute on
          <gi>name</gi>, <gi>persName</gi>, and <gi>corpName</gi> may be used to capture the nature
        of responsibility. While <gi>resp</gi> accommodates the wide variety of text that may occur
        in the description of responsibility statements, use of the <att>role</att> attribute
        provides the possibility of recording a controlled value independently of the textual
        content of <gi>resp</gi>.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Symphony No. 5 in C Minor : an electronic transcription</title>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Composed by: </resp>
            <persName role="composer">Ludwig van Beethoven</persName>
            <resp>Machine-readable transcription by: </resp>
            <persName role="encoder">Maja Hartwig</persName>
            <persName role="encoder">Kristina Richts</persName>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="editionstmt" type="div3">
      <head>Edition Statement</head>
      <p>The <gi>editionStmt</gi> element is the second component of the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element.
        It is optional but recommended when applicable.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="editionStmt"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>It contains elements for identifying the edition and those responsible for it:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="edition"/>
          <specDesc key="respStmt"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>For printed texts, the word 'edition' applies to the set of all the identical copies of an
        item produced from one master copy and issued by a particular publishing agency or a group
        of such agencies. A change in the identity of the distributing body or bodies does not
        normally constitute a change of edition, while a change in the master copy does.</p>
      <p>For electronic texts, the notion of a 'master copy' is not entirely appropriate, since they
        are far more easily copied and modified than printed ones; nonetheless, the term edition may
        be used for a particular state of a machine-readable text at which substantive changes are
        made and fixed. Synonymous terms used in these Guidelines are
        <mentioned>version</mentioned>, <mentioned>level</mentioned>, and
          <mentioned>release</mentioned>. The words <mentioned>revision</mentioned> and
          <mentioned>update</mentioned>, by contrast, are used for minor changes to a file which do
        not amount to a new edition.</p>
      <p>No simple rule can specify how ‘substantive’ changes have to be before they are regarded as
        producing a new edition, rather than a simple update. The general principle proposed here is
        that the production of a new edition entails a significant change in the intellectual
        content of the file, rather than its encoding or appearance. The addition of analytic coding
        to a text would thus constitute a new edition, while automatic conversion from one coded
        representation to another would not. Changes relating to the character code or physical
        storage details, corrections of misspellings, simple changes in the arrangement of the
        contents and changes in the output format do not normally constitute a new edition, whereas
        the addition of new information (e.g., a linguistic analysis expressed in part-of-speech
        tagging, sound or graphics, referential links to external data sets) almost always does.</p>
      <p>Clearly, there will always be borderline cases and the matter is somewhat arbitrary. The
        simplest rule is: if you think that your file is a new edition, then call it such. An
        edition statement is optional for the first release of a computer file; it is mandatory for
        each later release, though this requirement cannot be enforced.</p>
      <p>Note that all changes in a file, whether or not they are regarded as constituting a new
        edition or simply a new revision, should be independently noted in the revision description
        section of the file header (see section <ptr target="#revisionDescription"/>).</p>
      <p>The edition element should contain phrases describing the edition or version, including the
        word 'edition', 'version', or an equivalent term, together with a number or date, or terms
        indicating difference from other editions such as 'new edition', 'revised edition', etc. Any
        dates that occur within the edition statement should be marked with the <gi>date</gi>
        element. The <att>n</att> attribute of the edition element may be used as elsewhere to
        supply any formal identification (such as a version number) for the edition.</p>
      <p>One or more <gi>respStmt</gi> elements may also be used to supply statements of
        responsibility for the edition in question. These may refer to individuals or corporate
        bodies and can indicate functions such as that of a reviser, or can name the person or body
        responsible for the provision of supplementary matter, of appendices, etc., in a new
        edition.</p>
      <p>Some examples follow:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <editionStmt>
          <edition n="D2">Second draft, substantially extended, revised, and corrected.</edition>
        </editionStmt>
      </egXML>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <editionStmt>
          <edition>Student's edition, <date>June 1987</date></edition>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>New annotations by</resp>
            <name>George Brown</name>
          </respStmt>
        </editionStmt>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="physicalDescription" type="div3">
      <head>Physical Description of the File</head>
      <p>The third component of the fileDesc is a description of the physical qualities of the file.
        Two elements, both optional, are provided for this purpose:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="extent"/>
          <specDesc key="fingerprint"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>extent</gi> element describes the approximate size of a text as stored on some
        carrier medium, whether digital or non-digital, specified in any convenient units.</p>
      <p>For printed books, information about the carrier, such as the kind of medium used and its
        size, are of great importance in cataloging procedures. The print-oriented rules for
        bibliographic description of an item's medium and extent need some re-interpretation when
        applied to electronic media. An electronic file exists as a distinct entity quite
        independently of its carrier and remains the same intellectual object whether it is stored
        on a magnetic tape, a CD-ROM, a set of floppy disks, or as a file on a mainframe computer.
        Since, moreover, these Guidelines are specifically aimed at facilitating transparent
        document storage and interchange, any purely machine-dependent information should be
        irrelevant as far as the file header is concerned.</p>
      <p>This is particularly true of information about file-type although library-oriented rules
        for cataloging often distinguish two types of computer file: ‘data’ and ‘programs’. This
        distinction is quite difficult to draw in some cases, for example, hypermedia or texts with
        built-in search and retrieval software.</p>
      <p>Although it is equally system-dependent, some measure of the size of the computer file may
        be of use for cataloging and other practical purposes. Because the measurement and
        expression of file size is fraught with difficulties, only very general recommendations are
        possible; the element <gi>extent</gi>is provided for this purpose. It should contain a
        phrase indicating the size or approximate size of the computer file in one of the following
        ways:</p>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>in bytes of a specified length (e.g. ‘4000 16-bit bytes’)</item>
        <item>as falling within a range of values, for example: <list type="simple">
            <item>less than 1 Mb</item>
            <item>between 1 Mb and 5 Mb</item>
            <item>between 6 Mb and 10 Mb</item>
            <item>over 10 Mb</item>
          </list>
        </item>
        <item>in terms of any convenient logical units (for example, words or sentences, citations,
          paragraphs)</item>
        <item>in terms of any convenient physical units (for example, blocks, disks, tapes)</item>
      </list>
      <p>The use of standard abbreviations for units of quantity is recommended where applicable,
        here as elsewhere (see http://physics.nist.gov/cuu/Units/binary.html).</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <extent>between 1 16-bit MB and 2 16-bit MB</extent>
        <extent>4.2 MiB</extent>
        <extent>4532 Mbytes</extent>
        <extent>3200 sentences</extent>
        <extent>5 90-mm high density diskettes</extent>
      </egXML>
      <p>In one sense, the <gi>fingerprint</gi> element holds an identifier for the file. However,
        because this identifier, often referred to as a <term>checksum</term>, is computed from the
        file's contents, it can also be said to capture physical information about the file. The
        computed fingerprint can be used to distinguish between different versions of the file. That
        is, if the checksum of two files do not match, the data may have been altered or corrupted.
        MEI does not prescribe any particular method for computing the fingerprint.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <fingerprint>01805fe7508f0d98c595ba97b798717x</fingerprint>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="publicationDistribution" type="div3">
      <head>Publication, Distribution, etc.</head>
      <p>The <gi>pubStmt</gi> element is the fourth component of the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element and
        is mandatory.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="pubStmt"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>It may contain either a single <gi>unpub</gi> element, indicating that the file has yet to
        be published, or in the case of published material, one or more elements from the
        model.nameLike.geogname, model.addressLike, model.dateLike, and model.identifierLike
        classes, as well as the elements <gi>availability</gi> and <gi>respStmt</gi>.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="respStmt"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>respStmt</gi> element may be used to identify the publisher and distributor of the
        file. The publisher is the person or institution by whose authority a given edition of the
        file is made public. The distributor is the person or institution from whom copies of the
        text may be obtained.</p>
      <p>The following elements may be used to provide additional details regarding the publication
        and distribution of a bibliographic entity:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="geogName"/>
          <specDesc key="address"/>
          <specDesc key="identifier"/>
          <specDesc key="availability"/>
          <specDesc key="date"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The sub-elements of <gi>availability</gi> should be used to provide detailed information
        regarding the availability of an item.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="acqSource"/>
          <specDesc key="accessRestrict"/>
          <specDesc key="price"/>
          <specDesc key="useRestrict"/>
          <specDesc key="sysReq"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>Note that the dates, places, etc., given in the publication statement relate to the
        publisher, distributor, or release authority most recently mentioned. If the text was
        created at some date other than its date of publication, its date of creation should be
        given within the <gi>workDesc</gi> element, not in the publication statement. Give any other
        useful dates (e.g., dates of collection of data) in an <gi>annotation</gi> within the notes
        statement.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <pubStmt>
          <respStmt>
            <corpName>Musikwissenschaftliches Seminar &lt;Detmold&gt;</corpName>
          </respStmt>
          <address>
               <addrLine>Gartenstrasse 20</addrLine>
               <addrLine>32756 <geogName>Detmold</geogName></addrLine>
               <addrLine><geogName>Germany</geogName></addrLine>
            </address>
          <date>2011</date>
          <availability>
            <useRestrict>© 2004, MEI Consortium</useRestrict>
          </availability>
        </pubStmt>
      </egXML>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <pubStmt>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Publisher</resp>
            <corpName>Segno Press Inc.</corpName>
          </respStmt>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Distributor</resp>
            <corpName>University of Virginia</corpName>
          </respStmt>
          <address>
            <addrLine>21 B LowWater Street,</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Charlottesville, Virginia</addrLine>
            <addrLine>22901</addrLine>
          </address>
          <date>2010</date>
          <identifier>1234</identifier>
          <availability>
            <useRestrict>Available for purposes of academic research and teaching
              only.</useRestrict>
          </availability>
        </pubStmt>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="seriesStatement" type="div3">
      <head>Series Statement</head>
      <p>The <gi>seriesStmt</gi> element is the fifth component of the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element and
        is optional.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="seriesStmt"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>A series may be defined in one of the following ways:</p>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>A group of separate items related to one another by the fact that each item bears, in
          addition to its own title proper, a collective title applying to the group as a whole. The
          individual items may or may not be numbered.</item>
        <item>Each of two or more volumes of essays, lectures, articles, or other items, similar in
          character and issued in sequence.</item>
        <item>A separately numbered sequence of volumes within a series or serial.</item>
      </list>
      <p>The <gi>seriesStmt</gi> element may contain one or more of the following more specific
        elements:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="title"/>
          <specDesc key="respStmt"/>
          <specDesc key="identifier"/>
          <specDesc key="contents"/>
          <specDesc key="seriesStmt"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>title</gi> and <gi>respStmt</gi> elements have the same function described above:
        identification of the item, in this case the series, and the individuals or groups
        responsible for its creation and production. The <gi>title</gi> element is required within
          <gi>seriesStmt</gi>.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <seriesStmt>
          <title>MEI Sample Collection</title>
        </seriesStmt>
      </egXML>
      <p>The <gi>identifier</gi> element may be used to supply any identifying number associated
        with the series, including both standard numbers such as an ISSN and particular issue
        numbers. (Arabic numerals separated by punctuation are recommended for this purpose:
        '6.19.33', for example, rather than 'VI/xix:33'). Its <att>type</att> attribute is used to
        categorize the number further, taking the value 'ISSN' for an ISSN, for example.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <seriesStmt>
          <title level="s">Studies in Ornamentation</title>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>ed. by</resp>
            <name>Jacques Composeur</name>
          </respStmt>
          <identifier type="vol">1.2</identifier>
          <identifier type="ISSN">0 345 6789</identifier>
        </seriesStmt>
      </egXML>
      <p>The contents of the series may be enumerated using the <gi>contents</gi> element. Use of
        this element should be determined by the complexity of the resource and whether or not the
        information is readily available. The <gi>contents</gi> element may consist of a single
        paragraph when unstructured information is sufficient.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <contents>
          <p>On Wenlock Edge -- From Far, From Eve and Morning -- Is My Team Ploughing? -- Oh, When
            I Was In Love With You -- Bredon Hill -- Clun</p>
        </contents>
      </egXML>
      <p>Alternatively, <gi>contentItem</gi> elements may be used to provide structure for the
        content description.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <contents>
          <head>Contents</head>
          <contentItem>On Wenlock Edge</contentItem>
          <contentItem>From Far, From Eve and Morning</contentItem>
          <contentItem>Is My Team Ploughing?</contentItem>
          <contentItem>Oh, When I Was In Love With You</contentItem>
          <contentItem>Bredon Hill</contentItem>
          <contentItem>Clun</contentItem>
        </contents>
      </egXML>
      <p>Finally, using the <att>target</att> attribute, a link to an external table of contents may
        be supplied in lieu of or in addition to the child elements of <gi>contents</gi>.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <contents target="http://www.series.content/12345"/>
      </egXML>
      <p>The <gi>seriesStmt</gi> element is allowed to nest within itself in order to accommodate a
        series within a series.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"/>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="notesStatement" type="div3">
      <head>Notes Statement</head>
      <p>The <gi>notesStmt</gi> element is the sixth component of the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element and
        is optional. If used, it contains one or more <gi>annot</gi> elements, each containing a
        single piece of descriptive information of the kind treated as ‘general notes’ in
        traditional bibliographic descriptions.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="notesStmt"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>Some information found in the notes area in conventional bibliography has been assigned
        specific elements in these Guidelines; in particular the following items should be tagged as
        indicated, rather than as general notes:</p>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>the nature, scope, artistic form, or purpose of the file; also the genre or other
          intellectual category to which it may belong. These should be formally described within
          the <gi>workDesc</gi> element (section <ptr target="#workDescription"/>).</item>
        <item>bibliographic details relating to the source or sources of an electronic text: e.g.
          ‘Transcribed from a facsimile of the 1743 publication’. These should be formally described
          in the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element (section <ptr target="#sourceDescription"/>).</item>
        <item>further information relating to publication, distribution, or release of the text,
          including sources from which the text may be obtained, any restrictions on its use or
          formal terms on its availability. These should be placed in the appropriate division of
          the <gi>pubStmt</gi> element (section <ptr target="#publicationDistribution"/>).</item>
        <item>publicly documented numbers associated <emph>with the file</emph> should be placed in
          an <gi>altId</gi> element within the <gi>meiHead</gi> element. International Standard
          Serial Numbers (ISSN), International Standard Book Numbers (ISBN), and other
          internationally agreed upon standard numbers that uniquely identify an item, should be
          treated in the same way, rather than as specialized bibliographic notes. As described
          elsewhere, identifiers <emph>for sources of the file</emph> should be recorded within the
            <gi>sourceDesc</gi>.</item>
      </list>
      <p>Nevertheless, the <gi>notesStmt</gi> element may be used to record potentially significant
        details about the file and its features, e.g.:</p>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>dates, when they are relevant to the content or condition of the computer file: e.g.
          ‘manual dated 2010’, ‘file validated Apr 2011’</item>
        <item>names of persons or bodies connected with the technical production, administration, or
          consulting functions of the effort which produced the file, if these are not named in
          statements of responsibility in the title or edition statements of the file description:
          e.g. ‘Historical commentary provided by members of the Big Symphony Orchestra’</item>
        <item>availability of the file in an additional medium or information not already recorded
          about the availability of documentation: e.g. ‘User manual is loose-leaf in eleven
          paginated sections’</item>
        <item>language of work and abstract, if not encoded in the langUsage element, e.g. ‘Text in
          English with stage directions in French and German’</item>
      </list>
      <p>Each such item of information may be tagged using the general-purpose <gi>annot</gi>
        element. Groups of annotations are contained within the <gi>notesStmt</gi> element, as in
        the following example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <notesStmt>
          <annot>Historical commentary provided by John Smith.</annot>
          <annot>OCR scanning performed at University of Virginia.</annot>
        </notesStmt>
      </egXML>
      <p>There are advantages, however, to encoding such information with more precise elements
        elsewhere in the MEI header, when such elements are available. For example, the notes above
        might be encoded as follows:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <titleStmt>
          <title>…</title>
          <respStmt>
            <persName>John Smith</persName>
            <resp>historical commentary</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <respStmt>
            <orgName>University of Virginia</orgName>
            <resp>OCR scanning</resp>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="sourceDescription" type="div3">
      <head>Source Description</head>
      <p>The <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element is the seventh and final component of the <gi>fileDesc</gi>
        element. In MEI, <gi>sourceDesc</gi> is a grouping element containing one or more
          <gi>source</gi> elements, each of which records details of a source from which a computer
        file is derived. This might be a printed text or manuscript, another computer file, an audio
        or video recording, or a combination of these. An electronic file may also have no source,
        if what is being cataloged is an original text created in electronic form.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="sourceDesc"/>
          <specDesc key="source"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The content model of the <gi>source</gi> element is similar to that of the
          <gi>fileDesc</gi> and <gi>work</gi> elements. The list below reflects the order in which
        the components of <gi>source</gi> must occur.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="identifier"/>
          <specDesc key="titleStmt"/>
          <specDesc key="editionStmt"/>
          <specDesc key="pubStmt"/>
          <specDesc key="physDesc"/>
          <specDesc key="seriesStmt"/>
          <specDesc key="notesStmt"/>
          <specDesc key="history"/>
          <specDesc key="langUsage"/>
          <specDesc key="key"/>
          <specDesc key="tempo"/>
          <specDesc key="meter"/>
          <specDesc key="perfMedium"/>
          <specDesc key="classification"/>
          <specDesc key="castList"/>
          <specDesc key="incip"/>
          <specDesc key="contents"/>
          <specDesc key="relatedItem"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>In the simplest case, the <gi>source</gi> element may contain nothing more than a notes
        statement giving a simple prose description or a brief note stating that the document has no
        physical source:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <sourceDesc>
          <source>
            <notesStmt>
              <annot>Based on the Porter Wagner edition.</annot>
            </notesStmt>
          </source>
        </sourceDesc>
      </egXML>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <sourceDesc>
          <source>
            <notesStmt>
              <annot>Born digital.</annot>
            </notesStmt>
          </source>
        </sourceDesc>
      </egXML>
      <p>Alternatively, it may contain a basic bibliographic citation, also in an annotation:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <sourceDesc>
          <source>
            <notesStmt>
              <annot>Bach, Carl Philipp Emanuel. Sonata in B-flat major, Wq.62/1 (H.2)</annot>
            </notesStmt>
          </source>
        </sourceDesc>
      </egXML>
      <p>Most of the time, however, more structured bibliographic data is desired:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <sourceDesc>
          <source xml:id="s1">
            <identifier>1</identifier>
            <titleStmt>
              <title>Sonata in B-flat major, <identifier>Wq. 62/1 (H.2)</identifier></title>
              <respStmt>
                <name>Bach, Carl Philipp Emanuel</name>
              </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <pubStmt>
              <geogName>Paris</geogName>
              <respStmt>
                <name>A. Farrenc</name>
              </respStmt>
              <date>1861-72</date>
            </pubStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
              <title>Tresor des Pianistes, Vol. 13</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
              <annot>reprinted New York: Dover Publications, n.d.</annot>
            </notesStmt>
          </source>
        </sourceDesc>
      </egXML>
      <p>The<gi> identifier</gi> element is provided within <gi>source</gi> in order to accommodate
        identifying strings which cannot be captured by the <att>xml:id</att> attribute, such as
        numbers or strings requiring XML markup.</p>
      <p>The <gi>titleStmt</gi>, <gi>editionStmt</gi>, <gi>pubStmt</gi>, <gi>seriesStmt</gi>, and
          <gi>notesStmt</gi> elements function in exactly the same way as described in section <ptr
          target="#fileDescription"/> above and <ptr target="#workDescription"/> below and will not
        be covered again here.</p>
      <p>The <gi>history</gi> element is a container for non-bibliographic details relating to the
        creation of a source. The languages and sub-languages used by the source can be recorded in
        the <gi>langUsage</gi> element as described in section <ptr target="#"/> below. The usage of
          <gi>key</gi>, <gi>tempo</gi>, and <gi>meter</gi> below in section <ptr
          target="#workKeyTempoMeter"/>. The elements <gi>perfMedium</gi>; <gi>classification</gi>,
          <gi>castList</gi>, <gi>incip</gi>, <gi>contents</gi>, and <gi>relatedItem</gi> are also
        discussed in sections , <ptr target="#workMedium"/>, <ptr target="#workClass"/>, <ptr
          target="#workCast"/>, <ptr target="#workIncipit"/>, <ptr target="#workContents"/>, and
          <ptr target="#workRelatedItems"/>, respectively.</p>
      <p>If a source of the file is an unpublished manuscript, it is recommended that the
          <gi>unpub</gi> element be used as the only content of the source's <gi>pubStmt</gi>
        element. Other identifying information for the manuscript may be collected in the
          <gi>notesStmt</gi> element, as described in section <ptr target="#notesStatement"/>.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <source>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>[Untitled Bach Manuscript]</title>
            <respStmt>
              <persName>Johann Sebastian Bach</persName>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <pubStmt>
            <unpub/>
          </pubStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <annot>Manuscript discovered in library stacks, 2012</annot>
          </notesStmt>
        </source>
      </egXML>
      <div xml:id="associatingMetadataAndData">
        <head>Associating Metadata and Data</head>
        <p>In the MEI header, the <att>data</att> attribute may be used to associate metadata with
          related notational elements:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <!-- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -->
        </egXML>
        <p>Similarly, in the body of the MEI document, the <att>decls</att> attribute may be used to
          associate parts of the encoded text with related metadata:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <!-- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -->
        </egXML>
        <p>Most often the association is between the bibliographic description of a source and the
          material which is derived from it.</p>
      </div>
      <!--<div xml:id="computerFiles" type="div4">
        <head>MEI Files Derived From Other MEI Files</head>
        <p>If a computer file (call it B) is derived not from a printed source but from another
          computer file (call it A) which includes an MEI file header, then the source text of
          computer file B is another computer file, A. The four sections of A's file header will
          need to be incorporated into the new header for B in slightly differing ways, as listed
          below:</p>
        <list type="gloss">
          <label><gi>fileDesc</gi></label>
          <item>A's file description should be copied into the sourceDesc section of B's file
            description</item>
          <label><gi>workDesc</gi></label>
          <item>A's workDesc should be copied into B's, in principle unchanged; it may however be
            expanded by project-specific information relating to B.</item>
          <label><gi>encodingDesc</gi></label>
          <item>A's encoding practice may or (more likely) may not be the same as B's. Since the
            object of the encoding description is to define the relationship between the current
            file and its source, in principle only changes in encoding practice between A and B need
            be documented in B. The relationship between A and its source(s) is then only
            recoverable from the original header of A. In practice it may be more convenient to
            create a new complete encodingDesc for B based on A's.</item>
          <label><gi>revisionDesc</gi></label>
          <item>B is a new computer file, and should therefore have a new revision description. If,
            however, it is felt useful to include some information from A's revisionDesc, for
            example dates of major updates or versions, such information must be clearly marked as
            relating to A rather than to B.</item>
        </list>
      </div>-->
    </div>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="encodingDescription" type="div2">
    <head>Encoding Description</head>
    <p>The <gi>encodingDesc</gi> element is the second major subdivision of the MEI header. It
      specifies the methods and editorial principles which governed the transcription or encoding of
      the source material. Though not formally required, its use is highly recommended.</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="encodingDesc"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>The encoding description may contain elements taken from the model.encodingPart class. By
      default, this class makes available the following elements:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="appInfo"/>
        <specDesc key="editorialDecl"/>
        <specDesc key="projectDesc"/>
        <specDesc key="samplingDecl"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>Each of these elements is further described in the appropriate section below.</p>
    <div xml:id="applicationInformation" type="div3">
      <head>Application Information</head>
      <p>It is sometimes convenient to store information relating to the processing of an encoded
        resource within its header. Typical uses for such information might be:</p>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>to allow an application to discover that it has previously opened or edited a file,
          and what version of itself was used to do that;</item>
        <item>to show (through a date) which application last edited the file to allow for diagnosis
          of any problems that might have been caused by that application;</item>
        <item>to allow users to discover information about an application used to edit the
          file</item>
        <item>to allow the application to declare an interest in elements of the file which it has
          edited, so that other applications or human editors may be more wary of making changes to
          those sections of the file.</item>
      </list>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="application" atts="version"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>Each <gi>application</gi> element identifies the current state of one software application
        with regard to the current file. This element is a member of the att.datable class, which
        provides a variety of attributes for associating this state with a date and time, or a
        temporal range. The <att>xml:id</att> and <att>version</att> attributes should be used to
        uniquely identify the application and its major version number (for example, 'Edirom Tool
        1.5'). It is not intended that a software application should add a new <gi>application</gi>
        element each time it touches the file.</p>
      <p>The following example shows how these elements might be used to document the fact that
        version 1.5 of an application called ‘Music Markup Tool’ has an interest in two parts of a
        document which was last saved on June 6, 2011. The parts concerned are accessible at the
        URLs given as targets of the two <gi>ptr</gi> elements.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <appInfo>
          <application xml:id="MusicMarkupTool" version="1.5">
            <name>Music Markup Tool</name>
            <ptr target="#P1"/>
            <ptr target="#P2"/>
          </application>
        </appInfo>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="EditorialPrinciples" type="div3">
      <head>Declaration of Editorial Principles</head>
      <p>The <gi>editorialDecl</gi> element is used to provide details of the editorial practices
        applied during the encoding of a musical text.</p>
      <p>It may contain a prose description only, or one or more of a set of specialized elements,
        members of the MEI model.editorialDeclPart class. Where an encoder wishes to record an
        editorial policy not specified above, this may be done by formally adding a new element to
        this class, using the mechanisms discussed in chapter <ptr target="#"/> "Personalization and
        Customization".</p>
      <p>Some of these policy elements carry attributes to support automated processing of certain
        well-defined editorial decisions; all of them contain a prose description of the editorial
        principles adopted with respect to the particular feature concerned. Examples of the kinds
        of questions which these descriptions are intended to answer are given in the list
        below.</p>
      <list type="gloss">
        <label>correction</label>
        <item>
          <specDesc key="correction" atts="corrlevel"/>
          <specDesc key="att.regularmethod" atts="method"/>
          <p>Was the text corrected during or after data capture? If so, were corrections made
            silently or are they marked using the tags described in section <ptr target="#"/>
            "Simple Editorial Changes"? What principles have been adopted with respect to omissions,
            truncations, dubious corrections, alternate readings, false starts, repetitions,
            etc.?</p></item>
        <label>interpretation</label>
        <item>
          <specDesc key="interpretation"/>
          <p>Has any analytic or ‘interpretive’ information been provided — that is, information
            which is felt to be non-obvious, or potentially contentious? If so, how was it
            generated? How was it encoded?</p></item>
        <label>normalization</label>
        <item>
          <specDesc key="normalization"/>
          <specDesc key="att.regularmethod" atts="method"/>
          <p>Was the text normalized, for example by regularizing any non-standard enharmonic
            spellings, etc.? If so, were normalizations performed silently or are they marked using
            the tags described in section <ptr target="#"/> "Simple Editorial Changes"? What
            authority was used for the regularization? Also, what principles were used when
            normalizing numbers to provide the standard values for the <att>value</att> attribute
            described in section <ptr target="#"/> "Numbers and Measures" and what format is used
            for them?</p>
        </item>
        <label>segmentation</label>
        <item>
          <specDesc key="segmentation"/>
          <p>How is the musical text segmented? If mdiv and/or section elements have been used to
            partition the music for analysis, how are they marked and how was the segmentation
            arrived at?</p></item>
        <label>standard values</label>
        <item>
          <specDesc key="stdVals"/>
          <p>In most cases, attributes bearing standardized values should conform to a defined
            datatype. In cases where this is not appropriate, this element may be used to describe
            the standardization methods underlying the values supplied.</p></item>
      </list>
      <p>Experience shows that a full record should be kept of decisions relating to editorial
        principles and encoding practice, both for future users of the text and for the project
        which produced the text in the first instance. Any information about the editorial
        principles applied not falling under one of the above headings may be recorded as additional
        prose following the special-use elements.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <editorialDecl>
          <segmentation>
            <p>Separate mdiv elements have been created for each movement of the work.</p>
          </segmentation>
          <interpretation>
            <p>The harmonic analysis applied throughout movement 1 was added by hand and has not
              been checked.</p>
          </interpretation>
          <correction>
            <p>Errors in transcription controlled by using the Finale editor.</p>
          </correction>
          <normalization>
            <p>All sung text converted to Modern American spelling following Webster’s 9th
              Collegiate dictionary.</p>
          </normalization>
          <p><!-- Other editorial practices described here. --></p>
        </editorialDecl>
      </egXML>
      <p>An editorial practices declaration which applies to more than one text or division of a
        text need not be repeated in the header of each text or division. Instead, the @decls
        attribute of each text (or subdivision of the text) to which it applies may be used to
        supply a cross-reference to the declaration, as further described in section <ptr
          target="#associatingMetadataAndData"/>.</p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="projectDescription" type="div3">
      <head>Project Description</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="projectDesc"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>projectDesc</gi> element may be used to describe, in prose, the purpose for which a
        digital resource was created, together with any other relevant information concerning the
        process by which it was assembled or collected. This is of particular importance for corpora
        or miscellaneous collections, but may be of use for any text, for example to explain why one
        kind of encoding practice has been followed rather than another.</p>
      <p>For example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <encodingDesc>
          <projectDesc>
            <p>Texts collected for use in the MEI Summer Workshop, Aug. 2012.</p>
          </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="samplingDeclaration" type="div3">
      <head>Sampling Declaration</head>
      <p>The samplingDecl element may be used to describe, in prose, the rationale and methods used
        in selecting texts, or parts of text, for inclusion in the resource.</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="samplingDecl"/>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>samplingDecl</gi> element should include information about such matters as: <list
          type="bulleted">
          <item>the size of individual samples</item>
          <item>the method or methods by which they were selected</item>
          <item>the underlying population being sampled</item>
          <item>the object of the sampling procedure used</item>
        </list> but is not restricted to these.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <samplingDecl>
          <p>Encoding contains 40 randomly-selected measures.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
      </egXML>
      <p>It may also include a simple description of any parts of the source text included or
        excluded:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <samplingDecl>
          <p>Only the songs have been transcribed. Advertisements have been silently omitted. All
            mathematical expressions have been omitted, and their place marked with a <gi>gap</gi>
            element.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
      </egXML>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <samplingDecl>
          <p>Only the first 6 measures of movement 1 are encoded.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
      </egXML>
      <p>A sampling declaration which applies to more than one text or division of a text need not
        be repeated in the header of each such text. Instead, the <att>decls</att> attribute of each
        text (or subdivision of the text) to which the sampling declaration applies may be used to
        supply a cross-reference to it, as further described in section <ptr
          target="#associatingMetadataAndData"/>.</p>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="workDescription" type="div2">
    <head>Work Description</head>
    <p>The <gi>workDesc</gi> element is the third major subdivision of the MEI Header. It is an
      optional element, the purpose of which is to enable the recording of information
      characterizing various descriptive aspects of the abstract work.</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="workDesc"/>
        <specDesc key="work"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>Within <gi>workDesc</gi>, the <gi>work</gi> element is used to hold information for each
      resource being described.</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="work"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>All the components of <gi>work</gi> are optional, but they must occur in the following
      order:</p>
    <list type="ordered">
      <item>identifier</item>
      <item>titleStmt</item>
      <item>history</item>
      <item>langUsage</item>
      <item>key</item>
      <item>tempo</item>
      <item>meter</item>
      <item>perfMedium</item>
      <item>notesStmt</item>
      <item>classification</item>
      <item>castList</item>
      <item>incip</item>
      <item>contents</item>
      <item>relatedItem</item>
    </list>
    <div xml:id="workIdentification" type="div3">
      <p>Basic data identifying the intellectual work may be recorded in <gi>identifier</gi> and
          <gi>titleStmt</gi> elements. The identifier and title values recorded here may or may not
        be the same as those assigned to published versions of the work.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="identifier"/>
          <specDesc key="titleStmt"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The following components provide detailed information about the work, including the
        circumstances of its creation, the languages used within it, high-level musical attributes,
        performing forces, etc.</p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="workHistory" type="div3">
      <head>Work History</head>
      <p>The following elements are provided to capture the history of a musical work:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="history"/>
          <specDesc key="creation"/>
          <specDesc key="eventList"/>
          <specDesc key="event"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>history</gi> element is a container for the non-bibliographic details relating to a
        work. The <gi>creation</gi> element is intended to contain a brief statement of the
        circumstances of the work's creation. Its content is limited to text and <gi>date</gi> and
          <gi>geogName</gi> elements. Following it, a list of key events in the creation of the work
        may be enumerated using <gi>eventList</gi>. The list is comprised of <gi>event</gi> elements
        that contain a brief description of the associated event, including dates and locations
        where the event took place. The <att>type</att> attribute may be used to distinguish between
        event lists with different functions, such as a list of events in the compositional process
        and a list of performance dates.</p>
      <p>Paragraphs may be mixed with event lists, or used instead of <gi>eventList</gi> and
          <gi>creation</gi> elements, when a fuller, 'essay-like' description is desired.</p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="workLanguage" type="div3">
      <head>Language Usage</head>
      <p>The <gi>langUsage</gi> element is used within the <gi>workDesc</gi> element to describe the
        languages, sublanguages, dialects, etc. represented within a work. It contains one or more
          <gi>language</gi> elements, each of which provides information about a single
        language.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="langUsage"/>
          <specDesc key="language" atts="id"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>A <gi>language</gi> element may be supplied for each different language used in a document.
        If used, its <att>xml:id</att> attribute should specify an appropriate language identifier.
        This is particularly important if extended language identifiers have been used as the value
        of @xml:lang attributes elsewhere in the document.</p>
      <p>Here is an example of the use of this element:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <langUsage>
          <language xml:id="fr-CA">Québecois</language>
          <language xml:id="en-CA">Canadian English</language>
          <language xml:id="en-GB">British English</language>
        </langUsage>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="workKeyTempoMeter" type="div3">
      <head>Key, Tempo, and Meter</head>
      <p>The attributes key, tempo, and meter are often helpful for identifying a musical work when
        it does not have a distinctive title.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="key"/>
          <specDesc key="tempo"/>
          <specDesc key="meter"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>key</gi> element used exclusively within bibliographic descriptions. Do not confuse
        this element with <gi>keySig</gi>, which is used within the body of an MEI file to record
        this data for musical notation. Likewise, <gi>meter</gi> should not be confused with the
        attributes used by staffDef and scoreDef to record meter-related data for notated music. The
          <gi>tempo</gi> element can be used here as well as in the body of an MEI document;
        however, its attributes other than <att>xml:id</att>, <att>label</att>, <att>n</att>,
          <att>base</att>, and <att>lang</att> are meaningless in the MEI header context, and
        therefore should be avoided within a work description.</p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="workMedium" type="div3">
      <head>Performance Medium</head>
      <p>The following elements are available for description of a composition's performing
        forces:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="perfMedium"/>
          <specDesc key="ensemble"/>
          <specDesc key="performer"/>
          <specDesc key="instrVoice"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The perfMedium element provides the possibility of describing a work in terms of its medium
        of performance when the medium is integral to the composition. The description may be as
        simple or complex as the encoder requires. For example, a work for a standard ensemble may
        be indicated thus:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <perfMedium>
          <ensemble>
            <instrVoice>Orchestra</instrVoice>
          </ensemble>
        </perfMedium>
      </egXML>
      <p>while a composition for a non-standard group may be described with:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <perfMedium>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Guitar</instrVoice>
          </performer>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Didgeridoo</instrVoice>
          </performer>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Bongos</instrVoice>
          </performer>
        </perfMedium>
      </egXML>
      <p>The number of instrumentalists or vocalists is represented by the choice of
          <gi>ensemble</gi> and <gi>performer</gi> child elements. In the example above, three
        performers are called for by the composer. If, however, the composer intended for all the
        instruments to be performed by a single musician, the intention could be indicated by the
        following markup:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <perfMedium>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Guitar</instrVoice>
            <instrVoice>Didgerydoo</instrVoice>
            <instrVoice>Bongos</instrVoice>
          </performer>
        </perfMedium>
      </egXML>
      <p>Often a combination of individual performers and ensembles is required:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <perfMedium>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Tenor</instrVoice>
          </performer>
          <ensemble>
            <instrVoice>String quartet</instrVoice>
          </ensemble>
          <ensemble>
            <instrVoice>3 Radios</instrVoice>
          </ensemble>
        </perfMedium>
      </egXML>
      <p>In those cases where it is desirable to enumerate the membership of an ensemble,
          <gi>performer</gi> may be employed:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <perfMedium>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Tenor</instrVoice>
          </performer>
          <ensemble>
            <instrVoice>String quartet</instrVoice>
            <performer>
              <instrVoice>Violin</instrVoice>
            </performer>
            <performer>
              <instrVoice>Violin</instrVoice>
            </performer>
            <performer>
              <instrVoice>Viola</instrVoice>
            </performer>
            <performer>
              <instrVoice>Violoncello</instrVoice>
            </performer>
          </ensemble>
        </perfMedium>
      </egXML>
      <p>For large ensembles where multiple instruments of the same kind are used, the @count
        attribute may be used to specify the number of players:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <perfMedium>
          <ensemble>
            <instrVoice>Concert band</instrVoice>
            <performer>
              <instrVoice count="2">Piccolo</instrVoice>
            </performer>
            <performer>
              <instrVoice count="2">Flute</instrVoice>
            </performer>
            <performer>
              <instrVoice count="3">1st Clarinet</instrVoice>
            </performer>
            <performer>
              <instrVoice count="3">2nd Clarinet</instrVoice>
            </performer>
            <performer>
              <instrVoice count="3">3rd Clarinet</instrVoice>
            </performer>
            <!-- and so on -->
          </ensemble>
        </perfMedium>
      </egXML>
      <p>Solo parts may be marked with the <att>solo</att> attribute of <gi>instrVoice</gi>, like
        so:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <performer>
          <instrVoice solo="true">Violin</instrVoice>
        </performer>
        <ensemble>
          <instrVoice>Orchestra</instrVoice>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Violin</instrVoice>
          </performer>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Violin</instrVoice>
          </performer>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Viola</instrVoice>
          </performer>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Violoncello</instrVoice>
          </performer>
        </ensemble>
      </egXML>
      <p>The <gi>instrVoice</gi> element is used in all cases to indicate instrument names, standard
        ensemble names, and voice qualities.</p>
      <p>Dramatic roles may be indicated via the use of the <gi>role</gi> element. For example, the
        vocal qualities and associated roles for Beethoven's opera <title>Fidelio</title> may be
        encoded as:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <perfMedium>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Tenor</instrVoice>
            <role>Florestan</role>
          </performer>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Soprano</instrVoice>
            <role>Leonore, his wife</role>
          </performer>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Bass</instrVoice>
            <role>Rocco, gaoler</role>
          </performer>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Soprano</instrVoice>
            <role>Marzelline, his daughter</role>
          </performer>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Tenor</instrVoice>
            <role>Jaquino, assistant to Rocco</role>
          </performer>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Bass-baritone</instrVoice>
            <role>Don Pizarro, governor of the prison</role>
          </performer>
          <performer>
            <instrVoice>Bass</instrVoice>
            <role>Don Fernando, King's minister</role>
          </performer>
        </perfMedium>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="workNotes" type="div3">
      <head>Notes Statement</head>
      <p>The <gi>notesStmt</gi> element may be used within the description of the musical work to
        capture information not accounted for by the other elements of the description.</p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="workClass" type="div3">
      <head>Classification</head>
      <p>The next component of the core <gi>workDesc</gi> element is the <gi>classification</gi>
        element. This element is used to classify a musical text according to one or more of the
        following methods:</p>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>by reference to a recognized international classification scheme such as the Dewey
          Decimal Classification, the Universal Decimal Classification, the Colon Classification,
          the Library of Congress Classification, or any other system widely used in library and
          documentation work</item>
        <item>by providing a set of keywords, as provided, for example, by British Library or
          Library of Congress Cataloguing in Publication data.</item>
      </list>
      <p>The following elements are provided for this purpose:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="termList"/>
          <specDesc key="classCode"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>termList</gi> element categorizes an individual text by supplying a set of terms
        which may describe its topic or subject matter, its physical or intellectual form, date,
        etc. Each term is indicated by a <gi>term</gi> element. In some schemes, the order of items
        in the list is significant, for example, from major topic to minor; in others, the list has
        an organized substructure of its own. No recommendations are made here as to which method is
        to be preferred. Wherever possible, such terms should be taken from a recognized source.</p>
      <p>The classCode element offers the possibility of capturing a bibliographic citation and/or a
        URI at which the classification scheme or information about it may be found.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <classCode xml:id="LoC_IccoA">Library of Congress subject headings. Prepared by the
          Cataloging Policy and Support Office, Collections Services. Washington, D.C.: Library of
          Congress, Cataloging Distribution Service, 1993- .</classCode>
      </egXML>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <classCode xml:id="LoC_lccoB"
          authURI="http://www.loc.gov/aba/cataloging/classification/lcco/lcco_m.pdf"/>
      </egXML>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <classCode xml:id="LoC_lccoC"
          authURI="http://www.loc.gov/aba/cataloging/classification/lcco/lcco_m.pdf">Library of
          Congress subject headings. Prepared by the Cataloging Policy and Support Office,
          Collections Services. Washington, D.C.: Library of Congress, Cataloging Distribution
          Service, 1993- .</classCode>
      </egXML>
      <p>The <att>classcode</att> attribute may be used on each term element to make reference, by
        means of an identifier, to the classification scheme from which it is drawn.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <classification>
          <classCode xml:id="LCSH" authority="Library of Congress" authURI="http://www.loc.gov"/>
          <classCode xml:id="LoC_lcco" authority="Library of Congress"
            authURI="http://www.loc.gov/aba/cataloging/classification/lcco/lcco_m.pdf"/>
          <termList>
            <term classcode="#LCSH">Guitar music (Rock) </term>
            <term classcode="#LCSH">Rock music 1971-1980.</term>
            <term classcode="#LoC_Icco">M1630.18.Z26 O6 2011</term>
          </termList>
        </classification>
      </egXML>
      <p>Alternatively, <att>classcode</att> may be used on <gi>termList</gi> when all the contained
        terms come from the same source.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <classification>
          <classCode xml:id="LCSH" authority="Library of Congress" authURI="http://www.loc.gov"/>
          <classCode xml:id="LoC_lcco" authority="Library of Congress"
            authURI="http://www.loc.gov/aba/cataloging/classification/lcco/lcco_m.pdf"/>
          <termList classcode="#LCSH">
            <term>Guitar music (Rock) </term>
            <term>Rock music 1971-1980.</term>
          </termList>
          <termList classcode="#LoC_Icco">
            <term>M1630.18.Z26 O6 2011</term>
          </termList>
        </classification>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="workCast" type="div3">
      <head>Cast Lists</head>
      <p>A cast list is a specialized form of list, conventionally found at the start or end of a
        dramatic work, usually listing all the speaking/singing and non-speaking/singing roles in
        the play, often with additional description (‘Cataplasma, a maker of Periwigges and
        Attires’) or the name of an actor or actress (‘Old Lady Squeamish. Mrs Rutter’).</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="castList"/>
        <specDesc key="castItem"/>
        <specDesc key="castGrp"/>
      </p>
      <p>Cast lists often function as identifying metadata and for this reason are permitted within
        the description of a work.</p>
      <p>Because the format and internal structure of cast lists are unpredictable, a
          <gi>castList</gi> may contain any combination of <gi>castItem</gi> and <gi>castGrp</gi>
        elements.</p>
      <p>A castItem element may contain any mixture of text and the following elements:</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="role"/>
        <specDesc key="roleDesc"/>
      </p>
      <p>In the following example, <gi>roleDesc</gi> is used to describe the voice range of the
        role.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <role>Comala</role>
        <roleDesc>Soprano</roleDesc>
        <role>Dersagrena</role>
        <roleDesc>Mezzo-Soprano</roleDesc>
        <role>Melicoma</role>
        <roleDesc>Alto</roleDesc>
        <role>Fingal</role>
        <roleDesc>Baritone</roleDesc>
      </egXML>
      <p>The castItem element may also contain:</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="actor"/>
      </p>
      <p>However, this element is unlikely to be useful in the context of a work description. It is
        available though for the very rare occasion when a work was conceived for and is only
        performable by a single person or group, such as certain "performance art" works.</p>
      <p>It is common to find some roles presented in groups or sublists. Roles are also often
        grouped together by their function. To accommodate these situations, the <gi>castGrp</gi>
        element is provided as a component of <gi>castList</gi>. It may contain any combination of
          <gi>castItem</gi>, <gi>castGrp</gi>, and <gi>roleDesc</gi> elements. For example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <!-- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -->
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="workIncipit" type="div3">
      <head>Incipits</head>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="incip"/>
      </p>
      <p>The first few notes and/or words of a piece of music are often used for identification
        purposes, especially when the piece has only a generic title, such as "Sonata no. 3". They
        appear in catalogs of music and in tables of contents of printed music that include multiple
        works.</p>
      <p>The following elements are provided for the inclusion of incipits:</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="incip"/>
        <specDesc key="incipCode"/>
        <specDesc key="incipText"/>
        <specDesc key="score"/>
        <specDesc key="graphic"/>
      </p>
      <p>The elements <gi>incipCode</gi> and <gi>incipText</gi> and available for the inclusion of
        coded incipits and textual incipits, respectively. The <gi>incipText</gi> element should
        contain only the initial performed text of the work, while <gi>incipCode</gi> may contain
        both words and music, depending on the capabilities of the scheme used to encode it. When
        both music and text are provided in <gi>incipCode</gi>, it may be helpful to repeat the text
        in <gi>incipText</gi> in order to provide easier access to only the text, for example, for
        indexing of the text without having to extract it from the coded incipit.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <!-- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -->
      </egXML>
      <p>Both <gi>incipCode</gi> and <gi>incipText</gi> allow reference to an external file location
        via the <att>target</att> attribute and specification of the internet media type of the
        external file via the <att>mimetype</att> attribute.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <!-- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -->
      </egXML>
      <p>An MEI-encoded incipit may be captured in the <gi>score</gi> element.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <!-- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -->
      </egXML>
      <p>In addition, <gi>graphic</gi> may be used to include an image of an incipit.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <!-- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -->
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="workContents" type="div3">
      <head>Contents</head>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="contents"/>
        <specDesc key="contentItem"/>
      </p>
      <p>Often, it is helpful to identify an entity by listing its constituent parts. A simple
        description of the work's content, such as may be found in a bibliographic record, can be
        given in single paragraph element:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <contents>
          <p>A suitable tone ; Left hand colouring ; Rhythm and accent ; Tempo ; Flexibility ;
            Ornaments</p>
        </contents>
      </egXML>
      <p>Alternatively, a structured contents list may be constructed using the <gi>contentItem</gi>
        element:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <contents>
          <contentItem>Sonata in D major, op. V, no. 1 / Corelli</contentItem>
          <contentItem>Sonata in G minor / Purcell (with Robert Donington, gamba)</contentItem>
          <contentItem>Forlane from Concert royal no. 3 / Couperin</contentItem>
        </contents>
      </egXML>
      <p>Each <gi>contentItem</gi> element may be preceded by an optional <gi>label</gi>:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <contents>
          <label>1</label><contentItem>Sonata in D major, op. V, no. 1 / Corelli</contentItem>
          <label>2</label><contentItem>Sonata in G minor / Purcell (with Robert Donington,
            gamba)</contentItem>
          <label>3</label><contentItem>Forlane from Concert royal no. 3 / Couperin</contentItem>
        </contents>
      </egXML>
      <p>To reference a contents list in an external location, use the <att>target</att>
        attribute:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
        <contents target="http://www.contentProvider.org/toc/toc01.html"/>
      </egXML>
      <p>To facilitate the creation of music catalogs based on MEI header information,
          <gi>contents</gi> may contain a heading:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <contents>
          <head>Contents of this Work:</head>
          <contentItem>Sonata No. 1</contentItem>
          <contentItem>Sonata No. 2 </contentItem>
          <contentItem>Sonata No. 3</contentItem>
        </contents>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="workRelatedItems" type="div3">
      <head>Related Items</head>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="revisionDescription" type="div2">
    <head>Revision Description</head>
    <p>The final sub-element of the MEI header, the <gi>revisionDesc</gi> element, provides a
      detailed change log in which each change made to a text may be recorded. Its use is optional
      but highly recommended. It provides essential information for the administration of large
      numbers of files which are being updated, corrected, or otherwise modified as well as
      extremely useful documentation for files being passed from researcher to researcher or system
      to system. Without change logs, it is easy to confuse different versions of a file, or to
      remain unaware of small but important changes made in the file by some earlier link in the
      chain of distribution. No change should be made in any MEI-conformant file without
      corresponding entries being made in the change log.</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="revisionDesc"/>
        <specDesc key="change"/>
      </specList>
      <gi>revisionDesc</gi> (revision description) summarizes the revision history for a file.</p>
    <p><gi>change</gi> summarizes a particular change or correction made to a particular version of
      an electronic text which is shared between several researchers.</p>
    <p>The main purpose of the revision description is to record changes in the text to which a
      header is prefixed. However, it is recommended practice to include entries also for
      significant changes in the header itself (other than the revision description itself, of
      course). At the very least, an entry should be supplied indicating the date of creation of the
      header.</p>
    <p>The log consists of a list of <gi>change</gi> elements, each of which contains a detailed
      description of the changes made. If a number is to be associated with one or more changes (for
      example, a revision number), the <att>n</att> attribute may be used to indicate it. The person
      responsible for the change and the date of the change must be indicated by the
        <gi>respStmt</gi> and <gi>date</gi> elements, respectively. The description of the change
      itself is contained within the <gi>changeDesc</gi> element, which can hold one or more
      paragraphs.</p>
    <p>It is recommended to give changes in reverse chronological order, most recent first.</p>
    <p>For example:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <revisionDesc>
        <change n="4">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>KR</persName>
          </respStmt>
          <changeDesc>
            <p>Cleaned up MEI file automatically using Header.xsl.</p>
          </changeDesc>
          <date reg="2011-12-01"/>
        </change>
        <change n="3">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>KR</persName>
          </respStmt>
          <changeDesc>
            <p>Cleaned up MEI file automatically using ppq.xsl.</p>
          </changeDesc>
          <date reg="2011-10-21"/>
        </change>
      </revisionDesc>
    </egXML>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="minimalRecommendedHeader" type="div2">
    <head>Minimal and Recommended Header Information</head>
    <p>The MEI header allows for the provision of a very large amount of information concerning the
      text itself, its source, its encodings, and revisions of it, as well as a wealth of
      descriptive information, such as the languages it uses and the situation(s) in which it was
      produced, together with the setting and identity of participants within it. This diversity and
      richness reflects the diversity of uses to which it is envisaged that electronic texts
      conforming to these Guidelines will be put. It is emphatically not intended that all of the
      elements described above should be present in every MEI Header.</p>
    <p>The amount of encoding in a header will depend both on the nature and the intended use of the
      text. At one extreme, an encoder may expect that the header will be needed only to provide a
      bibliographic identification of the text adequate to local needs. At the other, wishing to
      ensure that their texts can be used for the widest range of applications, encoders will want
      to document as explicitly as possible both bibliographic and descriptive information, in such
      a way that no prior or ancillary knowledge about the text is needed in order to process it.
      The header in such a case will be very full, approximating the kind of documentation often
      supplied in the form of a manual. Most texts will lie somewhere between these extremes;
      textual corpora in particular will tend more to the latter extreme. In the remainder of this
      section we demonstrate first the minimal, and then a commonly recommended, level of encoding
      for the bibliographic information held by the MEI header.</p>
    <p>Supplying only the level of encoding required, the MEI header of a single text will look like
      the following example:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <meiHead>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Fughette (in Gottes Namen Fahren wir - Dies sind die heil'gen zehn Gebote) for
              Brass Quintett : an electronic transcription</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <pubStmt>
            <respStmt>
              <corpName dbkey="5115204-6" authURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd" authority="GND"
                >Musikwissenschaftliches Seminar &lt;Detmold&gt;</corpName>
            </respStmt>
          </pubStmt>
        </fileDesc>
      </meiHead>
    </egXML>
    <p>The only mandatory component of the MEI Header is the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element. Within this
      element, <gi>titleStmt</gi> and <gi>pubStmt</gi> are required constituents. Within the title
      statement, a title is required. Within the <gi>pubStmt</gi>, a publisher, distributor, or
      other agency responsible for the file is required.</p>
    <p>While not formally required, additional information is recommended even for a minimally
      effective header. For example, it is recommended that the person or corporate entity
      responsible for the creation of the encoding should be specified using <gi>respStmt</gi>
      within the <gi>titleStmt</gi> element. It is also recommended that information about the
      source, or sources, of the encoding be included. Each <gi>source</gi> element should contain
      at the least a loosely structured bibliographic citation that identifies the source used to
      construct the MEI file.</p>
    <p>Furthermore, If the electronic transcription is a member of a series of publications, the
      series title and publisher should be included using the <gi>seriesStmt</gi> element. It is
      also common for cataloging records to include genre and/or form information, here represented
      by the MEI <gi>classification</gi> element.</p>
    <p>We now present the same example header, expanded to include additionally recommended
      information, adequate for most bibliographic purposes, in particular to allow for the creation
      of an AACR2-conformant bibliographic record.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <meiHead>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Fughette (in Gottes Namen Fahren wir - Dies sind die heil'gen zehn Gebote) for
              Brass Quintett : an electronic transcription</title>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Encoded by:</resp>
              <persName xml:id="MH">Maja Hartwig</persName>
              <persName xml:id="KR">Kristina Richts</persName>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <pubStmt>
            <respStmt>
              <corpName>Musikwissenschaftliches Seminar &lt;Detmold&gt;</corpName>
            </respStmt>
            <date>2011</date>
          </pubStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>MEI Sample Collection</title>
            <respStmt>
              <corpName role="publisher">MEI Project</corpName>
            </respStmt>
          </seriesStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
            <source>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>Fughette (in Gottes Namen Fahren wir - Dies sind die heil'gen zehn Gebote)
                  for Brass Quintett</title>
                <respStmt>
                  <persName role="composer">Johann Christoph Bach</persName>
                  <persName role="arranger">Michel Rondeau</persName>
                </respStmt>
              </titleStmt>
              <pubStmt>
                <identifier type="URI"
                  >http://icking-music-archive.org/scores/j.chr.bach/JCBIN-xml.zip</identifier>
                <date reg="2011-10-13"/>
                <respStmt>
                  <name>Werner Icking Music Archive</name>
                </respStmt>
                <availability>
                  <useRestrict>© 2010 - Gatineau,Qc.Ca.</useRestrict>
                </availability>
              </pubStmt>
              <classification>
                <classCode xml:id="OCLC_DDC" authority="OCLC"
                  authURI="http://www.oclc.org/dewey/resources/summaries/default.htm#700"/>
                <termList>
                  <term classcode="#OCLC_DDC">785.15</term>
                </termList>
              </classification>
            </source>
          </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
      </meiHead>
    </egXML>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="independentHeader" type="div2">
    <head>Independent Headers</head>
    <p>Many libraries, repositories, research sites and related institutions collect bibliographic
      and documentary information about machine readable music documents without necessarily
      collecting the music documents themselves. Such institutions may thus want access to the
      header of an MEI document without its attached text in order to build catalogs, indexes and
      databases that can be used to locate relevant texts at remote locations, obtain full
      documentation about those texts, and learn how to obtain them. This section describes a set of
      practices by which the metadata headers of MEI documents can be encoded separately from those
      documents and exchanged as freestanding MEI documents. Headers exchanged independently of the
      documents they describe are called independent headers.</p>
    <div xml:id="independentHeaderDefinition" type="div3">
      <head>Definition and Principles for Encoders</head>
      <p>An independent header is a MEI metadata header that can be exchanged as an independent
        document between libraries, archives, collections, projects, and individuals.</p>
      <p>The structure of an independent header is exactly the same as that of an header attached to
        a document. This means that an <gi>meiHead</gi> can be extracted from an MEI document and
        sent to a receiving institution with little or no change.
        <!--However, some fields that are
        listed as ‘optional’ in the header are listed as ‘recommended’ for the independent header.
        For this reason, this section should be consulted in connection with any plan to provide
        headers as independent documents.--></p>
      <p>When deciding which information to include in the independent header, and the format or
        structure of that information, the following should be kept in mind: <list type="bulleted">
          <item>The independent header should provide full bibliographic information about the
            encoded text, its source, where the text can be located, and any restrictions governing
            its use.</item>
          <item>The independent header should contain useful information about the encoding of the
            text itself. In this regard, it is highly recommended that the encoding description be
            as complete as possible. The Guidelines do not require that the encoding description be
            included in the header (since some simple transcriptions of small items may not require
            it), but in practice the use of a header without an encoding description would be
            severely limited.</item>
          <item>The independent header should be amenable to automatic processing, particularly for
            loading into databases and for the creation of publications, indexes, and finding aids,
            without undue editorial intervention on the part of the receiving institution. For this
            reason, two recommendations are made regarding the format or structure of the header:
            first, where there is a choice between a prose content model and one that contains a
            formal series of specialized elements, wherever possible and appropriate the specialized
            elements should be preferred to unstructured prose. Second, with respect to corpora,
            information about each of the texts within a corpus should be included in the overall
            corpus-level <gi>meiHead</gi>. That is, source information, editorial practices,
            encoding descriptions, and the like should be included in the relevant sections of the
            corpus <gi>meiHead</gi>, with pointers to them from the headers of the individual texts
            included in the corpus. There are three reasons for this recommendation: first, the
            corpus-level header will contain the full array of bibliographic and documentary
            information for each of the texts in a corpus, and thus be of great benefit to remote
            users, who may have access only to the independent header; second, such a layout is
            easier for the coder to maintain than searching for information throughout a text; and
            third, generally speaking, this practice results in greater overall consistency,
            especially with respect to bibliographic citations.</item>
        </list>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="biblAnalog" type="div3">
      <head>Header Elements and their Relationship to Other Bibliographic Standards</head>
      <p>Mapping elements from the MEI metadata header to another descriptive system may help a
        repository harvest selected data from the MEI file to build a basic catalog record. For this
        purpose, the following attribute is provided on most meiHead elements:</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="att.bibl" atts="analog"/>
      </p>
      <p>The encoding system to which fields are mapped must be specified in <att>analog.</att> When
        possible, subfields as well as fields should be specified, e.g., subfields within MARC
        fields.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <!-- NEED EXAMPLE HERE! -->
      </egXML>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="headerOverview" type="div2">
    <head>Overview of the MEI Header Module</head>
    <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:</p>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="headerElements">
      <head>Elements</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="accessRestrict"/>
          <specDesc key="acqSource"/>
          <specDesc key="altId"/>
          <specDesc key="appInfo"/>
          <specDesc key="application"/>
          <specDesc key="availability"/>
          <specDesc key="change"/>
          <specDesc key="changeDesc"/>
          <specDesc key="classCode"/>
          <specDesc key="classification"/>
          <specDesc key="condition"/>
          <specDesc key="contentItem"/>
          <specDesc key="contents"/>
          <specDesc key="correction"/>
          <specDesc key="creation"/>
          <specDesc key="dimensions"/>
          <specDesc key="editionStmt"/>
          <specDesc key="editorialDecl"/>
          <specDesc key="encodingDesc"/>
          <specDesc key="ensemble"/>
          <specDesc key="event"/>
          <specDesc key="eventList"/>
          <specDesc key="exhibHist"/>
          <specDesc key="extent"/>
          <specDesc key="fileDesc"/>
          <specDesc key="fingerprint"/>
          <specDesc key="hand"/>
          <specDesc key="handList"/>
          <specDesc key="history"/>
          <specDesc key="incipCode"/>
          <specDesc key="incipText"/>
          <specDesc key="inscription"/>
          <specDesc key="instrVoice"/>
          <specDesc key="interpretation"/>
          <specDesc key="key"/>
          <specDesc key="language"/>
          <specDesc key="langUsage"/>
          <specDesc key="meiHead"/>
          <specDesc key="meter"/>
          <specDesc key="normalization"/>
          <specDesc key="notesStmt"/>
          <specDesc key="perfMedium"/>
          <specDesc key="performer"/>
          <specDesc key="physDesc"/>
          <specDesc key="physLoc"/>
          <specDesc key="physMedium"/>
          <specDesc key="plateNum"/>
          <specDesc key="price"/>
          <specDesc key="projectDesc"/>
          <specDesc key="provenance"/>
          <specDesc key="pubStmt"/>
          <specDesc key="relatedItem"/>
          <specDesc key="resp"/>
          <specDesc key="respStmt"/>
          <specDesc key="revisionDesc"/>
          <specDesc key="samplingDecl"/>
          <specDesc key="segmentation"/>
          <specDesc key="seriesStmt"/>
          <specDesc key="source"/>
          <specDesc key="sourceDesc"/>
          <specDesc key="stdVals"/>
          <specDesc key="sysReq"/>
          <specDesc key="term"/>
          <specDesc key="termList"/>
          <specDesc key="titleStmt"/>
          <specDesc key="treatHist"/>
          <specDesc key="treatSched"/>
          <specDesc key="unpub"/>
          <specDesc key="useRestrict"/>
          <specDesc key="watermark"/>
          <specDesc key="work"/>
          <specDesc key="workDesc"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="headerAttrClasses">
      <head>Attribute Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="att.regularmethod"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="headerModelClasses">
      <head>Model Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="model.editorialDeclPart"/>
          <specDesc key="model.encodingPart"/>
          <specDesc key="model.frontPart"/>
          <specDesc key="model.headerPart"/>
          <specDesc key="model.physDescPart"/>
          <specDesc key="model.pubStmtPart"/>
          <specDesc key="model.startLike.header"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
