<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
  © 2012 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
  not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License
  at http://www.osedu.org/licenses/ECL-2.0.
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
  OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language
  governing permissions and limitations under the License.
  
  This is a derivative work based on earlier versions of the schema © 2001-2006 Perry Roland
  and the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia; licensed under the Educational
  Community License version 1.0.
  
  CONTACT: info@music-encoding.org
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="lyricsDesc" n="0">
  <head>Vocal Text</head>
  <p>This chapter describes how to encode words and syllables in vocal notation. This text is
    typically written under a staff to indicate the text to be vocally performed. As such, this text
    should not be confused with other text on the score, for which see <ptr
      target="#textualElements"/> and <ptr target="#text"/>
  </p>
  <p>These guidelines suggest two methods for encoding text in vocal notation: encoding syllables
      <ref target="#lyricsInEvents">under each note</ref> and encoding performed text <ref
      target="#lyricsAfterEvents">after the notes</ref> (and other staff events) either within
      <gi>layer</gi> elements or within <gi>measure</gi> elements when available (for example in a
    Common Music Notation context). Each method may be more convenient depending on the source text
    and on the textual phenomena that the encoding intends to record.</p>
  <!-- TODO: Check if <syl> belongs here or in the shared chapter (#lyricSyllables). Writing here for now! -->
  <p>Both methods eventually rely on the <gi>syl</gi> element, which is part of the
      <soCalled>shared</soCalled> module and is therefore available in all MEI files. The following
    sections will begin by introducing the general use of <gi>syl</gi> and then show in detail the
    two different encoding methods.</p>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="lyricsSyl">
    <head>Lyric Syllables</head>
    <p>By <soCalled>lyric syllable</soCalled>, these guidelines mean a word or portion of a word
      that is to be performed vocally. Each syllable is encoded with the <gi>syl</gi> element, with
      which it is also possible to specify the position of the syllable in a word, the type of
      connectors between syllables, alignment adjustments, and the formatting for each syllable.
      These are the key components:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="syl" atts="worpos con halign"/>
      </specList>
    </p>

    <p>The attribute <att>wordpos</att> is used to specify the position of the marked-up lyric
      syllable in a word. It allows the following values:</p>
    <list type="simple">
      <item><label>i</label> Indicates that the current syllable's position is <emph>i</emph>nitial;
        that is, at the beginning of a word;</item>
      <item><label>m</label> Indicates that the current syllable is in the <emph>m</emph>iddle of a
        word;</item>
      <item><label>t</label> Indicates that the syllable's position is <emph>t</emph>erminal; that
        is, at the end of a word.</item>
      <!-- TODO: Need a value to indicate the syllable is the entire word? -->
    </list>

    <p>When a syllable is at the beginning or in the middle of a word (in which case it will have
      the <att>wordpos</att> attribute set to <soCalled>i</soCalled> or <soCalled>m</soCalled>), it
      is recommended to specify the type of connector written between the current and the following
      syllable. This is expressed with the <att>con</att> attribute, which takes the following
      values:</p>
    <list type="simple">
      <item><label>s</label> A <emph>s</emph>pace is used as connector between syllables;</item>
      <item><label>d</label> A <emph>d</emph>ash is used as connector between syllables;</item>
      <item><label>u</label> An <emph>u</emph>nderscore sign (indicating prologation of the
        syllable) is used as connector between syllables;</item>
      <item><label>t</label> A <emph>t</emph>ilde is used to indicate elision with the following
        syllable. This is typically rendered as a small curved line between the syllables.</item>
    </list>

    <p>Occasionally, a word or a final syllable needs to be extended across multiple notes. In this
      case an <soCalled>extender</soCalled> is provided. An extender is a continuous line drawn at
      the text's baseline from the end of the syllable associated with the first note until the last
      note to be sung with the syllable. The </p>

    <p>The use of <gi>syl</gi> described in this section is common to CMN and other notation
      systems, such as mensural notation. Other uses specific to certain types of notation and
      repertoires are addressed in other chapters. See for example <ptr target="neumes1.2"/>.</p>
  </div>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="lyricsInEvents">
    <head>Vocally Performed Text Encoded Within Notes</head>
    <p>Each lyric syllable can be encoded directly within an associated note, either by using the
        <att>syl</att> attribute on <gi>note</gi> or the <gi>verse</gi> element.</p>
    <p>Using the <att>syl</att> attribute on notes is the simplest way of encoding vocally performed
      text and is recommended only for simple situations or for those encodings which do not focus
      on vocally performed text.</p>
    <p>The following example from Handel's <title>Messiah</title> (HWV 56) shows the use of
        <att>syl</att>:</p>
    <figure>
      <head>Handel, Messiah HWV 56, Halleluja</head>
      <figDesc>Example of a simple encoding of sung text</figDesc>
      <graphic url="Images/modules/lyrics/ex_syl_att.png" height="100px"/>
    </figure>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <measure>
        <staff>
          <layer>
            <note pname="c" oct="5" dur="4" dots="1" syl="Hal-"/>
            <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="8" syl="le-"/>
            <beam>
              <note pname="a" oct="4" dur="8" syl="lu-"/>
              <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="8" syl="jah,"/>
            </beam>
            <rest dur="4"/>
          </layer>
        </staff>
      </measure>
    </egXML>

    <p>When there are multiple lines of vocally performed text, or the encoder wishes to be more
      specific about connectors, etc., the use of <gi>verse</gi> and <gi>syl</gi> is
      recommended.</p>

    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="verse" atts="rhythm"/>
      </specList>
    </p>

    <p>The following example from Handel's <title>Messiah</title> (HWV 56) shows the use of
        <gi>verse</gi>:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <measure>
        <staff>
          <layer>
            <note pname="c" oct="5" dur="4" dots="1">
              <verse n="1">
                <syl wordpos="i" con="d">Hal</syl>
              </verse>
            </note>
            <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="8">
              <verse n="1">
                <syl wordpos="m" con="d">le</syl>
              </verse>
            </note>
            <beam>
              <note pname="a" oct="4" dur="8">
                <verse n="1">
                  <syl wordpos="m" con="d">lu</syl>
                </verse>
              </note>
              <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="8">
                <verse n="1">
                  <syl wordpos="t">jah,</syl>
                </verse>
              </note>
            </beam>
            <rest dur="4"/>
          </layer>
        </staff>
      </measure>
    </egXML>

    <p>As it is common practice in written text, it is assumed that a space separates words. Many
      vocal texts, however, introduce elisions and connect two syllables into one unit. For example,
      the vocal text from Mozart's <title>Don Giovanni</title> sung by Don Giovanni in Finale II,
        <q>Ho fermo il core in petto</q> introduces an elision between the word <q>fermo</q> and
        <q>il</q> and between <q>core</q> and <q>in</q>. An elision can be indicated by placing both
      syllables within the same <gi>note</gi> and setting the <gi>syl</gi> element's <att>con</att>
      attribute value to 't':</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <note>
        <verse>
          <syl wordpos="t" con="t">re</syl>
          <syl wordpos="i">in</syl>
        </verse>
      </note>
    </egXML>

    <p>When there is more than one line of text, more than one <gi>verse</gi> element can be used.
      The following example from a piano reduction of Wagner's <title>Rheingold</title> has two
      lines of text, with an English translation on the second line. Note the use of the
        <att>xml:lang</att> attribute to differentiate the two languages:</p>
    <figure>
      <head>Example from Wagner's Rheingold with translated text.</head>
      <!--<graphic url="Images/modules/lyrics/ex_syl_att.png" width="100px"/>-->
    </figure>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <scoreDef>
        <staffGrp>
          <staffDef n="1" lines="5" clef.line="4" clef.shape="F" key.sig="4s"/>
        </staffGrp>
      </scoreDef>
      <section>
        <measure>
          <staff n="1">
            <layer n="1">
              <note pname="f" oct="3" dur="2" stem.dir="down">
                <verse n="1" xml:lang="ger">
                  <syl wordpos="i" con="d">Rei</syl>
                </verse>
                <verse n="2" xml:lang="eng">
                  <syl>thinks</syl>
                </verse>
              </note>
              <note pname="f" oct="3" dur="8" stem.dir="down">
                <verse n="1">
                  <syl wordpos="t">fes</syl>
                </verse>
                <verse n="2">
                  <syl>it</syl>
                </verse>
              </note>
              <note pname="f" oct="3" dur="8" stem.dir="down">
                <verse n="1">
                  <syl>zu</syl>
                </verse>
                <verse n="2">
                  <syl>were</syl>
                </verse>
              </note>
            </layer>
          </staff>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <staff n="1">
            <layer>
              <note pname="b" oct="3" dur="4" stem.dir="down">
                <verse n="1">
                  <syl wordpos="i" con="d">wal</syl>
                </verse>
                <verse n="2">
                  <syl>wise</syl>
                </verse>
              </note>
              <note pname="d" oct="3" dur="4" stem.dir="down">
                <accid accid="n"/>
                <verse n="1">
                  <syl wordpos="t">ten,</syl>
                </verse>
                <verse n="2">
                  <syl>now</syl>
                </verse>
              </note>
              <rest dur="4" dur.ges="8p"/>
            </layer>
          </staff>
        </measure>
      </section>
    </egXML>

    <p>Optionally, it is possible to include an <gi>lb</gi> element within <gi>verse</gi> to
      explicitly encode line and line group endings. This is specifically meant to facilitate
      karaoke applications.</p>

    <p>Finally, the <att>rhythm</att> attribute can be used to specify a rhythm for the syllable
      that differs from that of the notes on the staff.</p>
    <!-- TODO: NEED EXAMPLE HERE -->

  </div>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="lyricsAfterEvents">
    <head>Vocally Performed Text Encoded Separately</head>
    <p>Vocally performed text may also be encoded separately from the notes with the <gi>lyrics</gi>
      element. These are the main components:</p>

    <p><specList>
        <specDesc key="lyrics" atts="staff layer"/>
      </specList></p>

    <p>Since this element is separated from the encoding of the notes, it must be associated with a
      staff that will provide rhythm information when required for automated processing. The
        <att>staff</att> attribute gives the associated staff and if there is more than one layer on
      that staff, the <att>layer</att> attribute may be used to indicate the layer from which the
      rhythm should be taken. If there is any divergence between the rhythm of the vocally performed
      text and the notes, the <att>rhythm</att> attribute on <gi>verse</gi> may be used to specify
      the text's rhythm.</p>

    <p>The following example from Carl Maria von Weber's <title>Der Freischütz</title> illustrates
      this encoding method:</p>
    <figure>
      <head>Weber, Der Freischütz</head>
      <figDesc>Example of separate vocally performed text encoding</figDesc>
      <!--<graphic url="Images/modules/lyrics/ex_syl_att.png" width="100px"/>-->
    </figure>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <measure>
        <staff n="1">
          <layer n="1">
            <note pname="a" dur="4" oct="3" dots="1">
              <artic artic="acc"/>
            </note>
            <note pname="a" dur="4" oct="3" dots="1">
              <artic artic="acc"/>
            </note>
          </layer>
        </staff>
        <lyrics staff="1">
          <verse>
            <syl>Sturm</syl>
            <syl>und</syl>
          </verse>
        </lyrics>
      </measure>
      <measure>
        <staff n="1">
          <layer n="1">
            <note pname="g" dur="2" oct="3" dots="1" tie="i"/>
          </layer>
        </staff>
        <lyrics staff="1">
          <verse>
            <syl>Nacht!</syl>
          </verse>
        </lyrics>
      </measure>
      <measure>
        <staff n="1">
          <layer n="1">
            <note pname="g" dur="2" oct="3" dots="1" tie="t"/>
          </layer>
        </staff>
      </measure>
    </egXML>

    <p>In this encoding style, a <gi>syl</gi> element with its <att>con</att> attribute set to 't'
      and the following syllable are presumed to be associated with a single note. In the following
      example, the first two syllables occur on the first note and the third syllable occurs on the
      second note.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <staff>
        <layer>
          <note pname="g" dur="2" oct="3"/>
          <note pname="f" dur="2" oct="3"/>
        </layer>
      </staff>
      <!-- later -->
      <lyrics staff="1">
        <verse>
          <syl wordpos="t" con="t">re</syl>
          <syl wordpos="i">il</syl>
          <syl wordpos="i">pet</syl>
        </verse>
      </lyrics>
    </egXML>

  </div>

</div>
