<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!-- 
  © 2015 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI).
  Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
  not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License
  at http://opensource.org/licenses/ECL-2.0.
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
  OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language
  governing permissions and limitations under the License.
  
  This is a derivative work based on earlier versions of the schema © 2001-2006 Perry Roland
  and the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia; licensed under the Educational
  Community License version 1.0.
  
  CONTACT: info@music-encoding.org
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="mensural" n="0">
  <head>Mensural Notation</head>
  <p>This chapter describes the module for encoding mensural notation from the late 13th century to
    about 1600. Historically, mensural notation preceded the development of Common Music Notation
    (CMN) and it included a wide range of features that persist in CMN and that can be encoded in a
    standard manner in MEI. In mensural notation, pitches are notated as in CMN, leaving out here
    the major exception of <emph>musica ficta</emph>. The pitch is given by the position of the note
    on the staff and the current clef as in CMN, and the mensural module introduces no modification
    to MEI regarding how pitches are encoded.</p>
  <p>There are a certain number of differences, however, regarding the representation of duration in
    mensural notation. The mensural module introduces specific attribute values for notes and rests
    for appropriately encoding mensural durations. One of the main particularities is that the
    actual duration of a note is not given only by its symbol but also by position and the context
    in which the symbol appears. The general context is given by one of the 16 mensural
      <emph>species</emph> provide four levels of division: <emph>modus major</emph>, <emph>modus
      minor</emph>, <emph>tempus</emph> and <emph>prolatio</emph>. Depending on the context, certain
    rules must be applied in order to determine the duration of a note. In these cases, encoding
    both the sign and its actual duration is highy desirable.</p>
  <p>Another particularity of mensural notation is the use of proportions that are indicated by
    numeric proportions or by specific mensuration signs. The proportions indicate that the
    durations have to be modified accordingly and they can be combined in a very complex manner.
    Over time, proportions and mensuration signs were simplified and became time signatures in CMN.
    The attributes and elements that are necessary for encoding proportions and mensural signs are
    made available by the module.</p>
  <p>In mensural notation, notes can also be notated in ligatures that regroup two or more notes.
    Ligatures were a legacy from an earlier notation system that were still widely used in
    Renaissance music notation. They gradually disappeared during the seventeenth century. The
    mensural module provides multiple ways of encoding the ligatures.</p>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="mensuralNotes">
    <head>Note and Rest Values</head>
    <p>When the mensural module is included, <att>dur</att> on <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi>, <gi
        scheme="MEI">rest</gi>, and other elements can take the following values:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>maxima</item>
      <item>longa</item>
      <item>brevis</item>
      <item>semibrevis</item>
      <item>minima</item>
      <item>semiminima</item>
      <item>fusa</item>
      <item>semifusa</item>
    </list>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="mensuralRules">
      <head>Actual Duration with Alterations and Imperfections</head>
      <p>In ternary divisions, the dichotomy between the duration sign of the notes and their actual
        duration requires specific attention. The rules of mensural notation can require the
        alteration or the imperfection of a note; that is, an increase or reduction in its performed
        duration. In these cases, if the encoding is intended to be suitable for more than just
        graphically representing the notation, encoding only the duration of the sign can quickly
        become insufficient. It that case, it is recommended to encode the sign in the
          <att>dur</att> attribute and its performed duration using the <att>num</att> and
          <att>numbase</att> attributes.</p>
      <p>The following example illustrates an alteration (the second <emph>brevis</emph>) in
          <emph>modus minor perfectus</emph> and <emph>tempus imperfectum</emph>. The performed
        duration of each note is given as a proportion of a whole note using the <att>num</att> and
          <att>numbase</att>:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<note dur="longa" num="6" numbase="1"/>
<note dur="brevis" num="2" numbase="1"/>
<note dur="brevis" num="4" numbase="1"/>
<note dur="longa" num="6" numbase="1"/>
      </egXML>
      <p>The following example illustrates an imperfection (the two <emph>longae</emph>) in
          <emph>modus minor perfectus</emph> and <emph>tempus perfectum</emph> with the same
          <emph>longa</emph>-<emph>brevis</emph>-<emph>brevis</emph>-<emph>longa</emph> sequence but
        with an additional <emph>punctus divisionis</emph> between the two <emph>breves</emph>:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<note dur="longa" num="6" numbase="1"/>
<note dur="brevis" num="3" numbase="1"/>
<dot form="div"/>
<note dur="brevis" num="3" numbase="1"/>
<note dur="longa" num="6" numbase="1"/>
      </egXML>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="mensuralSigns">
    <head>Mensuration Signs</head>
    <p>Using the mensural module, mensuration signs can be indicated with the attributes available
      on the <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> elements. Mensuration
      signs encoded using attributes on <gi scheme="MEI">scoreDef</gi> are regarded as default
      values which may be overridden by values attached to individual <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi>
      elements.</p>
    <p>The division levels corresponding to <emph>modus maior</emph>, <emph>modus minor</emph>,
        <emph>tempus</emph> and <emph>prolatio</emph> can be encoded in the <att>modusmaior</att>,
        <att>modusminor</att>, <att>tempus</att> and <att>prolatio</att> attributes respectively.
      Their value must be 3 (perfect) or 2 (imperfect).</p>
    <!-- TODO: add a couple of example of signs -->
    <p>The mensur signs themselves can be encoded in the <att>sign</att> attribute with a possible
      value of "C" or "O". Its orientation can be encoded in the <att>orient</att> attribute, for
      example, with the value "reversed" for a flipped C sign. The number of slahes (up to 6) can be
      given in the <att>slash</att> attribute. There is also a <att>dot</att> attribute for
      indicating the presence of a dot.</p>
    <!-- TODO:  example -->
    <p>
      <gi scheme="MEI">mensur</gi> elements can also be used instead of <gi scheme="MEI"
        >staffDef</gi> and its attributes.</p>
    <!-- TODO:  example -->
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="mensuralProportions">
    <head>Proportions</head>
    <p>Proportions can also be indicated within the <gi scheme="MEI">staffDef</gi> element. The
        <att>num</att> and <att>numbase</att> attributes are available for encoding the numerator
      and the denominator of the proportion respectively. There is also a <gi scheme="MEI"
        >proport</gi> element that can be used as an alternative.</p>
    <!-- TODO:  example -->
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="mensuralLigatures">
    <head>Ligatures</head>
    <p>Ligatures can be encoded using the <gi scheme="MEI">ligature</gi> element. The
        <att>form</att> attribute is available for specifying if the ligature is recta or
      obliqua.</p>
    <figure>
      <head>Recta and obliqua ligatures</head>
      <graphic url="Images/modules/mensural/ex_ligatures01.png"/>
    </figure>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<ligature form="recta">
  <note pname="d" oct="4" dur="semibrevis"/>
  <note pname="g" oct="3" dur="semibrevis"/>
</ligature>
<ligature form="obliqua">
  <note pname="g" oct="3" dur="semibrevis"/>
  <note pname="c" oct="4" dur="semibrevis"/>
</ligature>
    </egXML>
    <p>In cases where the ligature contains both recta and obliqua notes, the <att>lig</att>
      attribute of the <gi scheme="MEI">note</gi> element can be used to specify the form of the
      ligature at the note level.</p>
    <figure>
      <head>Ligature with more than two notes with recta and obliqua</head>
      <graphic url="Images/modules/mensural/ex_ligatures02.png"/>
    </figure>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<ligature form="recta" xmlns="http://www.music-encoding.org/ns/mei">
  <note pname="a" oct="3" dur="longa"/>
  <note pname="e" oct="4" dur="longa"/>
  <note pname="d" oct="4" lig="obliqua" dur="semibrevis"/>
  <note pname="c" oct="4" lig="obliqua" dur="semibrevis"/>
  <note pname="b" oct="3" dur="brevis"/>
  <note pname="e" oct="4" dur="brevis"/>
</ligature>
    </egXML>
    <p/>
  </div>
  <!-- 
    This is not specific to the module, but I think it is important to have it somewhere
  -->
  <div type="div2" xml:id="mensuralData">
    <head>Music Data Organization</head>
    <p>The data organization based on <gi scheme="MEI">measure</gi> elements that usually prevails
      in MEI is not appropriate for mensural notation because most music until 1600 was written in a
      non-measured manner. Even though it is not defined by the mensural module, a more suitable
      alternate data organization without measures is available: <gi scheme="MEI">staff</gi>
      elements may occur directly within the <gi scheme="MEI">section</gi> element without being
      organized into measures first. The organization of events (notes, rests, etc.) within the <gi
        scheme="MEI">staff</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">layer</gi> elements remains unchanged.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<section xmlns="http://www.music-encoding.org/ns/mei">
  <staff n="1">
    <layer>
      <note pname="c" oct="5" dur="longa"/>
      <note pname="g" oct="4" dur="brevis"/>
      <note pname="e" oct="4" dur="brevis"/>
    </layer>
  </staff>
  <staff n="2">
    <layer>
      <note pname="c" oct="3" dur="maxima"/>
    </layer>
  </staff>
</section>
    </egXML>
    <p>This feature may also be used to encode measured music without using the <gi scheme="MEI"
        >measure</gi> element. That is, the same data organization described above may be used, but
      with the addition of barlines, indicated by the <gi scheme="MEI">barLine</gi> element, for
      those situations where a measure-by-measure organization is not appropriate, for exampe, when
      measures are not coincident in all the staves of a score.</p>
    <!-- TODO: an example.  Mozart perhaps? -->
  </div>
  <!-- 
    I don't know if this is relevant here. Maybe this is more of a tutorial, 
    but I thought it might be useful to have information about it. My plan is 
    to write a short text and link them to the guidelines of the shared module
  -->
  <!-- Yes, by all means! PR -->
  <div type="div2" xml:id="mensuralOther">
    <head>Elements and Attributes from Other Modules</head>
    <p/>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="mensuralAccid">
      <head>Accidentals</head>
      <p>[explain that accidentals are usually encoded as independant elements and that accid.ges
        can be used within notes]</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="mensuralColoration">
      <head>Coloration</head>
      <p>[explain where/how coloration can be encoded]</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="mensuralCustos">
      <head>Custos</head>
      <p>[explain that there is a custos element available]</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="mensuralDot">
      <head>Dot</head>
      <p>[explain that dots are independant elements in mensural music and that @dot of notes should
        not be used]</p>
    </div>
  </div>
  <!--<div type="div2" xml:id="mensuralOverview">
    <!-\- Overview -\->
    <head>Overview of the Mensural Module</head>
    <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:</p>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="mensuralElements">
      <head>Elements</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="ligature"/>
          <specDesc key="mensur"/>
          <specDesc key="proport"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="mensuralAttributeClasses">
      <head>Attribute Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="att.ligature.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.ligature.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.ligature.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.ligature.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mensur.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mensur.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mensur.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mensur.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mensuration.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.mensuration.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.note.ges.mensural"/>
          <specDesc key="att.note.log.mensural"/>
          <specDesc key="att.proport.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.proport.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.proport.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.proport.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.rest.ges.mensural"/>
          <specDesc key="att.rest.vis.mensural"/>
          <specDesc key="att.scoreDef.log.mensural"/>
          <specDesc key="att.scoreDef.vis.mensural"/>
          <specDesc key="att.staffDef.log.mensural"/>
          <specDesc key="att.staffDef.vis.mensural"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="mensuralModelClasses">
      <head>Model Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="model.eventLike.mensural"/>
          <specDesc key="model.layerPart.mensural"/>
          <specDesc key="model.staffDefPart.mensural"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
  </div>-->
</div>
