<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  © 2010 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs Unported License, 
  Version 3.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/.
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="namesDates" n="0">
  <head>Names and Dates</head>
  <p>This chapter describes a module which may be used for the encoding of names (names of persons
    or corporations/organizations) or descriptive phrases for styles, periods or geographical
    indications. In section xy Names, Numbers, Dates, Abbreviations, and Addresses it was noted that
    the elements provided in the core module allow an encoder to specify that a given text segment
    is a proper noun. <!--ToDo: synchronisation with section Names, Numbers etc. !--> The elements
    provided by the present module allow the encoder to supply a detailed sub-structure for such
    proper nouns, and to distinguish explicitly between persons and organizations, and between
    stylistic, periodical or geographical indications.</p>
  <p>The chapter begins by discussing the elements provided for the encoding of names
    (<gi>name</gi>) and dates (<gi>date</gi>) in general, up to more specifical elements like
    corporate names (<gi>corpName</gi>), geographical names (<gi>geogName</gi>), period names
      (<gi>periodName</gi>), personal names (<gi>persName</gi>) and style names
    (<gi>styleName</gi>). In general it is recommended to use standardised spelling forms of proper
    nouns conforming to standards and to record the names and web-accessible locations of used
    controlled vocabularies. Especially for geographical, organizational and personal names there
    are several authority files, such as the Gemeinsame Normdatei (GND), the Library of Congress
    Authorities, the Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names (TGN) or the MARC code list for relators.
    Recommendations on which standards could be used can be found in the descriptions of the
    individual elements.
    <!-- Generell: Vielleicht an den Stellen, wo eines der nachfolgenden Elemente in vielen Elementen erlaubt ist,
    auf die model.Klasse verweisen, in Form von: These elements are all members of the model.placeNamePart etc.,
    wird in TEI ebenfalls so gehandhabt.--><!-- #MH: finde ich gut! -->
  </p>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="namesdatesOverview">
    <head>Overview of the namesDates module</head>
    <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:</p>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="namesdatesElements">
      <head>Elements</head>
      <p>Basic Elements and Data Structures of the namesDates module are:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="name"/>
          <specDesc key="date"/>
          <specDesc key="corpName"/>
          <specDesc key="geogName"/>
          <specDesc key="persName"/>
          <specDesc key="periodName"/>
          <specDesc key="styleName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="name">
      <head>name</head>
      <p>The <gi>name</gi> element contains the name of an entity that is difficult to tag more
        specifically as a <gi>corpName</gi>, <gi>geogName</gi>, <gi>persName</gi>, or
        <gi>title</gi>. In section xy Names, Numbers, Dates, Abbreviations, and Addresses
        <!--ToDo: link to chapter shared--> it was noted that the <gi>name</gi> element may be used
        in place of the more specific elements when it is not known what kind of name is being
        described or when a high degree of precision is not necessary. For example, the
          <gi>name</gi> element might be used when it is not clear whether the name "Bach" refers to
        a person or a geographic feature. When name parts are needed, use <gi>name</gi>
        sub-elements. The recommended values for the <att>type</att> attribute are: pers, corp,
        place, process. The date sub-element is available within <gi>name</gi> in order to record
        any dates, associated with the name, i.e. creation and dissolution in the case of a
        corporate entity or place. The name of the list from which a controlled value is taken, such
        as the Library of Congress Name Authority File (LCNAF), may be recorded using the authority
        attribute.</p>
      <p>Examples for the use of the <gi>name</gi> element are: <list>
          <item>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <name type="pers">Henry VIII, King of England</name>
            </egXML>
          </item>
          <item>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <name type="corp">The Beatles</name>
            </egXML>
          </item>
          <item>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <name type="place">Bach</name>
            </egXML>
          </item>
          <item>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <name type="process"/>
              <!--ToDo: Fill in example-->
            </egXML>
          </item>
        </list>
      </p>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="date">
      <head>date</head>
      <p>The element <gi>date</gi> contains a date in any format, including a date range, which may
        be expressed either as textual content, e.g., <date>March 1-21, 1812</date>, or using date
        sub-elements, possibly combined with text, e.g., <date><date>March 1, 1812</date> -
            <date>March 21, 1812</date></date>. The latter form is useful when the starting and
        ending points of the date range require qualification. The <gi>date</gi> element may occur
        within a set of elements. To specify the given data the following attributes can be used: <list>
          <item><att>calendar</att>: indicates the system or calendar to which a date belongs, for
            example, Gregorian, Julian, Roman, Mosaic, Revolutionary, Islamic, etc.</item>
          <item><att>cert</att>: signifies the degree of certainty or precision associated with a
            feature (high, medium, low, unknown)</item>
          <item><att>enddate</att>: contains the end point of a date range</item>
          <item><att>notafter</att>: contains an upper boundary for an uncertain date</item>
          <item><att>notbefore</att>: contains a lower boundary for an uncertain date</item>
          <item><att>reg</att>: gives the value of a date in standard ISO form.</item>
          <item><att>startdate</att>: contains the starting point of a date range</item>
        </list></p>
      <p>
        <!--Text/Standardisierung empfehlen, einleitenden Text zum reg attribute schreiben-->
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <date reg="2011-05-12"/>
        </egXML>
      </p>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="corpName">
      <head>corpName</head>
      <p>Corporate names are non-personal names which refer to structured bodies of one or more
        persons that act as a single entity. Typical examples include associations, businesses,
        projects or institutions (e.g. 'the Royal College of Music' or 'the BBC'), but also racial
        or ethnic groupings or political factions where these are regarded as forming a single
        agency. Organization names typically include some type of indicator or pattern or words that
        help identify them as non-personal names.</p>
      <p>The <gi>corpName</gi> element is particularly used within the <ref target="#header"
          >header</ref> of an MEI document. It might be enclosed in the <gi>respStmt</gi> element
        (example 1) <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <respStmt>
            <corpName>Library of Congress</corpName>
          </respStmt>
        </egXML> or could be used whereever it is necessary to mark up a corporate name, for example
        if a corporation is responsible for a certain event in the history of a musical work
        (example 2) <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <history>
            <eventList>
              <event>
                <corpName/>
              </event>
            </eventList>
          </history>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>When name parts are needed, they could be encoded in <gi>corpName</gi> sub-elements, for
        example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <corpName>Federal Research Division, <corpName>Library of Congress</corpName>
          </corpName>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>CorpName elements as well as <gi>corpName</gi> sub-elements might also be completed with
        address-elements for entering postal addresses of organizations within several
          <gi>addrLine</gi> elements. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <corpName>German Research Foundation
            <address>
              <addrLine>Kennedyallee 40</addrLine>
              <addrLine>53175 Bonn</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Germany</addrLine>
            </address>
          </corpName>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>Exact designations of corporate names can be taken from a controlled vocabulary, such as
        the Gemeinsame Normdatei (GND). If a controlled value is used, the list, from which it is
        taken should be recorded. In this case the following attributes are particularly relevant: <list>
          <item><att>authority</att>: to record the list from which a controlled value is
            taken,</item>
          <item><att>authURI</att> (authority URI): to record the web-accessible location of the
            controlled vocabulary from which the value is taken,</item>
          <item><att>dbkey</att> (database key): to record a value which serves as a primary key in
            an external database.</item>
        </list></p>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="geogName">
      <head>geogName</head>
      <p>Geographical names are proper noun designations for places (e.g. Baltimore, Maryland),
        natural features (e.g. Black Forest) or political jurisdictions (e.g. Quartier Latin,
        Paris). Like other proper nouns or noun phrases used as names, they can simply be marked up
        with the <gi>geogName</gi> element.</p>
      <p>The element can be used, e.g., to label geographical names in titles: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <title><geogName>Bohemian</geogName> folk songs</title>
        </egXML> or <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <title>Music in the <geogName>German Democratic Republic</geogName></title>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>Name sub-parts may be encoded in <gi>geogName</gi> sub-elements. For example: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <geogName>Baltimore, <geogName>Maryland</geogName></geogName>
        </egXML></p>
      <p>To enable a localization of an organization or to specify names of places with identical
        names it is recommendable to use a controlled vocabulary for names of places and countries.
        In this case the following attributes are particularly relevant: <list>
          <item><att>authority</att>: to record the list from which a controlled value is taken,
            e.g. the Thesaurus of Geographic Names (TGN),</item>
          <item><att>authURI</att> (authority URI): to record the web-accessible location of the
            controlled vocabulary from which the value is taken,</item>
          <item><att>dbkey</att> (database key): to record a value which serves as a primary key in
            an external database.</item>
        </list></p>
      <p>The encoder may use these attributes in combination. In case of the city Frankfurt, for
        example, a clarification whether Frankfurt am Main or Frankfurt an der Oder is meant, can be
        achieved by indicating the ID of the TGN entry. <list>
          <item>Frankfurt am Main: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <geogName dbkey="7005293" authority="TGN"
                authURI="www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn">Frankfurt</geogName>
            </egXML>
          </item>
          <item>Frankfurt an der Oder: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <geogName dbkey="7005972" authority="TGN"
                authURI="www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn">Frankfurt</geogName>
            </egXML>
          </item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p>The names of places given within addresses could be marked up with <gi>geogName</gi>
        elements as well, for example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <corpName dbkey="2007744-0" authURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd" authority="GND">German Research
            Foundation
            <address>
            <addrLine>Kennedyallee 40</addrLine>
            <addrLine>53175 <geogName dbkey="7005090" authURI="www.getty.edu/research/tools/
                vocabularies/tgn" authority="TGN">Bonn</geogName></addrLine>
            <addrLine><geogName dbkey="7000084" authURI="www.getty.edu/research/tools/
                vocabularies/tgn" authority="TGN">Germany</geogName></addrLine>
            </address>
          </corpName>
        </egXML>
      </p>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="periodName">
      <head>periodName</head>
      <p>PeriodNames are names which describe a particular period of time, which were characterized
        by obvious similarities in style, for example 'Baroque' or '3rd Style Period'. <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <periodName>Baroque</periodName>
        </egXML></p>
      <p>Each epochal term is to be seen as problematic, as it creates the impression that various
        styles replace each other directly and completely. This creates a number of differentiation
        issues, as there had indeed been simultaneous stylistic tendencies with little in common
        (and even often contradictory).</p>
      <p>The date sub-element is available within <gi>periodName</gi> in order to record any dates,
        associated with the periodName, i.e. the startdate and the enddate of a certain epoch:
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <periodName><date startdate="1600" enddate="1750"/>Baroque</periodName>
        </egXML>. The startdate and the enddate of a certain period may also be recorded by using
        the <att>startdate</att> and <att>enddate</att> attributes. <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <periodName startdate="1600" enddate="1750">Baroque</periodName>
        </egXML>.</p>
      <p>If a controlled value is used, the list, from which it is taken should be recorded. In this
        case the following attributes are particularly relevant: <list>
          <item><att>authority</att>: to record the list from which a controlled value is
            taken,</item>
          <item><att>authURI</att> (authority URI): to record the web-accessible location of the
            controlled vocabulary from which the value is taken,</item>
          <item><att>dbkey</att> (database key): to record a value which serves as a primary key in
            an external database.</item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <!--general question: which element should be used for the encoding of genres, forms etc.?-->
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="persName">
      <head>persName</head>
      <p>Personal names within an MEI-Doument could simply be marked up with the <gi>persName</gi>
        element which contains a propernoun or proper-noun phrase referring to an individual person.
        Personal names consist of several components, like forenames and surnames, but also other
        components like inherited or life-time titles of nobility, honorific or academic prefixes,
        military ranks or traditional descriptive phrases. It is not possible to mark up each of
        these components separately in MEI.
        <!-- #MH: warum nicht, und was muss man tun, wenn man das aber gerne machen möchte? --></p>
      <p>The <gi>persName</gi> element is often enclosed in the <gi>respStmt</gi> element which may
        occur within <gi>titleStmt</gi>, <gi>pubStmt</gi>, <gi>seriesStmt</gi> and <gi>change</gi>.
        A typical environment of the <gi>persName</gi> element would look like this: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <sourceDesc>
            <source>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>Im wunderschönen Monat Mai</title>
                <respStmt>
                  <persName>Robert Schumann</persName>
                </respStmt>
              </titleStmt>
            </source>
          </sourceDesc>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>Apart from the composer or originator of a musical work, there could be a lot of other
        persons being involved into the genesis of a musical work, like librettists, lyricists,
        arrangers, editors, transcripers, printers, publishers etc. The special roles of these
        persons may be marked up with the <att>role</att> attribute. For example: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <persName role="composer">Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart</persName>
        </egXML> or <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <persName role="lyricist">Heinrich Heine</persName>
        </egXML>The <ref target="http://www.loc.gov/marc/relators/relaterm.html">Marc code list for
          relators</ref> offers a variety of controlled terms on this concern.</p>
      <p>It is recommended to record personal names by using a standard for personal names, such as
        the Gemeinsame Normdatei (GND) or the Library of Congress Name Authorities.
        <!-- ToDo: Add link to GND und LoC Authorities --> The name of the list as well as the
        web-accessible location from which a controlled value is taken may be recorded using the
          <att>authority</att> and the <att>authURI</att> attribute. To record a value which serves
        as a primary key in an external database, the <att>dbkey</att> attribute may be used.</p>
      <p>Ideally, the three attributes are used in combination. For example: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <persName role="composer" dbkey="118584596" authURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd" authority="GND"
            >Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart</persName>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>Any data according to a person can be marked up by using the date sub-element. However,
        life data should not be marked up separately when taking a controlled value, as information
        relating to the biography of a person should be recorded in the linked database. </p>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="styleName">
      <head>styleName</head>
      <p>Music can be devided into different genres, forms and styles. The term style denotes a mode
        of expression or more particularly the manner in which a work of art is executed. "In the
        discussion of music, which is orientated towards relationships rather than meanings, the
        term raises special difficulties; it may be used to denote music characterized of an
        individual composer, of a period, of a geographical area or centre, or of a society or
        social function. For the aesthetician style concerns surface or appearance, though in music
        appearance and essence are ultimately inseparable. For the historian a style is a
        distinguishing and ordering concept, both consistent of and denoting generalities; he or she
        groups examples of music according to similarities between them." (Source: Grove Music
        Online, Article: Style, request date: 27.04.2012) Musical styles have to be distinguished
        from musical genres. The transitions are, however, fluent. The <gi>styleName</gi> element
        should not be confused with the <gi>periodName</gi> element (see above).
        <!--ToDo: add link to sub-chapter--></p>
      <p>StyleNames can be simply marked up with the <gi>styleName</gi> element, for example: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <styleName>bebop</styleName>
        </egXML>. It may be, e.g., used for recording a stylename within a title: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <title>La voix du <styleName>bebop</styleName></title>
        </egXML>, or to record a style of a certain epoch by using the <gi>styleName</gi>
        sub-element: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <periodName>Moderne <styleName>Jazz</styleName></periodName>
        </egXML></p>
      <p>If a controlled value is used, the list, from which it is taken should be recorded. In this
        case the following attributes are particularly relevant: <list>
          <item><att>authority</att>: to record the list from which a controlled value is
            taken,</item>
          <item><att>authURI</att> (authority URI): to record the web-accessible location of the
            controlled vocabulary from which the value is taken,</item>
          <item><att>dbkey</att> (database key): to record a value which serves as a primary key in
            an external database.</item>
        </list>
      </p>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="namesdatesAttributeClasses">
      <head>Attribute Classes</head>
      <p>No attribute classes are defined in this module.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="namesdatesModelClasses">
      <head>Model Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="model.nameLike.agent"/>
          <specDesc key="model.nameLike.geogName"/>
          <specDesc key="model.nameLike.place"/>
          <specDesc key="model.nameLike.label"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>