<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  © 2010 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs Unported License, 
  Version 3.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/.
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="namesDates" n="0">
  <head>Names and Dates</head>
  <p>This chapter describes a module which may be used for the encoding of names (names of persons
    or corporations/organizations) or descriptive phrases for styles, periods or geographical
    indications. In section <ptr target="#namesNumbersDates"/> it was noted that the elements
    provided in the core module allow an encoder to specify that a given text segment is a proper
    noun. The elements provided by the present module allow the encoder to supply a detailed
    sub-structure for such proper nouns, and to distinguish explicitly between persons and
    organizations, and between stylistic, periodical or geographical indications.</p>
  <p>The chapter begins by discussing the elements provided for the encoding of names
    (<gi>name</gi>) and dates (<gi>date</gi>) in general and finishes by addressing more specific
    elements for corporate names (<gi>corpName</gi>), geographic names (<gi>geogName</gi>), period
    names (<gi>periodName</gi>), personal names (<gi>persName</gi>) and style names
      (<gi>styleName</gi>). In general it is recommended to use standardized forms of proper nouns
    and to record the names and web-accessible locations of the controlled vocabularies used. There
    are several authority files, especially for geographical, organizational and personal names,
    such as the Gemeinsame Normdatei (GND), the Library of Congress Authorities, the Getty Thesaurus
    of Geographic Names (TGN), and the MARC code list for relators. Recommendations on which
    standards could be used can be found in the descriptions of the individual elements.
    <!-- Generell: Vielleicht an den Stellen, wo eines der nachfolgenden Elemente in vielen Elementen erlaubt ist,
    auf die model.Klasse verweisen, in Form von: These elements are all members of the model.placeNamePart etc.,
    wird in TEI ebenfalls so gehandhabt.--><!-- #MH: finde ich gut! -->
  </p>
  <p>The basic elements for capturing names and dates are defined in the shared module:</p>
  <p>
    <specList>
      <specDesc key="name"/>
      <specDesc key="date"/>
    </specList>
  </p>
  <p>The <gi>name</gi> element contains the name of an entity that is difficult to tag more
    specifically as a <gi>corpName</gi>, <gi>geogName</gi>, <gi>persName</gi>, or <gi>title</gi>. In
    section <ptr target="#namesNumbersDates"/> it was noted that the <gi>name</gi> element may be
    used in place of the more specific elements when it is not known what kind of name is being
    described or when a high degree of precision is not necessary. For example, the <gi>name</gi>
    element might be used when it is not clear whether the name "Bach" refers to a person or a
    geographic feature. When name parts are needed, use <gi>name</gi> sub-elements. The recommended
    values for the <att>type</att> attribute are: <list type="simple">
      <item>pers, </item>
      <item>corp, </item>
      <item>place, </item>
      <item>process.</item>
    </list> The date sub-element is available within <gi>name</gi> in order to record any dates
    associated with the name, i.e., creation and dissolution in the case of a corporate entity or
    place. The name of the list from which a controlled value is taken, such as the Library of
    Congress Name Authority File (LCNAF), may be recorded using the authority attribute.</p>
  <p>Examples of the use of the <gi>name</gi> element:</p>
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <name type="pers">Henry VIII, King of England</name>
    <name type="corp">The Beatles</name>
    <name type="place">Bach</name>
    <name type="process"/>
    <!--ToDo: Fill in example-->
  </egXML>
  <p>The element <gi>date</gi> contains a date in any format, including a date range. A date range
    may be expressed as textual content or, when intervening punctuation is present, as a
    combination of date sub-elements and text.</p>
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <date>5/3/05</date>
    <date>May 30, 2012</date>
    <date>March 1-21, 1812</date>
    <date>
      <date>March 1, 1812</date> - <date>March 21, 1812</date></date>
  </egXML>
  <p>To be more specific about the date, the following attributes can be used: <list type="gloss">
      <label><att>calendar</att></label>
      <item>indicates the system or calendar to which a date belongs, for example, Gregorian,
        Julian, Roman, Mosaic, Revolutionary, Islamic, etc.</item>
      <label><att>cert</att></label>
      <item>signifies the degree of certainty or precision associated with a feature (high, medium,
        low, unknown)</item>
      <label><att>enddate</att></label>
      <item>contains the end point of a date range in standard ISO form</item>
      <label><att>notafter</att></label>
      <item>contains an upper boundary for an uncertain date</item>
      <label><att>notbefore</att></label>
      <item>contains a lower boundary for an uncertain date</item>
      <label><att>reg</att></label>
      <item>gives the value of a date in standard ISO form</item>
      <label><att>startdate</att></label>
      <item>contains the starting point of a date range in standard ISO form</item>
    </list>
  </p>
  <!--TODO: Give more examples of the use of the attributes above.  PR -->
  <p>In the following example, the ambiguous date text "5/3/05" is resolved using the <att>reg</att>
    attribute:</p>
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <date reg="1905-05-03">5/3/05</date>
    <date reg="2005-03-05">5/3/05</date>
  </egXML>
  <!--Text/Standardisierung empfehlen, einleitenden Text zum reg attribute schreiben-->

  <div type="div2" xml:id="namesdatesSpecialized">
    <head>Specialized Name and Date Elements</head>
    <p>In addition to the generic <gi>name</gi> and <gi>date</gi> elements, the namesDates module
      provides for the markup of the specialized cases described below.</p>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="corpName">
      <head>Corporate Names</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="corpName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>Corporate names are non-personal names which refer to structured bodies of one or more
        persons that act as a single entity. Typical examples include associations, businesses,
        projects or institutions (e.g. 'the Royal College of Music' or 'the BBC'), but also racial
        or ethnic groupings or political factions where these are regarded as forming a single
        agency. Organization names typically include some type of indicator or pattern or words that
        help identify them as non-personal names.</p>
      <p>The <gi>corpName</gi> element is frequently used within the <ref target="#header"
          >header</ref> of an MEI document. It is typically found in the <gi>respStmt</gi>
        element:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <respStmt>
          <corpName>Library of Congress</corpName>
        </respStmt>
      </egXML>
      <p>It may also be used whereever it is necessary to mark a corporate name, for example when a
        corporation is responsible for a certain event in the history of a musical work:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <history>
          <eventList>
            <event>
              <corpName>The XYZ Corporation</corpName>
            </event>
          </eventList>
        </history>
      </egXML>
      <!-- TODO: Provide more detail in this example -->

      <p>When name parts are needed, they may be encoded in <gi>corpName</gi> sub-elements, for
        example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <corpName>Federal Research Division, <corpName>Library of Congress</corpName>
        </corpName>
      </egXML>

      <!-- :-( This is an artifact of allowing corpName to contain all other inline elements.  Putting addresses inside corporate
      names shouldn't be encouraged. -->
      <!-- <p>CorpName elements as well as <gi>corpName</gi> sub-elements might also be completed with
        address elements for entering postal addresses of organizations within several
          <gi>addrLine</gi> elements. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <corpName>German Research Foundation
            <address>
              <addrLine>Kennedyallee 40</addrLine>
              <addrLine>53175 Bonn</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Germany</addrLine>
            </address>
          </corpName>
        </egXML>
      </p> -->

      <p>Standard designations for corporate bodies can be taken from a controlled vocabulary, such
        as the Gemeinsame Normdatei (GND). If a controlled value is used, the list from which it is
        taken should be recorded. In this case the following attributes are particularly relevant:
          <list type="gloss">
          <label><att>authority</att></label>
          <item>to record the list from which a controlled value is taken,</item>
          <label><att>authURI</att> (authority URI)</label>
          <item>to record the web-accessible location of the controlled vocabulary from which the
            value is taken,</item>
          <label><att>dbkey</att> (database key)</label>
          <item>to record a value which serves as a primary key in an external database.</item>
        </list>
      </p>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="geogName">
      <head>Geographic Names</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="geogName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>Geographic names are proper noun designations for places (e.g. Baltimore, Maryland),
        natural features (e.g. Black Forest) or political jurisdictions (e.g. Quartier Latin,
        Paris).</p>
      <p>The element can be used, e.g., to label geographical names in titles:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <title><geogName>Bohemia</geogName>: Folk Songs</title>
        <title>Music in the <geogName>German Democratic Republic</geogName></title>
      </egXML>

      <p>Geographic name sub-parts may be encoded in <gi>geogName</gi> sub-elements. For
        example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <geogName><geogName>Baltimore</geogName>, <geogName>Maryland</geogName></geogName>
        <geogName><geogName>French Quarter</geogName>, <geogName>New Orleans,
            </geogName><geogName>Louisiana</geogName></geogName>
      </egXML>
      <p>To enable localization of an organization, or to specify names of places with identical
        names, the use of controlled vocabulary is recommend for names of administrative divisions,
        such as cities, states, and countries. In this case, the following attributes are
        particularly relevant:</p>
      <list type="gloss">
        <label><att>authority</att></label>
        <item>records the list from which a controlled value is taken, e.g., the Thesaurus of
          Geographic Names (TGN),</item>
        <label><att>authURI</att> (authority URI)</label>
        <item>records the web-accessible location of the controlled vocabulary from which the value
          is taken,</item>
        <label><att>dbkey</att> (database key)</label>
        <item>records a value which serves as a primary key in an external database.</item>
      </list>
      <p>The encoder may use these attributes in combination. In case of the German city of
        Frankfurt, for example, a clarification whether Frankfurt am Main or Frankfurt an der Oder
        is meant can be achieved by referring to the ID of the TGN entry:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <!-- Frankfurt am Main -->
        <geogName dbkey="7005293" authority="TGN"
          authURI="www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn">Frankfurt</geogName>
        <!-- Frankfurt an der Oder -->
        <geogName dbkey="7005972" authority="TGN"
          authURI="www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn">Frankfurt</geogName>
      </egXML>

      <p>The names of places given within addresses can be marked with <gi>geogName</gi> elements,
        for example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <corpName dbkey="2007744-0" authURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd" authority="GND">German Research
          Foundation</corpName>
        <address>
            <addrLine>Kennedyallee 40</addrLine>
            <addrLine>53175 <geogName dbkey="7005090" authURI="www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn" authority="TGN">Bonn</geogName></addrLine>
            <addrLine><geogName dbkey="7000084" authURI="www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn" authority="TGN">Germany</geogName></addrLine>
            </address>
      </egXML>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="periodName">
      <head>Time Period Names</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="periodName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>periodName</gi> element is for names which describe a particular period of time,
        for example, those which characterize obvious similarities in style, such as 'Baroque' or
        '3rd Style Period':</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <periodName>Baroque</periodName>
      </egXML>
      <!-- What are you trying to say in the paragraph below?  That such terms shouldn't be used as descriptive terms in the header?
        That they shouldn't be used at all? The element is designed for use in front and back matter where "free text"
        often includes such terms. -->
      <p>Each epochal term is to be seen as problematic, as it creates the impression that various
        styles replace each other directly and completely. This creates a number of differentiation
        issues, as there had indeed been simultaneous stylistic tendencies with little in common
        (and even often contradictory).</p>
      <p>The date sub-element is available within <gi>periodName</gi> in order to record any dates
        associated with the name that should be captured in the text, for example, start and end
        dates:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <periodName>Baroque (<date>1600</date>-<date>1750</date>)</periodName>
      </egXML>
      <p>The start and end points of a certain period may also be recorded by using the
          <att>startdate</att> and <att>enddate</att> attributes:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <periodName startdate="1600" enddate="1750">Baroque</periodName>
      </egXML>
      <p>If a controlled value is used, the list from which it is taken should be recorded. In this
        case the following attributes are particularly relevant: <list type="gloss">
          <label><att>authority</att></label>
          <item>to record the list from which a controlled value is taken,</item>
          <label><att>authURI</att> (authority URI)</label>
          <item>to record the web-accessible location of the controlled vocabulary from which the
            value is taken,</item>
          <label><att>dbkey</att> (database key)</label>
          <item>to record a value which serves as a primary key in an external database.</item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <!--general question: which element should be used for the encoding of genres, forms etc.?-->
      <!-- PR: If you mean which element should be used in the header, it's <term>. However, unlike TEI,
        MEI doesn't yet permit <term> to occur in its "text-y" parts. It can be added there, but <term> would
        then need to be moved from the header to the shared module. -->
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="persName">
      <head>Personal Names</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="persName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>Personal names within an MEI-Doument could simply be marked up with the <gi>persName</gi>
        element which contains a propernoun or proper-noun phrase referring to an individual person.
        Personal names consist of several components, like forenames and surnames, but also other
        components like inherited or life-time titles of nobility, honorific or academic prefixes,
        military ranks or traditional descriptive phrases. It is not possible to mark up each of
        these components separately in MEI.
        <!-- #MH: warum nicht, und was muss man tun, wenn man das aber gerne machen möchte? --></p>
      <p>The <gi>persName</gi> element is often enclosed in the <gi>respStmt</gi> element which may
        occur within <gi>titleStmt</gi>, <gi>pubStmt</gi>, <gi>seriesStmt</gi> and <gi>change</gi>.
        A typical environment of the <gi>persName</gi> element would look like this: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <sourceDesc>
            <source>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>Im wunderschönen Monat Mai</title>
                <respStmt>
                  <persName>Robert Schumann</persName>
                </respStmt>
              </titleStmt>
            </source>
          </sourceDesc>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>Apart from the composer or originator of a musical work, there could be a lot of other
        persons being involved into the genesis of a musical work, like librettists, lyricists,
        arrangers, editors, transcripers, printers, publishers etc. The special roles of these
        persons may be marked up with the <att>role</att> attribute. For example: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <persName role="composer">Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart</persName>
        </egXML> or <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <persName role="lyricist">Heinrich Heine</persName>
        </egXML>The <ref target="http://www.loc.gov/marc/relators/relaterm.html">Marc code list for
          relators</ref> offers a variety of controlled terms on this concern.</p>
      <p>It is recommended to record personal names by using a standard for personal names, such as
        the Gemeinsame Normdatei (GND) or the Library of Congress Name Authorities.
        <!-- ToDo: Add link to GND und LoC Authorities --> The name of the list as well as the
        web-accessible location from which a controlled value is taken may be recorded using the
          <att>authority</att> and the <att>authURI</att> attribute. To record a value which serves
        as a primary key in an external database, the <att>dbkey</att> attribute may be used.</p>
      <p>Ideally, the three attributes are used in combination. For example: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <persName role="composer" dbkey="118584596" authURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd" authority="GND"
            >Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart</persName>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>Any data according to a person can be marked up by using the date sub-element. However,
        life data should not be marked up separately when taking a controlled value, as information
        relating to the biography of a person should be recorded in the linked database. </p>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="styleName">
      <head>Style Names</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="styleName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>Music can be devided into different genres, forms and styles. The term style denotes a mode
        of expression or more particularly the manner in which a work of art is executed. "In the
        discussion of music, which is orientated towards relationships rather than meanings, the
        term raises special difficulties; it may be used to denote music characterized of an
        individual composer, of a period, of a geographical area or centre, or of a society or
        social function. For the aesthetician style concerns surface or appearance, though in music
        appearance and essence are ultimately inseparable. For the historian a style is a
        distinguishing and ordering concept, both consistent of and denoting generalities; he or she
        groups examples of music according to similarities between them." (Source: Grove Music
        Online, Article: Style, request date: 27.04.2012) Musical styles have to be distinguished
        from musical genres. The transitions are, however, fluent. The <gi>styleName</gi> element
        should not be confused with the <gi>periodName</gi> element (see above).
        <!--ToDo: add link to sub-chapter--></p>
      <p>StyleNames can be simply marked up with the <gi>styleName</gi> element, for example: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <styleName>bebop</styleName>
        </egXML>. It may be, e.g., used for recording a stylename within a title: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <title>La voix du <styleName>bebop</styleName></title>
        </egXML>, or to record a style of a certain epoch by using the <gi>styleName</gi>
        sub-element: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <periodName>Moderne <styleName>Jazz</styleName></periodName>
        </egXML></p>
      <p>If a controlled value is used, the list, from which it is taken should be recorded. In this
        case the following attributes are particularly relevant: <list>
          <item><att>authority</att>: to record the list from which a controlled value is
            taken,</item>
          <item><att>authURI</att> (authority URI): to record the web-accessible location of the
            controlled vocabulary from which the value is taken,</item>
          <item><att>dbkey</att> (database key): to record a value which serves as a primary key in
            an external database.</item>
        </list>
      </p>
    </div>
  </div>
  <!--<div type="div2" xml:id="namesdatesOverview">
    <head>Overview of the NamesDates module</head>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="namesdateElements">
      <p>The namesDates module provides the following elements:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="corpName"/>
          <specDesc key="geogName"/>
          <specDesc key="persName"/>
          <specDesc key="periodName"/>
          <specDesc key="styleName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="namesdatesAttributeClasses">
      <head>Attribute Classes</head>
      <p>No attribute classes are defined in this module.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="namesdatesModelClasses">
      <head>Model Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="model.nameLike.agent"/>
          <specDesc key="model.nameLike.geogName"/>
          <specDesc key="model.nameLike.place"/>
          <specDesc key="model.nameLike.label"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
  </div>-->
</div>
