<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
  © 2014 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
  not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License
  at http://www.osedu.org/licenses/ECL-2.0.
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
  OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language
  governing permissions and limitations under the License.
  
  This is a derivative work based on earlier versions of the schema © 2001-2006 Perry Roland
  and the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia; licensed under the Educational
  Community License version 1.0.
  
  CONTACT: info@music-encoding.org
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="namesDates" n="0">
  <head>Names and Dates</head>
  <p>This chapter describes the MEI module used for the encoding of names (names of persons or
    corporations/organizations) or descriptive phrases for styles, periods or geographical
    indications. In section <ptr target="#namesNumbersDates"/> it was noted that the elements
    provided in the core module allow an encoder to specify that a given text segment is a proper
    noun. The elements provided by the present module allow the encoder to supply a detailed
    sub-structure for such proper nouns, and to distinguish explicitly between persons and
    organizations, and between stylistic, periodical or geographical indications.</p>
  <p>The chapter begins by discussing the elements provided for the encoding of names (<gi
      scheme="MEI">name</gi>) and dates (<gi scheme="MEI">date</gi>) in general and finishes by
    addressing more specific elements for corporate names (<gi scheme="MEI">corpName</gi>),
    geographic names (<gi scheme="MEI">geogName</gi>), period names (<gi scheme="MEI"
      >periodName</gi>), personal names (<gi scheme="MEI">persName</gi>) and style names (<gi
      scheme="MEI">styleName</gi>). In general it is recommended to use standardized forms of proper
    nouns and to record the names and web-accessible locations of the controlled vocabularies used.
    There are several commonly-referenced authority files, especially for geographical,
    organizational and personal names, such as the Gemeinsame Normdatei (GND), the Library of
    Congress Authorities, the Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names (TGN), and the MARC code list for
    relators. Recommendations on which standards could be used can be found in the descriptions of
    the individual elements.</p>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="namesdatesBasic">
    <head>Basic Elements for Names and Dates</head>
    <p>The basic elements for capturing names and dates are defined in the shared module:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="name"/>
        <specDesc key="date"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">name</gi> element contains the name of an entity that is difficult to
      tag more specifically as a <gi scheme="MEI">corpName</gi>, <gi scheme="MEI">geogName</gi>, <gi
        scheme="MEI">persName</gi>, or <gi scheme="MEI">title</gi>. In section <ptr
        target="#namesNumbersDates"/> it was noted that the <gi scheme="MEI">name</gi> element may
      be used in place of the more specific elements when it is not known what kind of name is being
      described or when a high degree of precision is not necessary. For example, the <gi
        scheme="MEI">name</gi> element might be used when it is not clear whether the name "Bach"
      refers to a person or a geographic feature. When name parts are needed, use <gi scheme="MEI"
        >name</gi> sub-elements. The recommended values for the <att>type</att> attribute are:</p>
    <list type="gloss">
      <label>'pers'</label>
      <item> - a personal name</item>
      <label>'corp'</label>
      <item> - the name of a corporate entity</item>
      <label>'place'</label>
      <item> - a geographic name</item>
      <label>'process'</label>
      <item> - the name of a process or mechanical agent</item>
    </list>
    <p>The date sub-element is available within <gi scheme="MEI">name</gi> in order to record any
      dates associated with the name, for example, creation and dissolution in the case of a
      corporate entity or place or birth and death dates in the case of an individual. The name of
      the list from which a controlled value is taken, such as the Library of Congress Name
      Authority File (LCNAF), may be recorded using the authority attribute.</p>
    <p>Examples of the use of the <gi scheme="MEI">name</gi> element:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<name type="pers">Henry VIII, King of England</name>
<name type="corp">The Beatles</name>
<name type="place">Orbach</name>
<name type="process">OMR software</name>
    </egXML>
    <p>The element <gi scheme="MEI">date</gi> contains a date in any format, including a date range.
      A date range may be expressed as textual content or, when intervening punctuation is present,
      as a combination of date sub-elements and text.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<date>5/3/05</date>
<date>May 30, 2012</date>
<date>March 1-21, 1812</date>
<date>
  <date>March 1, 1812</date> - <date>March 21, 1812</date>
</date>
    </egXML>
    <p>To be more specific about the date, the attributes in the <ident type="class"
        >att.datable</ident> class can be used:</p>
    <list type="gloss">
      <label><att>startdate</att></label>
      <item> - contains the starting point of a date range in standard ISO form</item>
      <label><att>enddate</att></label>
      <item> - contains the end point of a date range in standard ISO form</item>
      <label><att>notbefore</att></label>
      <item> - contains a lower boundary for an uncertain date</item>
      <label><att>notafter</att></label>
      <item> - contains an upper boundary for an uncertain date</item>
      <label><att>isodate</att></label>
      <item> - gives the value of a textual date in standard ISO form</item>
      <label><att>calendar</att></label>
      <item> - indicates the system or calendar to which a date belongs, for example, Gregorian,
        Julian, Roman, Mosaic, Revolutionary, Islamic, etc.</item>
      <label><att>cert</att></label>
      <item> - signifies the degree of certainty or precision associated with a feature (high,
        medium, low, unknown)</item>
    </list>
    <p>In the following example, the ambiguous date text "5/3/05" is resolved using the
        <att>isodate</att> attribute:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<date isodate="1905-05-03">5/3/05</date>
<date isodate="2005-03-05">5/3/05</date>
    </egXML>
  </div>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="namesdatesSpecialized">
    <head>Specialized Name and Date Elements</head>
    <p>In addition to the generic <gi scheme="MEI">name</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI">date</gi> elements
      provided by the shared module, the namesDates module provides for the markup of the
      specialized cases described below.</p>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="namesdatesCorpNames">
      <head>Corporate Names</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="corpName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>Corporate names are non-personal names which refer to structured bodies of one or more
        persons that act as a single entity. Typical examples include associations, businesses,
        projects or institutions (e.g.,. 'the Royal College of Music' or 'the BBC'), but also racial
        or ethnic groupings or political factions where these are regarded as forming a single
        agency. Organization names typically include some type of indicator or pattern or words that
        help identify them as non-personal names.</p>
      <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">corpName</gi> element is frequently used within the <ref
          target="#header">header</ref> of an MEI document. It is typically found in the <gi
          scheme="MEI">respStmt</gi> element:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<respStmt>
  <corpName>Library of Congress</corpName>
</respStmt>
      </egXML>
      <p>It may also be used wherever it is necessary to mark a corporate name, for example when a
        corporation is responsible for a certain event in the history of a musical work:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<history>
  <eventList>
    <event>
      <p>First performance by <corpName>The Boston Symphony Orchestra</corpName>,
          <date>October 22, 1881</date>.</p>
    </event>
  </eventList>
</history>
      </egXML>

      <p>When it is necessary to provide structure for a name, the separate parts of the name may be
        encoded in <gi scheme="MEI">corpName</gi> sub-elements, for example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<corpName>Federal Research Division, <corpName>Library of Congress</corpName></corpName>
      </egXML>

      <p>Standard designations for corporate bodies can be taken from a controlled vocabulary, such
        as the Gemeinsame Normdatei (GND). If a controlled value is used, the list from which it is
        taken should be recorded. In this case, the following attributes are particularly
        relevant:</p>
      <list type="gloss">
        <label><att>authority</att></label>
        <item> - to record the list from which a controlled value is taken,</item>
        <label><att>authURI</att> (authority URI)</label>
        <item> - to record the web-accessible location of the controlled vocabulary from which the
          value is taken,</item>
        <label><att>dbkey</att> (database key)</label>
        <item> - to record a value which serves as a primary key in an external database.</item>
      </list>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="namesdatesGeogNames">
      <head>Geographic Names</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="geogName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>Geographic names are proper noun designations for places (e.g.,. Baltimore, Maryland),
        natural features (e.g.,. Black Forest) or political jurisdictions (e.g.,. Quartier Latin,
        Paris).</p>
      <p>The element can be used, e.g., to label geographical names in titles:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<title><geogName>Bohemia</geogName>: Folk Songs</title>
<title>Music in the <geogName>German Democratic Republic</geogName></title>
      </egXML>

      <p>Geographic name sub-parts may be encoded in <gi scheme="MEI">geogName</gi> sub-elements.
        For example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<p>
  <geogName><geogName>Baltimore</geogName>, <geogName>Maryland</geogName></geogName>
  <geogName><geogName>French Quarter</geogName>, <geogName>New Orleans</geogName>,
      <geogName>Louisiana</geogName></geogName>
</p>
      </egXML>
      <p>To enable localization of an organization, or to specify names of places with identical
        names, the use of controlled vocabulary is recommend for names of administrative divisions,
        such as cities, states, and countries. In this case, the following attributes are
        particularly relevant:</p>
      <list type="gloss">
        <label><att>authority</att></label>
        <item> - records the list from which a controlled value is taken, e.g., the Thesaurus of
          Geographic Names (TGN),</item>
        <label><att>authURI</att> (authority URI)</label>
        <item> - records the web-accessible location of the controlled vocabulary from which the
          value is taken,</item>
        <label><att>dbkey</att> (database key)</label>
        <item> - records a value which serves as a primary key in an external database.</item>
      </list>
      <p>The encoder may use these attributes in combination. In case of the German city of
        Frankfurt, for example, a clarification whether Frankfurt am Main or Frankfurt an der Oder
        is meant can be achieved by referring to the ID of the TGN entry:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<!-- Frankfurt am Main -->
<geogName dbkey="7005293" authority="TGN" authURI="www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn">Frankfurt</geogName>
<!-- Frankfurt an der Oder -->
<geogName dbkey="7005972" authority="TGN" authURI="www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn">Frankfurt</geogName>
      </egXML>

      <p>The names of places given within addresses can be marked with <gi scheme="MEI"
          >geogName</gi> elements, for example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<corpName dbkey="2007744-0" authURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd" authority="GND">German Research
  Foundation</corpName>
<address>
  <addrLine>Kennedyallee 40</addrLine>
  <addrLine>53175 <geogName dbkey="7005090" authURI="www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn" authority="TGN">Bonn</geogName></addrLine>
  <addrLine><geogName dbkey="7000084" authURI="www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn" authority="TGN">Germany</geogName></addrLine>
</address>
      </egXML>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="namesdatesPeriodNames">
      <head>Time Period Names</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="periodName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">periodName</gi> element is for names which describe a particular
        period of time, for example, those which characterize obvious similarities in style, such as
          <soCalled>Baroque</soCalled> or <soCalled>3rd Style Period</soCalled>:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<periodName>Baroque</periodName>
      </egXML>

      <p>The date sub-element is available within <gi scheme="MEI">periodName</gi> in order to
        record any dates associated with the name that should be captured in the text, for example,
        start and end dates of the named period:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<periodName>Baroque (<date>1600</date>-<date>1750</date>)</periodName>
      </egXML>
      <p>Recording start and end points of a certain period using the <att>startdate</att> and
          <att>enddate</att> attributes may prove to be better for machine processing:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<periodName startdate="1600" enddate="1750">Baroque</periodName>
      </egXML>
      <p>If a controlled value is used, the list from which it is taken should be recorded. In this
        case the following attributes are relevant:</p>
      <list type="gloss">
        <label><att>authority</att></label>
        <item> - to record the list from which a controlled value is taken,</item>
        <label><att>authURI</att> (authority URI)</label>
        <item> - to record the web-accessible location of the controlled vocabulary from which the
          value is taken,</item>
        <label><att>dbkey</att> (database key)</label>
        <item> - to record a value which serves as a primary key in an external database.</item>
      </list>
      <!--general question: which element should be used for the encoding of genres, forms etc.?-->
      <!-- PR: If you mean which element should be used in the header, it's <term>. However, unlike TEI,
        MEI doesn't yet permit <term> to occur in its "text-y" parts. It can be added there, but <term> would
        then need to be moved from the header to the shared module. -->
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="namesdatesPersNames">
      <head>Personal Names</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="persName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <!-- Need schematron rule to enforce the following: -->
      <p>Personal names within an MEI document may simply be marked with the <gi scheme="MEI"
          >persName</gi> element containing a proper noun or proper noun phrase referring to an
        individual. Personal names, however, often consist of several components, like forenames and
        surnames, but also other components, such as inherited or life-time titles of nobility,
        honorific or academic prefixes, military ranks or traditional descriptive phrases. These
        components may be marked using <gi scheme="MEI">name</gi> sub-elements, the function of
        which may be indicated using the <att>type</att> attribute. In this case, <att>type</att>
        attribute may take the following values:</p>
      <list type="gloss">
        <label>'forename'</label>
        <item> - contains a forename, given or baptismal name.</item>
        <label>'surname'</label>
        <item> - a family (inherited) name, as opposed to a given, baptismal, or nick name.</item>
        <label>'rolename'</label>
        <item> - contains a name component which indicates that the referent has a particular role
          or position in society, such as an official title or rank.</item>
        <label>'addname'(additional name)</label>
        <item> - contains an additional name component, such as a nickname, epithet, or alias, or
          any other descriptive phrase used within a personal name.</item>
        <label>'namelink' (name link)</label>
        <item> - contains a connecting phrase or link used within a name but not regarded as part of
          it, such as <emph>van der</emph> or <emph>of</emph>.</item>
        <label>'genname' (generational name)</label>
        <item> - contains a name component used to distinguish otherwise similar names on the basis
          of the relative ages or generations of the persons named.</item>
      </list>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<persName>
  <name type="forename">Henry</name>
  <name type="genname">VIII</name>, <name type="rolename">King of England</name>,
    <date>1491-1547</date>
</persName>
<persName>
  <name type="surname">Kilmarnock</name>, <name type="forename">William</name>
  <name type="forename">Boyd</name>, <name type="rolename">Earl of</name>
</persName>
      </egXML>

      <p>The <gi scheme="MEI">persName</gi> element is often enclosed in the <gi scheme="MEI"
          >respStmt</gi> element which may occur within <gi scheme="MEI">titleStmt</gi>, <gi
          scheme="MEI">pubStmt</gi>, <gi scheme="MEI">seriesStmt</gi> and <gi scheme="MEI"
          >change</gi>. This usage of the <gi scheme="MEI">persName</gi> element typical looks like
        this:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" valid="false">
<sourceDesc>
  <source>
    <titleStmt>
      <title>Im wunderschönen Monat Mai</title>
      <respStmt>
        <persName>Robert Schumann</persName>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
  </source>
</sourceDesc>
      </egXML>
      <p>Apart from the composer or originator of a musical work, however, there could be many other
        persons involved in the genesis of a musical work, such as librettists, lyricists,
        arrangers, editors, transcribers, printers, publishers, etc. The special roles of these
        persons may be marked using the <att>role</att> attribute on <gi scheme="MEI">persName</gi>.
        For example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<persName role="arranger">Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart</persName>
      </egXML>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<persName role="lyricist">Heinrich Heine</persName>
      </egXML>
      <p>The <ref target="http://www.loc.gov/marc/relators/relaterm.html">Marc code list for
          relators</ref> offers a variety of controlled terms that may serve as values for this use
        of <att>role</att>.</p>
      <p>For names in the metadata header, the use of a controlled list, such as the Gemeinsame
        Normdatei (GND) or the Library of Congress Name Authorities, is recommended.
        <!-- ToDo: Add link to GND und LoC Authorities --> The name and web-accessible location of
        the list may be recorded using the <att>authority</att> and <att>authURI</att> attributes,
        respectively. To record a value which serves as a primary key in an external database, the
          <att>dbkey</att> attribute may be used.</p>
      <p>For maximal machine-processability, these three attributes may be used in combination. For
        example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<persName role="composer" dbkey="118584596" authURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd" authority="GND">Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart</persName>
      </egXML>
      <!--<p>Any data according to a person can be marked up by using the date sub-element. However,
        life data should not be marked up separately when taking a controlled value, as information
        relating to the biography of a person should be recorded in the linked database. </p>-->
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="namesdatesStyleNames">
      <head>Style Names</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="styleName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>Music can be divided into different styles, genres, and forms. The term <term>style</term>
        denotes a mode of expression, or more particularly, the manner in which a work of art is
        executed:</p>
      <p>"In the discussion of music, which is orientated towards relationships rather than
        meanings, the term raises special difficulties; it may be used to denote music characterized
        of an individual composer, of a period, of a geographical area or center, or of a society or
        social function. For the aesthetician style concerns surface or appearance, though in music
        appearance and essence are ultimately inseparable. For the historian a style is a
        distinguishing and ordering concept, both consistent of and denoting generalities; he or she
        groups examples of music according to similarities between them." (Source: "Style", Grove
        Music Online, accessed: April 27, 2012) <!--ToDo: add link to sub-chapter--></p>
      <p>The name of a musical style can be marked by the <gi scheme="MEI">styleName</gi> element,
        for example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<styleName>bebop</styleName>
      </egXML>
      <p>It may be, e.g., used for recording a style name within a title:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<title>La voix du <styleName>bebop</styleName></title>
      </egXML>
      <p>or to record a style of a certain epoch by using the <gi scheme="MEI">styleName</gi>
        sub-element:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<periodName>Modern <styleName>Jazz</styleName></periodName>
      </egXML>

      <p>If a controlled value is used, the list, from which it is taken should be recorded. In this
        case the following attributes are particularly relevant:</p>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item><att>authority</att>: records the list from which a controlled value is taken,</item>
        <item><att>authURI</att> (authority URI): indicates the web-accessible location of the
          controlled vocabulary from which the value is taken,</item>
        <item><att>dbkey</att> (database key): holds a value which serves as a primary key in an
          external database.</item>
      </list>

      <p>Musical forms and genres must be distinguished from musical style. Form and genre are
        typically indicated using the <gi scheme="MEI">classification</gi> element, described in
        chapter <ptr target="#workClass"/>.</p>
    </div>
  </div>
  <!--<div type="div2" xml:id="namesdatesOverview">
    <head>Overview of the NamesDates module</head>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="namesdatesElements">
      <p>The namesDates module provides the following elements:</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="corpName"/>
          <specDesc key="geogName"/>
          <specDesc key="persName"/>
          <specDesc key="periodName"/>
          <specDesc key="styleName"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="namesdatesAttributeClasses">
      <head>Attribute Classes</head>
      <p>No attribute classes are defined in this module.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="namesdatesModelClasses">
      <head>Model Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="model.nameLike.agent"/>
          <specDesc key="model.nameLike.geogName"/>
          <specDesc key="model.nameLike.place"/>
          <specDesc key="model.nameLike.label"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
  </div>-->
</div>
