<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  © 2010 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs Unported License, 
  Version 3.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/.
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="neumes" n="0">
  <head>Neume Notation</head>
  <p>This chapter describes the elements, model classes, and attribute classes that are part of the
    MEI.neumes module.</p>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="neumesOverview">
    <!-- Overview -->
    <head>Overview of the Neumes Module</head>
    <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="ineume"/>
        <specDesc key="syllable"/>
        <specDesc key="uneume"/>
      </specList>
    </p>

    <!--<div type="div3" xml:id="neumesElements">
      <head>Elements</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="ineume"/>
          <specDesc key="syllable"/>
          <specDesc key="uneume"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="neumesAttributeClasses">
      <head>Attribute Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="att.ineume.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.ineume.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.ineume.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.ineume.vis"/>
          <specDesc key="att.uneume.anl"/>
          <specDesc key="att.uneume.ges"/>
          <specDesc key="att.uneume.log"/>
          <specDesc key="att.uneume.vis"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="neumesModelClasses">
      <head>Model Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="model.eventLike.neumes"/>
          <specDesc key="model.layerPart.neumes"/>
          <specDesc key="model.syllableLike"/>
          <specDesc key="model.syllablePart"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>-->

  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="neumes1.1">
    <head>Module Background</head>
    <p>Neume encoding in MEI was initially developed as part of the Hildegard von Bingen project at
      the University of Tübingen. MEI was chosen as the basic representation format after a <ref
        target="http://www.dimused.uni-tuebingen.de/tuebingen_phase1_e.php">comparison of existing
        music encoding formats</ref>. The initial work on this module was performed by Gregor
      Schräder <ref target="http://www.dimused.uni-tuebingen.de/downloads/studienarbeit.pdf">(Ein
        XML-Datenformat zur Repräsentation kritischer Musikedition unter besonderer Berücksichtigung
        von Neumennotation)</ref>, supervised by Prof. Stefan Morent. </p>
    <p>This module was originally developed against version 1.8 of the MEI DTD, and has subsequently
      been translated to the TEI ODD schema.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="neumes1.2">
    <head>Neume Notation</head>
    <p> Most neume notation is used to set music to an existing text. The syllable is the
      fundamental unit of structure, with the neumes themselves serving as a means of "sonifying"
      the text. A syllable may be expressed via one or more neumes, with the particular neume shape
      chosen depending on the pitch contour that is being employed and the desired interpretation.
      For example, two pitches in rising succession might be encoded as a "podatus" (sometimes also
      called a "pes"), or it might be encoded as two separate punctums, depending on whether it
      should be sung smoothly connected or with a slight amount of space between the notes.</p>
    <p> There are a limited number of possiblities for the most popular musical contours. In
      general, groups of two to four notes are given unique names, assigned depending on their
      contour. A "clivis" would be two joined descending notes, while a "podatus" is two joined
      ascending notes. Table 1 shows most of the named neume shapes. Neume groups of more than four
      notes are simply called "compound" neumes.</p>
    <table n="1">
      <row>
        <cell>
          <graphic url="guidelines/Images/modules/neumes/parrish_neumes.png"/>
        </cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell> Table 1: Variant neume notation. (From Parrish, "The notation of medieval music," 6)
        </cell>
      </row>
    </table>
    <p>As shown in Table 1, it is possible to have many different styles of neume shapes, derived
      from local practices of regional groups. In general, these styles are all interpreted in a
      similar fashion; however, there is evidence that the performance practice of some styles of
      neume notation differed with regard to rhythm and cadence. This version of the MEI neumes
      module does not attempt to encode any rhythmic information present in the neume notation.
      While it may be possible to encode rhythmic values on <gi>note</gi> elements, this practice is
      highly discouraged and, if present, should be interpreted as a modern transcription not
      present in the original sources.</p>
    <p> Neume notation existed before the invention of the staff. Staffless neume notation
      ("adiastemtic", "cheironomic" or "in campo aperto") existed primarily as a mnemonic device,
      reminding performers of the contour of the melody but lacking any absolute pitch information.
      These neumes were written above the text. With the invention of the staff lines and the clef,
      "heightened" or "diastematic" neume notation could be used to provide exact interval
      information. In some cases the staff lines are not actually drawn on the page, but their
      position relative to an imaginary line and initial clef is consistent.</p>
    <p>The <gi>syllable</gi> element is used as the primary organizational element for neume
      notation within a <gi>layer</gi> element. Within <gi>syllable</gi>, the <gi>syl</gi> element
      defined in the MEI.shared module is used for encoding the textual content, while the
        <gi>uneume</gi> and <gi>ineume</gi> elements are used to encode the neumes themeselves.
      Within these neume module elements, other standard MEI mechanisms are available to
      accommodate, for example, editorial or critical markup.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="neumes1.4">
    <head>Examples</head>
    <p>Some of these examples are excerpts from works of Hildegard von Bingen, with the encoding
      performed by Stefan Morent and Gregor Schräder.</p>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="neumes1.4.1">
      <head>Basic Encoding</head>
      <p>The example illustrates the most basic encoding of neume notation. Encoded here is the
        opening of Hildegarde's "O Splendidissima Gemma" with the text "O splendidissima".
        Information about the staff has been omitted for brevity, but it was originally encoded on a
        5-line staff with two clefs, a "C" and a "F" on lines 5 and 3, respectively.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <layer>
          <syllable>
            <syl n="initial">
              <rend color="red">O</rend>
            </syl>
            <uneume name="porrectus">
              <note pname="e" oct="3"/>
              <note pname="d" oct="3"/>
              <note pname="e" oct="3"/>
            </uneume>
          </syllable>
          <syllable>
            <syl>splen_</syl>
            <uneume name="clivis">
              <note pname="g" oct="3"/>
              <note pname="e" oct="3"/>
            </uneume>
            <uneume name="pes">
              <note pname="d" oct="3"/>
              <note pname="e" oct="3"/>
            </uneume>
          </syllable>
          <syllable>
            <syl>di_</syl>
            <ineume name="climacus">
              <uneume name="virga">
                <note pname="f" oct="3"/>
              </uneume>
              <uneume name="punctum">
                <note pname="d" oct="3"/>
              </uneume>
              <uneume name="punctum">
                <note pname="c" oct="3"/>
              </uneume>
            </ineume>
          </syllable>
          <syllable>
            <syl>dis_</syl>
            <uneume name="virga">
              <note pname="e" oct="3"/>
            </uneume>
          </syllable>
          <syllable>
            <syl>si_</syl>
            <ineume name="scandicus">
              <uneume name="punctum">
                <note pname="a" oct="2"/>
              </uneume>
              <uneume name="punctum">
                <note pname="b" oct="2"/>
              </uneume>
              <uneume name="virga">
                <note pname="c" oct="3"/>
              </uneume>
            </ineume>
          </syllable>
          <syllable>
            <syl>ma</syl>
            <uneume name="clivis">
              <note pname="b" oct="2"/>
              <note pname="a" oct="2"/>
            </uneume>
          </syllable>
        </layer>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="neumes1.4.2">
      <head>Encoding Variants</head>
      <p>Variant readings across sources may be encoded. In this example, source "D" has a punctum
        on the syllable "so" that is not present in source "R".</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <syllable>
          <syl>so_</syl>
          <uneume xml:id="d18e" name="punctum">
            <note pname="g" oct="3"/>
          </uneume>
          <app xml:id="app1">
            <rdg source="D">
              <uneume xml:id="d19e" name="punctum">
                <note pname="g" oct="3"/>
              </uneume>
            </rdg>
            <rdg source="R"/>
          </app>
        </syllable>
      </egXML>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="neumes1.4.3">
      <head>Supplied Notes</head>
      <p>In the case of neume notation where no absolute pitch is indicated, you may use the
          <gi>supplied</gi> element to indicate an editorially-added pitch. This element's
          <att>source</att> attribute may be used to supply a reference to a source with the
        absolute pitch provided.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <syllable>
          <syl>so_</syl>
          <uneume xml:id="d13" name="podatus">
            <supplied>
              <note pname="g" oct="3"/>
            </supplied>
          </uneume>
        </syllable>
      </egXML>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
