<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  © 2010 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs Unported License, 
  Version 3.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/.
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="shared" n="0">
  <head>Shared Elements, Model Classes, and Attribute Classes</head>
  <p>This chapter describes the elements, model classes, and attribute classes that are part of the
    MEI.shared module.</p>

  <div type="div2">
    <head>Document Elements</head>
    <p>The following elements are available for the representation of the outermost structure of an
      MEI document:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="mei" atts="meiversion"/>
        <specDesc key="meiCorpus"/>
        <specDesc key="meiHead"/>
        <specDesc key="music"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>A typical MEI document contains an <gi>mei</gi> element, which in turn contains metadata,
      represented by an <gi>meiHead</gi> element, and the musical text itself, represented by a
        <gi>music</gi> element. The <gi>meiHead</gi> element, formally declared in the MEI.header
      module, is described in chapter <ptr target="#header"/></p>
    <p>Other variations on this basic form are also available for the representation of a:</p>
    <list type="simple">
      <item>collection of related MEI-encoded texts</item>
      <item>document that contain only metadata, known as an independent or stand-alone
        header.</item>
      <item>musical text that is intended to be embedded within another kind of markup, such as TEI,
        via XML namespaces.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Further information regarding the organization and encoding of music corpora is given in
      chapter <ptr target="#"/><!--“Music Corpora”.-->. Stand-alone headers are more fully described
      in chapter <ptr target="#header"/>.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="div2">
    <head>Music Element</head>
    <p>The remainder of this chapter describes the <gi>music</gi> element and its high-level
      constituents.</p>
    <p>MEI texts may be regarded either as unitary, that is, forming an organic whole, or as
      composite, that is, consisting of several components which are in some important sense
      independent of each other. The distinction is not always entirely obvious. For example, a
      collection of songs might be regarded as a single item in some circumstances, or as a number
      of distinct items in others. In such borderline cases, the encoder must choose whether to
      treat the text as unitary or composite; each may have advantages and disadvantages in a given
      situation.</p>
    <p>Whether unitary or composite, the musical text is marked with the <gi>music</gi> tag and may
      contain front matter, a body, and back matter. In unitary texts, the body is tagged using the
        <gi>body</gi> element; in composite texts, however, where the textual body consists of a
      series of subordinate musical texts or other groups, it is tagged with the <gi>group</gi>
      element. The overall structure of any musical text, unitary or composite, is thus defined by
      the following elements: </p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="front"/>
        <specDesc key="body"/>
        <specDesc key="group"/>
        <specDesc key="back"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>The overall structure of a single musical text is:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <mei>
        <meiHead>
          <!-- metada goes here -->
        </meiHead>
        <music>
          <front>
            <!-- front matter of text, if any, goes here -->
          </front>
          <body>
            <!-- body of text goes here -->
          </body>
          <back>
            <!-- back matter of text, if any, goes here -->
          </back>
        </music>
      </mei>
    </egXML>

    <p>The overall structure of a composite musical text made up of two unitary musical texts is: </p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <mei>
        <meiHead>
          <!-- metadata for the composite musical text  -->
        </meiHead>
        <music>
          <front>
            <!-- front matter for composite musical text -->
          </front>
          <group>
            <music>
              <front>
                <!-- front matter of first unitary musical text, if any -->
              </front>
              <body>
                <!-- body of first unitary musical text -->
              </body>
              <back>
                <!-- back matter of first unitary musical text, if any -->
              </back>
            </music>
            <music>
              <body>
                <!-- body of second unitary musical text -->
              </body>
            </music>
          </group>
          <back>
            <!-- back matter for composite musical text, if any -->
          </back>
        </music>
      </mei>
    </egXML>
    <div type="div3">
      <head>Divisions of the body</head>
      <p>This section describes sub-division of the body of a musical text.
        <!--Front and back matter
          are described in chapter XX, “Text in MEI”.--></p>
      <p>The body of a unitary musical text may contain one or more discrete, linear segments. The
        names commonly used for these structural subdivisions vary with the genre and period of the
        music, or even at the whim of the author, editor, or publisher. For example, a major
        subdivision of a symphony is generally referred to as a ‘movement’. An opera, on the other
        hand, is usually organized into ‘acts’ and then further by ‘scenes’. All such divisions are
        treated as occurrences of the same neutrally-named element, with an attribute @type used to
        categorize them independently of their hierarchic level.</p>
      <p>The following element is used to identify musical subdivisions: </p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="mdiv"/>
      </p>
      <p>As a member of the class att.typed, this element has attributes which can be used to
        classify or sub-classify elements.</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="mdiv" atts="type subtype"/>
      </p>
      <p>To accommodate “divisions within divisions”, an <gi>mdiv</gi> element may contain
        additional <gi>mdiv</gi> elements down to any level required. For example, the encoding of a
        symphony might have the following structure:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <body xmlns="http://www.music-encoding.org/ns/mei">
          <mdiv type="symphony">
            <mdiv type="movement" n="1">
              <!-- contents of mvt 1 -->
            </mdiv>
            <mdiv type="movement" n="2">
              <!-- contents of mvt 2 -->
            </mdiv>
            <mdiv type="movement" n="3">
              <!-- contents of mvt 3 -->
            </mdiv>
            <mdiv type="movement" n="4">
              <!-- contents of mvt 4 -->
            </mdiv>
          </mdiv>
        </body>
      </egXML>
      <p>or, in the case of Verdi's opera, <title> Il Trovatore</title>:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <body>
          <mdiv type="opera">
            <mdiv type="act" n="I">
              <mdiv type="scene" n="1"><!-- contents of act I, sc. 1 --></mdiv>
              <mdiv type="scene" n="2"><!-- contents of act I, sc. 2--></mdiv>
              <mdiv type="scene" n="3"><!-- contents of act I, sc. 3 --></mdiv>
            </mdiv>
            <mdiv type="act" n="II">
              <mdiv type="scene" n="1"><!-- contents of act II, sc. 1 --></mdiv>
              <mdiv type="scene" n="2"><!-- contents of act II, sc. 2 --></mdiv>
              <mdiv type="scene" n="3"><!-- contents of act II, sc. 3 --></mdiv>
              <mdiv type="scene" n="4"><!-- contents of act II, sc. 4 --></mdiv>
              <mdiv type="scene" n="5"><!-- contents of act II, sc. 5 --></mdiv>
            </mdiv>
            <mdiv type="act" n="III">
              <mdiv type="scene" n="1"><!-- contents of act III, sc. 1 --></mdiv>
              <mdiv type="scene" n="2"><!-- contents of act III, sc. 2 --></mdiv>
              <mdiv type="scene" n="3"><!-- contents of act III, sc. 3 --></mdiv>
            </mdiv>
            <mdiv type="act" n="IV">
              <mdiv type="scene" n="1"><!-- contents of act IV, sc. 1 --></mdiv>
              <mdiv type="scene" n="2"><!-- contents of act IV, sc. 2 --></mdiv>
              <mdiv type="scene" n="3"><!-- contents of act IV, sc. 3 --></mdiv>
            </mdiv>
          </mdiv>
        </body>
      </egXML>
      <p>Conventionally, the musical structures represented by <gi>mdiv</gi> elements are separated
        by pauses; however, <foreign>attacca</foreign>, <foreign>attacca subito</foreign>,
          <foreign>seque</foreign>, or similar terms are sometimes used at the end of an
          <gi>mdiv</gi> to indicate that the next <gi>mdiv</gi> should begin immediately after the
        conclusion of the current one.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3">
      <head>Content of musical divisions</head>
      <p>The <gi>mdiv</gi> element may contain one or both of two possible views: score and
        parts.</p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="score"/>
          <specDesc key="parts"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The score element contains a traditional, full (or “open”) score while the parts element
        contains each performer’s view of the work. Score and parts views are intended to
        accommodate different methods of organizing the markup – no particular presentation is
        implied, and software may render a collection of parts as a score or a score as a collection
        of parts. The explicit encoding of two views is necessary because it is not always possible
        or desirable to automatically derive one view from the other. In addition, separating scores
        and parts can eliminate a great deal of markup complexity.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <body>
          <mdiv type="movement" n="1">
            <score>
              <!-- markup of score goes here -->
            </score>
            <parts>
              <!-- markup of performers’ parts goes here -->
            </parts>
          </mdiv>
          <!-- additional movements go here -->
        </body>
      </egXML>
      <p>Performers' parts are contained within <gi>part</gi> elements:</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="part"/>
      </p>
      <p>A <gi>part</gi> is effectively a mini-score requiring all the encoding features of a full
        score. <gi>Part</gi> elements are useful for encoding performing parts when there is no
        score, such as in early music part books, when the music has non-aligning bar lines, when
        different layout, such as page turns, are needed for the score and parts, or for
        accommodating software that requires part-by-part encoding. Please note that part elements
        in MEI are not an indication of voice leading. Voice leading can be encoded using the next
        attribute available on all event-type elements.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <parts>
          <part>
            <!-- first performer’s part -->
          </part>
          <part>
            <!-- second performer’s part -->
          </part>
          <!-- additional performers’ parts -->
        </parts>
      </egXML>
      <p>In both score and part views, the <gi>scoredef</gi> element is used to describe logical
        characteristics of the encoded music, such as key signature, the "actual" key (as opposed to
        the notated key signature), meter, etc. and visual features, such as page size, staff
        groupings and labels, etc.</p>
      <p>A <gi>part</gi> or <gi>score</gi> may be further divided into linear segments called
        “sections”.</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="section"/>
      </p>
      <p><gi>Section</gi> elements often function as a scoping mechanism for clef signs, key and
        meter signatures, plus metronome, tempo, and expression markings. Their use minimizes the
        need for backward scanning to establish context when the starting point for access is not at
        the beginning of the score. <gi>Section</gi> elements may also be used for other
        user-defined, i.e., analytical or editorial, purposes, and arbitrarily nested to any desired
        level. </p>
      <p>The <gi>ending</gi> element is a specialized instance of the <gi>section</gi> element that
        may not be recursively nested.</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="ending"/>
      </p>
      <p>The most common (non-analytical) use of <gi>section</gi> and <gi>ending</gi> elements is
        illustrated below:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <score>
          <section>
            <!-- section one to be repeated -->
          </section>
          <ending n="1">
            <!-- 1st ending -->
          </ending>
          <ending n="2">
            <!-- 2nd ending -->
          </ending>
          <section>
            <!-- next section -->
          </section>
        </score>
      </egXML>
      <p>Within <gi>section</gi> elements, several methods of organization are possible, depending
        upon notational style of the source material and the encoder's needs. For example, when the
        MEI.cmn module is used, the default organization is measure-by-measure, with <gi>staff</gi>
        and <gi>layer</gi> sub-elements within each <gi>measure</gi>. Further discussion of CMN
        notation is continued in chapter <!-- XX, “CMN notation”-->.</p>
      <p>However, staff-by-staff organization is more appropriate for music without measures and is
        provided when the MEI.mensural module is employed. Coverage of mensural notation is provided
        in chapter <!--XX, “Mensural notation”-->.</p>
      <p>It must be noted it is possible to encode CMN notation without using <gi>measure</gi>
        elements; that is, staff-by-staff organization may be used and the ends of measures marked
        using <gi>barLine</gi> elements. In certain circumstances, this approach may be preferable
        for reproduction of the visual layout of the music. When both the MEI.cmn and MEI.mensural
        modules are invoked, the simultaneous use of the <gi>measure</gi> and <gi>barLine</gi>
        elements should be avoided.</p>
      <p>The remainder of this chapter covers the remaining elements available within the music
        element.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3">
      <head>Grouped texts</head>
      <p>The group element discussed in chapter <!--XX, “Grouped Texts”-->, should be used to
        represent a collection of independent musical texts which is to be regarded as a single unit
        for processing or other purposes.</p>
      <p>
        <specDesc key="group"/>
      </p>
      <p>Examples of composite texts which should be represented using the <gi>group</gi> element
        include anthologies and other collections. The presence of common front matter referring to
        the whole collection, possibly in addition to front matter relating to each individual
        musical text, is a good indication that a given musical text might usefully be encoded in
        this way; however, this structure may be found useful in other circumstances as well. </p>
      <p>For example, the overall structure of a collection of songs might be encoded as follows: </p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <music>
          <group>
            <!-- Example incomplete! -->
          </group>
        </music>
      </egXML>
      <p>A musical text which is a member of a group may itself contain groups:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <music>
          <group>
            <!-- Example incomplete! -->
          </group>
        </music>
      </egXML>
      <p>The group element may be used in this way to encode any kind of collection of which the
        constituents are regarded by the encoder as works in their own right, such as <foreign>ad
          hoc</foreign> collections or anthologies of works of a single composer not originally
        conceived of as a single composition or musical pieces by different composers.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3">
      <head>Front matter</head>
      <p>By front matter we mean distinct sections of a text (usually, but not necessarily, a
        printed one), prefixed to it by way of introduction or identification as a part of its
        production. Features such as title pages or prefaces are clear examples; a less definite
        case might be the prologue attached to a dramatic work. The front matter of an encoded text
        should not be confused with the MEI header described in chapter <!--3, “The MEI Header”-->, which
        provides metadata for the entire file. </p>
      <p>An encoder may choose simply to ignore the front matter in a text, if the original
        presentation of the work is of no interest, or for other reasons. No specific tags are
        provided for the various kinds of subdivision which may appear within front matter: instead,
        generic div (“division”) elements may be used, which should not be confused with mdiv
        (“musical division”) elements. The following suggested values for the @type attribute may be
        used to distinguish various kinds of division characteristic of front matter: </p>
      <list type="unordered">
        <item>'preface' – A foreword or preface addressed to the reader in which the author or
          publisher explains the content, purpose, or origin of the text. </item>
        <item>'ack' – A formal declaration of acknowledgment by the author in which persons and
          institutions are thanked for their part in the creation of a text.</item>
        <item>'dedication' – A formal offering or dedication of a text to one or more persons or
          institutions by the author.</item>
        <item>'abstract' – A summary of the content of a text as continuous prose.</item>
        <item>'contents' – A table of contents, specifying the structure of a work and listing its
          constituents. The list element should be used to mark its structure.</item>
        <item>'frontispiece' – A pictorial frontispiece, possibly including some text.</item>
      </list>
      <p>The following extended example demonstrates how various parts of the front matter of a text
        may be encoded. The front part begins with a title page, which is presented in section <!--XX,
        “Title Pages”-->, below. This is followed by a dedication and a preface, each of which is
        encoded as a distinct div: </p>
      <p>&lt;div type="dedication"&gt;</p>
      <p> &lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- Dedicatory text --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>
      <p>&lt;/div&gt;</p>
      <p>&lt;div type="preface"&gt;</p>
      <p> &lt;head&gt;Preface&lt;/head&gt;</p>
      <p> &lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- paragraph 1 --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>
      <p> &lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- paragraph 2 --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</p>
      <p>&lt;/div&gt;</p>
      <p>The front matter concludes with another div element, shown in the next example, this time
        containing a table of contents, which contains a list element (as described in section 3.7
        Lists). Note the use of the ptr element to provide page-references: the implication here is
        that the target identifiers supplied (song1, song2, etc.) will correspond with identifiers
        used for the mdiv elements containing the individual songs themselves. (For the ptr element,
        see chapter <!--XX, “Simple Links and Cross-References”-->.) </p>
      <p>&lt;div type="contents"&gt;</p>
      <p> &lt;head&gt;Contents&lt;/head&gt;</p>
      <p> &lt;list&gt;</p>
      <p> &lt;item n="1"&gt;On Wenlock Edge &lt;ptr target="#song1"/&gt;&lt;/item&gt;</p>
      <p> &lt;item n="2"&gt;From Far, From Eve and Morning &lt;ptr
        target="#song2"/&gt;&lt;/item&gt;</p>
      <p> &lt;/list&gt;</p>
      <p>&lt;/div&gt;</p>
      <p>Alternatively, the pointers in the table of contents might link to the page breaks at which
        a song begins, assuming that these have been included in the markup: </p>
      <p>&lt;!-- .... --&gt;</p>
      <p>&lt;item n="1"&gt;On Wenlock Edge &lt;ref
        target="#song1-p15"&gt;15&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/item&gt;</p>
      <p>&lt;!-- .... --&gt;</p>
      <p>&lt;mdiv type="song"&gt;</p>
      <p> &lt;pb xml:id="song-p15"/&gt;</p>
      <p> &lt;!-- .... --&gt;</p>
      <p>&lt;/mdiv&gt;</p>
      <p>&lt;!-- .... --&gt;</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3">
      <head>Title pages</head>
      <p>Detailed analysis of the title page and other preliminaries of older printed books and
        manuscripts is of major importance in descriptive bibliography and the cataloging of printed
        books; such analysis, however, requires a more detailed approach than the general one
        described here. The following elements are suggested as a means of encoding the major
        features of most title pages: </p>
      <list type="unordered">
        <item>&lt;titlePage&gt; (title page) contains the title page of a text, appearing within the
          front or back matter. </item>
        <item>&lt;p&gt; (paragraph) contains one or more text phrases that form a logical prose
          passage.</item>
        <item>&lt;table&gt; contains text displayed in tabular form, that is, in rows and
          columns.</item>
        <item>&lt;list&gt; contains a series of items separated from one another and arranged in a
          linear, often vertical, sequence.</item>
        <item>&lt;quote&gt; designates an extended quotation; that is, a passage attributed to a
          source external to the text.</item>
        <item>&lt;lg&gt; (line group) contains a section of text that is organized as a group of
          lines.</item>
        <item>&lt;graphic&gt; indicates the location of an inline graphic, illustration, or
          figure.</item>
      </list>
      <p>Together with the figure element described in chapter <!--XX, “Tables, Formulæ, and Graphics-->”,
        these elements constitute the model.titlepagePart class. Any number of elements from this
        class can appear grouped together within a titlePage element. The figure element is included
        so as to enable encoders to record the presence of complex non-textual material on a title
        page. For simple cases such as printers' ornaments or illustrations, the graphic element
        discussed in section <!--XX, “Graphics and other non-textual components”-->, should be adequate. </p>
      <p>
        <hi rend="strikethrough">The elements listed above, together with the head element, also
          constitute the class model.pLike.front. The elements in this class can appear within a
          minimal front element without any need to group them together and encode a complete title
          page.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Encoders wishing to add new elements to either class may do so using the methods described
        in section <!--XX, “Personalization and Customization”-->. Two examples of the use of these
        elements follow. First, the title page of the work discussed earlier in this section: </p>
      <p>
        <hi rend="strikethrough">&lt;front&gt; &lt;titlePage&gt; &lt;docTitle&gt; &lt;titlePart
          type="main"&gt;Is There a Text in This Class?&lt;/titlePart&gt; &lt;titlePart
          type="sub"&gt;The Authority of Interpretive Communities&lt;/titlePart&gt;
          &lt;/docTitle&gt; &lt;docAuthor&gt;Stanley Fish&lt;/docAuthor&gt; &lt;docImprint&gt;
          &lt;publisher&gt;Harvard University Press&lt;/publisher&gt; &lt;pubPlace&gt;Cambridge,
          Massachusetts&lt;/pubPlace&gt; &lt;pubPlace&gt;London, England&lt;/pubPlace&gt;
          &lt;/docImprint&gt; &lt;/titlePage&gt;&lt;/front&gt;</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Second, a characteristically verbose 17th century example. Note the use of the lb tag to
        mark the line breaks of the original where necessary: </p>
      <p>
        <hi rend="strikethrough">&lt;titlePage&gt; &lt;docTitle&gt; &lt;titlePart type="main"&gt;THE
          &lt;lb/&gt;Pilgrim's Progress &lt;lb/&gt;FROM &lt;lb/&gt;THIS WORLD, &lt;lb/&gt;TO
          &lt;lb/&gt;That which is to come:&lt;/titlePart&gt; &lt;titlePart type="sub"&gt;Delivered
          under the Similitude of a &lt;lb/&gt;DREAM&lt;/titlePart&gt; &lt;titlePart
          type="desc"&gt;Wherein is Discovered, &lt;lb/&gt;The manner of his setting out,
          &lt;lb/&gt;His Dangerous Journey; And safe &lt;lb/&gt;Arrival at the Desired
          Countrey.&lt;/titlePart&gt; &lt;/docTitle&gt; &lt;epigraph&gt; &lt;cit&gt; &lt;quote&gt;I
          have used Similitudes,&lt;/quote&gt; &lt;bibl&gt;Hos. 12.10&lt;/bibl&gt; &lt;/cit&gt;
          &lt;/epigraph&gt; &lt;byline&gt;By &lt;docAuthor&gt;John
          Bunyan&lt;/docAuthor&gt;.&lt;/byline&gt; &lt;imprimatur&gt;Licensed and Entred according
          to Order.&lt;/imprimatur&gt; &lt;docImprint&gt; &lt;pubPlace&gt;LONDON,&lt;/pubPlace&gt;
          Printed for &lt;name&gt;Nath. Ponder&lt;/name&gt; &lt;lb/&gt;at the
          &lt;name&gt;Peacock&lt;/name&gt; in the &lt;name&gt;Poultrey&lt;/name&gt; &lt;lb/&gt;near
          &lt;name&gt;Cornhil&lt;/name&gt;, &lt;docDate&gt;1678&lt;/docDate&gt;.
          &lt;/docImprint&gt;&lt;/titlePage&gt;</hi>
        <lb/>
        <lb/>Where, as here, it is considered important to encode salient features of the way a
        title page was originally rendered, the techniques exemplified in <!--2.3.4 The Tagging
        Declaration--> may also be useful. </p>
      <p>Where title pages are encoded, their physical rendition is often of considerable
        importance. One approach to this requirement would be to use the seg tag, described in
        chapter <!--16 Linking, Segmentation, and Alignment-->, to segment the typographic content of each
        part of the title page, and then use the global @rend attribute to specify its rendition.
        Another would be to use a module customized for the description of typographic entities such
        as pages, lines, rules, etc., bearing special-purpose attributes to describe line-height,
        leading, degree of kerning, font, etc. Further discussion of these problems is provided in
        chapter <!--XX, “Representation of Primary Sources”-->.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3">
      <head>Back matter</head>
      <p>Conventions vary as to which elements are grouped as back matter and which as front. For
        example, some books place the table of contents at the front, and others at the back. Even
        title pages may appear at the back of a book as well as at the front. The content model for
        back and front elements are therefore identical. <hi rend="color(FF0000)">(NOT YET IN
          MEI!)</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The following suggested values may be used for the @type attribute on all division
        elements, in order to distinguish various kinds of division characteristic of back matter: </p>
      <list type="unordered">
        <item>'appendix' – An ancillary self-contained section of a work, often providing additional
          but in some sense extra-canonical text.</item>
        <item>'glossary' – A list of terms associated with definition texts (‘glosses’).</item>
        <item>'notes' – A section in which textual notes are gathered together.</item>
        <item>'bibliography' – A list of bibliographic citations.</item>
        <item>'index' – Any form of index to the work.</item>
        <item>'colophon' – A statement appearing at the end of a book describing the conditions of
          its physical production.</item>
      </list>
      <p>No additional elements are proposed for the encoding of back matter at present. Some
        characteristic examples follow; first, an index (for the case in which a printed index is of
        sufficient interest to merit transcription): </p>
      <p>&lt;back&gt; &lt;div type="index"&gt; &lt;head&gt;Index&lt;/head&gt; &lt;list
        type="index"&gt; &lt;item&gt;Actors, public, paid for the contempt attending their
        profession, &lt;ref&gt;263&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;/item&gt; &lt;item&gt;Africa, cause assigned for
        the barbarous state of the interior parts of that continent, &lt;ref&gt;125&lt;/ref&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt; &lt;item&gt;Agriculture &lt;list type="indexentry"&gt; &lt;item&gt;ancient
        policy of Europe unfavourable to, &lt;ref&gt;371&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;artificers necessary to carry it on, &lt;ref&gt;481&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;cattle and tillage mutually improve each other, &lt;ref&gt;325&lt;/ref&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt; &lt;item&gt;wealth arising from more solid than that which proceeds from
        commerce &lt;ref&gt;520&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;/item&gt; &lt;/list&gt; &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Alehouses, not the efficient cause of drunkenness, &lt;ref&gt;461&lt;/ref&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt; &lt;/list&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/back&gt;<lb/>
        <lb/> Note that if the page breaks in the original source have also been explicitly encoded,
        and given identifiers, the references to them in the above index can more usefully be
        recorded as links. For example, assuming that the encoding of page 461 of the original
        source starts like this: </p>
      <p>&lt;pb xml:id="P461"/&gt;then the last item above might be encoded more usefully in either
        of the following forms: </p>
      <p>&lt;item&gt;Alehouses, not the efficient cause of drunkenness, &lt;ref
        target="#P461"&gt;461&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Alehouses, not the efficient cause
        of drunkenness, &lt;ptr target="#P461"/&gt;&lt;/item&gt;Next, a back-matter division in
        epistolary form: </p>
      <p>&lt;back&gt; &lt;div type="letter"&gt; &lt;head&gt;A letter written to his wife, founde
        with this booke after his death.&lt;/head&gt; &lt;p&gt;The remembrance of the many wrongs
        offred thee, and thy unreproued vertues, adde greater sorrow to my miserable state, than I
        can utter or thou conceiue. ... ... yet trust I in the world to come to find mercie, by the
        merites of my Saiuour to whom I commend thee, and commit my soule.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;signed&gt;Thy repentant husband for his disloyaltie, &lt;name&gt;Robert
        Greene.&lt;/name&gt; &lt;/signed&gt; &lt;epigraph xml:lang="la"&gt; &lt;p&gt;Faelicem fuisse
        infaustum&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/epigraph&gt; &lt;trailer&gt;FINIS&lt;/trailer&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/back&gt;<lb/>
        <lb/> And finally, a list of corrigenda and addenda with pseudo-epistolary features: </p>
      <p>&lt;back&gt; &lt;div type="corrigenda"&gt; &lt;head&gt;Addenda&lt;/head&gt; &lt;salute
        xml:lang="la"&gt;M. Scriblerus Lectori&lt;/salute&gt; &lt;p&gt;Once more, gentle reader I
        appeal unto thee, from the shameful ignorance of the Editor, by whom Our own Specimen of
        &lt;name&gt;Virgil&lt;/name&gt; hath been mangled in such miserable manner, that scarce
        without tears can we behold it. At the very entrance, Instead of &lt;q
        xml:lang="gr"&gt;προλεγομενα&lt;/q&gt;, lo! &lt;q xml:lang="gr"&gt;προλεγωμενα&lt;/q&gt;
        with an Omega! and in the same line &lt;q xml:lang="la"&gt;consulâs&lt;/q&gt; with a
        circumflex! In the next page thou findest &lt;q xml:lang="la"&gt;leviter
        perlabere&lt;/q&gt;, which his ignorance took to be the infinitive mood of &lt;q
        xml:lang="la"&gt;perlabor&lt;/q&gt; but ought to be &lt;q xml:lang="la"&gt;perlabi&lt;/q&gt;
        ... Wipe away all these monsters, Reader, with thy quill.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/back&gt;</p>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div type="div2">
    <head>Shared Element Classes</head>
  </div>
  <div type="div2">
    <head>Shared Attribute Classes</head>
  </div>
  <div type="div2">
    <p>The MEI.shared module</p>
    <p>The module described by the present chapter has the following components: </p>
    <p>Module MEI.shared:</p>
    <p>•Elements defined: [list of MEI elements]</p>
    <p>The selection and combination of modules to form an MEI schema is described in chapter <!--1.2,
      “Defining an MEI Schema”-->.</p>
  </div>
</div>
