<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  © 2010 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs Unported License, 
  Version 3.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/.
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="tablature" n="0">
  <head>Tablature Notation</head>
  <p>This chapter describes the attribute classes that are part of the MEI.tablature module.</p>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="tablatureOverview">
    <!-- Overview -->
    <head>Overview of the Tablature Module</head>
    <p>The tablature module is used to record tablature notation. This version is fairly basic, designed
    primarily for guitar and similar plucked-string instruments.</p>
    <p>The <att>lines</att> attribute on the <gi>staffDef</gi> element is used to define the 
      number of lines, courses, or strings, present in the tablature. The <att>tab.strings</att> attribute 
      is then used to enumerate the pitches of the open string. It is important to note that this
      is given using the written pitch, not the sounding pitch. For example, the 
      Western 6-string guitar, in standard tuning, sounds an octave below written pitch.
    </p>
    <p>The <att>tab.strings</att> attribute gives the string tuning, ordered from highest to 
    lowest pitch.</p>
    <p>For standard guitar tuning, the <gi>staffDef</gi> element might look like this:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <staffDef n="1" lines="6" tab.strings="e5 b4 g4 d4 a3 e3" />
    </egXML>
    <p>Chromatic alteration may be indicated with the '-' or 'f' (flat), or the 
      '#' or 's' (sharp). Multiple sharps and flats are not permitted.</p>
    <p>A guitar in E flat tuning might look like this:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <staffDef n="1" lines="6" tab.strings="ef5 bf4 gf4 df4 af3 ef3" />
    </egXML>
    <p>Some instruments, like the 12-string guitar, have the four lowest strings tuned an octave above
    but are still written on a 6-line tablature staff. In this case, you may enumerate the open string pitches
    while maintaining 6 lines.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <staffDef n="1" lines="6" tab.strings="e4 e3 a4 a3 d4 d3 g5 g4 b4 b4 e5 e5" />
    </egXML>
    <p>The <gi>note</gi> element is then used to capture the specific events in 
    the tablature. The <att>tab.string</att> attribute is used to capture which 
    string the note is to be played on. String order is the same as that given 
    in the <att>tab.strings</att> attribute. This  attribute takes a positive 
    integer in the range of 1-9.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <note tab.string="3" pname="a" oct="3" dur="4"/>
    </egXML>
    <p>In the case of fretted instruments, you may also capture the fret number with the <att>tab.fret</att> attribute. 
      You may also capture the open string with an "o" value. </p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <note tab.string="6" pname="a" oct="2" dur="4" tab.fret="5"/>
      <note tab.string="5" pname="a" oct="2" dur="4" tab.fret="o"/>
    </egXML>
    <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:</p>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="tablatureElements">
      <head>Elements</head>
      <p>No elements are defined in this module.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="tablatureAttributeClasses">
      <head>Attribute Classes</head>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="att.note.ges.tablature"/>
          <specDesc key="att.staffDef.ges.tablature"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="tablatureModelClasses">
      <head>Model Classes</head>
      <p>No model classes are defined in this module.</p>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
