<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
  © 2012 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.
  Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
  not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License
  at http://www.osedu.org/licenses/ECL-2.0.
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
  OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language
  governing permissions and limitations under the License.
  
  This is a derivative work based on earlier versions of the schema © 2001-2006 Perry Roland
  and the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia; licensed under the Educational
  Community License version 1.0.
  
  CONTACT: info@music-encoding.org
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="text" n="0">
  <head>Text in MEI</head>
  <p>This chapter describes methods for encoding textual content with MEI. Textual information on
    scores has several different uses, although some text is closer to music notation than other.
    For example tempo marks, directives and lyrics are directly functional to the notated music and
    are, therefore, described in other chapters (see for example <ptr target="#lyrics"/> and <ptr
      target="#textDirectives"/>). This chapter, on the other hand, focuses on the text that
    accompanies the score, i.e., paratext (prefatory material, title pages, back matter, appendices,
    etc.), titles, prose, poetry, etc.</p>
  <p>Most of the elements described here take inspiration from encoding formats that deal primarily
    with text, such as HTML and the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI). These elements are provided to
    encode relatively basic textual information. For deeper encoding of text, these Guidelines
    recommend consideration of other text-specific encoding formats with embedded MEI markup.</p>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="textDivisions">
    <head>Organizing Text into Divisions</head>
    <p>Text can be organized in different parts, for example in chapters or sections. The
        <gi>div</gi> element is used to encode such structural divisions.</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="div" atts="type subtype"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>For example, printed scores, before the actual notation, can have text that can be organized
      in multiple section (e.g. a preface, a critical report, performance instructions, etc. for
      which see the following sections); each of these sections should be identified by a different
        <gi>div</gi> element. Text might also occur in between music sections (see <ptr
        target="#mdivContent"/>), for example in a collection of romantic piano works, a few pieces
      might be followed by poetry. Such a text would be encoded with <gi>div</gi> as shown in the
      following example:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <mdiv>
        <section>
          <!-- Score of Franz Liszt's "Sonetto 104 del Petrarca -->
        </section>
        <div>
          <!-- Text of Francesco Petrarca's Sonett n. 104. -->
          <lg>
            <l>L'aspectata vertù, che 'n voi fioriva</l>
            <l>quando Amor cominciò darvi bataglia,</l>
            <!-- ... -->
          </lg>
        </div>
      </mdiv>
    </egXML>

    <p>Textual divisions may have titles or other forms of headers, which are encoded with the
        <gi>head</gi> element.</p>

    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="head"/>
      </specList>
    </p>

    <p>The following example shows the encoding of a preface translated into three different
      languages, each with a different title: </p>

    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <div xml:lang="en">
        <head>Preface</head>
        <!-- text -->
      </div>
      <div xml:lang="de">
        <head>Vorwort</head>
        <!-- text -->
      </div>
      <div xml:lang="it">
        <head>Prefazione</head>
        <!-- text -->
      </div>
    </egXML>
    <p>Having said that <gi>div</gi> identifies any structural organization of text, it is often
      helpful to distinguish the typology of division. The attributes <att>type</att> and
        <att>subtype</att> can be used for this purpose. It is required that <att>type</att> be
      present when <att>subtype</att> is used, though their value can be freely set by the
      encoder.</p>

    <p>The following example shows the use of <att>type</att> to indicate three prefaces in English,
      German and Italian are columns on the same page.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <div xml:lang="en" type="column" n="1">
        <head>Preface</head>
        <!-- text -->
      </div>
      <div xml:lang="de" type="column" n="2">
        <head>Vorwort</head>
        <!-- text -->
      </div>
      <div xml:lang="it" type="column" n="3">
        <head>Prefazione</head>
        <!-- text -->
      </div>
      <pb/>
    </egXML>
  </div>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="textProse">
    <head>Paragraphs</head>
    <p> Paragraphs are fundamental to prose text and typically group one or more sentences that form
      a logical passage. A paragraph is usually typographically distinct: The text begins on a new
      line and the first letter of the content is often indented, enlarged, or both.</p>
    <p>A paragraph is encoded with the <gi>p</gi> element:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="p"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>Prose text is used for several different purposes within a MEI document, therefore <gi>p</gi>
      can occur in many situations. For example, it may be used within metadata elements (see <ptr
        target="#header"/>):</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The encoding contains only the first 5 measures.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
    </egXML>
    <p>Alternatively, paragraphs may be part of the document contents (so encoded within
        <gi>music</gi>), either as <ref target="#textFrontBack">paratextual material</ref>, or
      within the music notation. In these cases, a paragraph will likely be contained by a
        <gi>div</gi> or other elements containing prose (e.g. <gi>annot</gi>, <gi>figDesc</gi>,
      etc.).</p>
    <p>The following example shows a paragraph in a preface section:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <front>
        <div>
          <head>The Preludes<lb/>Symphonic Poem No.3 by F. Liszt.</head>
          <p>What else is our life but a series of preludes to that unknown Hymn, the first and
            solemn note of which is intoned by Death?</p>
        </div>
      </front>
    </egXML>
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="textLists">
    <head>Lists</head>
    <p>When a text contains lists, they can be encoded with the following elements:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="list" atts="type subtype"/>
        <specDesc key="head"/>
        <specDesc key="item"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>The <gi>list</gi> element can identify any kind of list; the <att>type</att> attribute can be
      used to specify whether the list is ordered, unordered etc. Each item in the list is encoded
      with the <gi>item</gi> element. The <att>n</att> can be used to record a label for a list
      item, as in the following example:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <p>The modulation follows the following steps: <list type="ordered">
          <item n="1">C major</item>
          <item n="2">A minor</item>
          <item n="3">D major seventh</item>
          <item n="4">G major</item>
        </list>
      </p>
    </egXML>
    <p>Occasionally, lists have headers or titles, which can be encoded with <gi>head</gi>:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <list>
        <head>Ornaments in different languages</head>
        <item xml:lang="en" n="English">Turn</item>
        <item xml:lang="it" n="Italian">Gruppetto</item>
        <item xml:lang="fr" n="French">Gruppetto</item>
        <item xml:lang="de" n="German">Doppelschlag</item>
      </list>
    </egXML>
  </div>
  <!-- PR: The following section describes TEI use of quote, not MEI. :-)  In MEI, quote is a quoted block from
    another source. If we ever get around to adding the kind of quotation you're describing here, which is
    by the way, much more useful in TEI than MEI, I think we should use 'q'.  A short (inline) quotation is 'q',
    a block (longer) quotation is 'quote'.  Get it?  :-) -->
  <div type="div2" xml:id="textQuote">
    <head>Quotation</head>
    <p>It is common, in many types of texts, to use quotation marks. Following the Text Encoding
      Initiative recommendation, it is suggested to prioritize the encoding of textual function over
      typographical rendering, which is subject to variation (for example the English "" and the
      German „“).</p>
    <p>A quotation is typically attributed to another text than to the one being encoded. The
        <gi>quote</gi> element is used to mark this function:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="quote"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <p>The following examples show the use of <gi>quote</gi>.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <front>
        <div>
          <head>Les Préludes<lb/>Poème symphonique No.3 de F. Liszt.</head>
          <p>
            <!-- Other text --> Cependant l'homme ne se résigne guère à goûter longtemps la
            bienfaisante tiédeur qui l'a d'abord charmé au sein de la nature, et lorsque <quote>la
              trompette a jeté le signal des alarmes</quote>, il court au poste périlleux quelle que
            soit la guerre qui l'appelle à ses rangs, afin de retrouver dans le combat la pleine
            conscience de lui-même et l'entière possession de ses forces. </p>
        </div>
      </front>
    </egXML>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <p>Hugh MacDonald has argued that Liszt's Symphonic Poems were meant to <quote>display the
          traditional logic of symphonic thought</quote>.</p>
    </egXML>
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="textPoetry">
    <head>Poetry</head>
    <p>This <gi>lg</gi> (line group) element is used generically to encode any section of text that
      is organized as a group of lines. Although, following the recommendations of the Text Encoding
      Initiative, it is recommended to use it for marking up poetry together with the other
      following elements:</p>
    <p>
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="lg"/>
        <specDesc key="head"/>
        <specDesc key="l"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    <!-- PR: I don't understand what you're saying about <gi>l</gi> and its correspondence to a line of text.  Can you explain please? -->
    <p>Because <gi>lg</gi> groups verses, it can be used to encode different stanzas when present.
      The <gi>l</gi> element, instead, identifies a verse, which does not necessarily correspond to
      a line of text, which is why the <gi>lb</gi> element is allowed within <gi>l</gi>. Moreover,
      it is common for a poem to include a title or a header, as is demonstrated by the following
      example:</p>

    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <mdiv>
        <section>
          <!-- Score of Franz Liszt's "Sonetto 104 del Petrarca" -->
        </section>
        <div>
          <!-- Text of Francesco Petrarca's Sonett n. 104. -->
          <lg>
            <head>Sonetto 104</head>
            <l>L'aspectata vertù, che 'n voi fioriva</l>
            <l>quando Amor cominciò darvi bataglia,</l>
            <l>produce or frutto, che quel fiore aguaglia,</l>
            <l>et che mia speme fa venire a riva.</l>
            <!-- ... -->
          </lg>
        </div>
      </mdiv>
    </egXML>

  </div>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="textFrontBack">
    <head>Paratext</head>
    <p>This section introduces paratextual material, such as title pages, prefaces, indexes and any
      other text that precedes or follows the actual score.</p>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="textFront">
      <head>Front Matter</head>
      <p>By <soCalled>front matter</soCalled> these Guidelines mean distinct sections of a text
        (usually, but not necessarily, a printed one), prefixed to it by way of introduction or
        identification as a part of its production. Features such as title pages or prefaces are
        clear examples; a less definite case might be the prologue attached to a dramatic work. The
        front matter of an encoded text should not be confused with the MEI header described in
        chapter <ptr target="#header"/>, which provides metadata for the entire file.</p>
      <p>An encoder may choose simply to ignore the front matter in a text, if the original
        presentation of the work is of no interest, or for other reasons. No specific tags are
        provided for the various kinds of subdivision which may appear within front matter: instead,
        generic <gi>div</gi> (“division”) elements may be used, which should not be confused with
          <gi>mdiv</gi> (“musical division”) elements. The following suggested values for the
          <att>type</att> attribute may be used to distinguish various kinds of division
        characteristic of front matter: </p>
      <list type="gloss">
        <label>'preface' – </label>
        <item>A foreword or preface addressed to the reader in which the author or publisher
          explains the content, purpose, or origin of the text. </item>
        <label>'ack' – </label>
        <item>A formal declaration of acknowledgement by the author in which persons and
          institutions are thanked for their part in the creation of a text.</item>
        <label>'dedication' – </label>
        <item>A formal offering or dedication of a text to one or more persons or institutions by
          the author.</item>
        <label>'abstract' – </label>
        <item>A summary of the content of a text as continuous prose.</item>
        <label>'contents' – </label>
        <item>A table of contents, specifying the structure of a work and listing its constituents.
          The list element should be used to mark its structure.</item>
        <label>'frontispiece' – </label>
        <item>A pictorial frontispiece, possibly including some text.</item>
      </list>
      <p>The following extended example demonstrates how various parts of the front matter of a text
        may be encoded. The front part begins with a title page, which is presented in section <ptr
          target="#textTitlePages"/>, below. This is followed by a dedication and a preface, each of
        which is encoded as a distinct div: </p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <titlePage><!-- transcription of title page --></titlePage>
        <div type="dedication">
          <p><!-- Dedicatory text --></p>
        </div>
        <div type="preface">
          <head>Preface</head>
          <p><!-- paragraph 1 --></p>
          <p><!-- paragraph 2 --></p>
          <!-- additional material -->
        </div>
      </egXML>
      <p>The front matter concludes with another <gi>div</gi> element, shown in the next example,
        this time containing a table of contents, which contains a <gi>list</gi> element (as
        described in chapter <ptr target="#textLists"/>). Note the use of the <gi>ptr</gi> element
        to provide page-references: the implication here is that the target identifiers (song1,
        song2, etc.) will correspond with identifiers used for the <gi>mdiv</gi> elements containing
        the individual songs. (For a description of the <gi>ptr</gi> element, see chapter <ptr
          target="#ptrRef"/>.) </p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <div type="contents">
          <head>Contents</head>
          <list form="ordered">
            <item>On Wenlock Edge <ptr target="#song1"/></item>
            <item>From Far, From Eve and Morning <ptr target="#song2"/></item>
            <item>Is My Team Ploughing? <ptr target="#song3"/></item>
            <item>Oh, When I Was In Love With You <ptr target="#song4"/></item>
            <item>Bredon Hill <ptr target="#song5"/></item>
            <item>Clun <ptr target="#song6"/></item>
          </list>
        </div>
      </egXML>
      <p>Alternatively, the pointers in the table of contents might link to the page breaks at which
        a song begins, assuming that these have been included in the markup: </p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <list form="ordered">
          <item>On Wenlock Edge <ref target="#song1-p1">1</ref></item>
          <item>From Far, From Eve and Morning <ref target="#song2-p15">15</ref></item>
          <!-- .... -->
        </list>
        <!-- Later in the document -->
        <mdiv type="song">
          <pb xml:id="song1-p1"/>
          <!-- .... -->
        </mdiv>
        <mdiv type="song">
          <pb xml:id="song2-p15"/>
          <!-- .... -->
        </mdiv>
        <!-- .... -->
      </egXML>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="textTitlePages">
      <head>Title Pages</head>
      <p>Detailed analysis of the title page and other preliminaries of older printed books and
        manuscripts is of major importance in descriptive bibliography and the cataloging of printed
        books; such analysis, however, requires a more detailed approach than the general one
        described here. The following elements are suggested as a means of encoding the major
        features of most title pages: </p>
      <p>
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="titlePage"/>
          <specDesc key="p"/>
          <specDesc key="table"/>
          <specDesc key="list"/>
          <specDesc key="quote"/>
          <specDesc key="lg"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <!-- TODO: Include or not? NOT CURRENTLY ALLOWED! <p>The graphic element is included so as to enable
          encoders to record the presence of complex non-textual material on a title page. For
          simple cases such as printers' ornaments or illustrations, the graphic element discussed
          in section <!-\-XX, “Graphics and other non-textual components”-\->, should be adequate. </p>-->
      <p>The following example shows the title page of the work presented above. Note the use of the
          <gi>lb</gi> element to mark the line breaks of the original where necessary.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <titlePage>
          <p>ON WENLOCK EDGE</p>
          <p>A CYCLE OF SIX SONGS<lb/> FOR TENOR VOICE ___ WITH ACCOMPANIMENT OF<lb/> Pianoforte and
            String Quartet (ad lib)<lb/> THE WORDS BY A. E. HOUSMAN<lb/> (FROM "A SHROPSHIRE
            LAD")</p>
          <p>
            <figure/>
          </p>
          <p>MUSIC BY<lb/> R. VAUGHAN<lb/> WILLIAMS</p>
          <list>
            <item>PRICE $3.75</item>
            <item>(COMPLETE WITH SET OF STRING PARTS $5.00</item>
            <item>STRING PARTS SEPARATELY $1.00</item>
          </list>
          <p>Boosey &amp; Hawkes, Inc.</p>
          <p>New York, U.S.A.</p>
          <p>London &#xb7; Toronto &#xb7; Sydney &#xb7; Capetown</p>
        </titlePage>
      </egXML>
      <p>The physical rendition of title page information is often of considerable importance. One
        approach to this requirement would be to use the <gi>rend</gi> element, described in chapter
          <ptr target="#textRendition"/> to specify the rendition of each of the components of the
        title page. Another would be to employ a CSS stylesheet. Finally, a module customized for
        the description of typographic entities such as pages, lines, rules, etc., bearing
        special-purpose attributes to describe line-height, leading, degree of kerning, font, etc.
        could be employed.</p>
      <!--Further discussion of these issues is provided in chapter <ptr target="#"/> -->
      <!--TODO: Add reference to “Representation of Primary Sources”-->
    </div>

  </div>



  <div type="div2" xml:id="textBack">
    <head>Back Matter</head>
    <p>Conventions vary as to which elements are grouped as back matter and which as front. For
      example, some books place the table of contents at the front, and others at the back.
      <!-- TODO: Even
          title pages may appear at the back of a book as well as at the front. The content model
          for back and front elements are therefore identical. <hi rend="color(FF0000)">(NOT YET IN
            MEI!)</hi> -->
    </p>
    <p>The following suggested values may be used for the <att>type</att> attribute on all division
      elements, in order to distinguish various kinds of divisions characteristic of back matter: </p>
    <list type="gloss">
      <label>'appendix' – </label>
      <item>An ancillary self-contained section of a work, often providing additional but in some
        sense extra-canonical text.</item>
      <label>'glossary' – </label>
      <item>A list of terms associated with definition texts (‘glosses’).</item>
      <label>'notes' – </label>
      <item>A section in which textual notes are gathered together.</item>
      <label>'bibliography' – </label>
      <item>A list of bibliographic citations.</item>
      <label>'index' – </label>
      <item>Any form of index to the work.</item>
      <label>'colophon' – </label>
      <item>A statement appearing at the end of a book describing the conditions of its physical
        production.</item>
    </list>
    <p>No additional elements are proposed for the encoding of back matter at present. Some
      characteristic examples follow; first, an index (for the case in which a printed index is of
      sufficient interest to merit transcription): </p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <back>
        <div type="index">
          <head>Index</head>
          <list type="index">
            <item>a2, a3, etc., <ref>175-176</ref></item>
            <item>Abbreviations, <ref>3</ref>
              <list type="indexentry">
                <item>Percussion, <ref>205-213</ref></item>
                <item>Strings, <ref>307</ref></item>
              </list>
            </item>
            <item>Afterbeats, <ref>77</ref></item>
          </list>
        </div>
      </back>
    </egXML>
    <p>Note that if the page breaks in the original source have also been explicitly encoded, and
      given identifiers, the references to them in the above index can more usefully be recorded as
      links. For example, assuming that the encoding of page 77 of the original source starts like
      this:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <pb xml:id="text.P77"/>
    </egXML>
    <p>then the last item above might be encoded more usefully in either of the following forms:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <item>Afterbeats, <ref target="#text.P77">77</ref>
      </item>
    </egXML>
  </div>

</div>
