<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="tagDoc" id="tagDesc_change"><h2>&lt;change&gt; change</h2><h3>Description:</h3><p> Individual change within the revision description. Additions, deletions, and significant
      recoding should be noted, but not correction of minor typographical errors. It is
      recommended that revisions should be entered in reverse chronological order, with the
      most recent &lt;change&gt; first. The resp attribute contains a pointer to an element
      containing info about the person/entity responsible for change. The edition element can
      be used to designate an MEI encoding that has been so substantively changed that it
      constitutes a new version that supersedes earlier versions. This element is modelled on
      an element in Encoded Archival Description (EAD). 
   </p><h3>May contain:</h3><p><a title="Show description of changedesc-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/changedesc">changedesc</a>, <a title="Show description of date-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/date">date</a>, <a title="Show description of respstmt-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/respstmt">respstmt</a></p><h3>May occur within:</h3><p><a title="Show description of revisiondesc-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/revisiondesc">revisiondesc</a></p><h3>Attributes:</h3><ul><li><p><span class="attributeName">analog</span>, optional, CDATA 
            <span class="description">contains a reference to a field or element in another
               descriptive encoding system to which an MEI element is comparable. Mapping
               elements from one system to another may help a repository harvest selected
               data from the MEI file to build a basic catalog record. The encoding system
               from which fields are taken must be specified. When possible, subfields as
               well as fields should be specified, e.g., subfields within MARC
               fields.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">n</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">provides a label (name or number) for an element. While
               its value need not be unique, it is required to be a single token.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">xml:id</span>, optional, xs:ID 
            <span class="description">regularizes the naming of an element and thus
               facilitates building links between it and other resources. Each id attribute
               within a document must have a unique value.
            </span></p></li></ul><h3>Module:</h3><p> header </p></div>