<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="tagDoc" id="tagDesc_front"><h2>&lt;front&gt; front</h2><h3>Description:</h3><p> Bundles prefatory text found before the start of the musical text. &lt;titlepage&gt; may
      be used to transcribe the item's title page. Other front matter structures, such as a
      preface, dedication, or table of contents, may be encoded as textual divisions; that is,
      as &lt;div&gt;s, with an optional &lt;head&gt; sub-element describing the nature of the
      division. The &lt;pb&gt; element is allowed here in order to accommodate page images,
      e.g. cover, endpapers, etc. before and after the actual textual matter. This element is
      modelled on an element in the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI). 
   </p><h3>May contain:</h3><p><a title="Show description of div-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/div">div</a>,
      <a href="/documentation/tagLibrary/lb">lb</a>, <a title="Show description of pb-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/pb">pb</a>,
      <a title="Show description of titlepage-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/titlepage">titlepage</a></p><h3>May occur within:</h3><p><a title="Show description of music-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/music">music</a></p><h3>Attributes:</h3><ul><li><p><span class="attributeName">facs</span>, optional, xs:IDREFS 
            <span class="description">permits the current element to reference a facsimile
               image or image zone which corresponds to it.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">n</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">provides a label (name or number) for an element. While
               its value need not be unique, it is required to be a single token.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">xml:id</span>, optional, xs:ID 
            <span class="description">regularizes the naming of an element and thus
               facilitates building links between it and other resources. Each id attribute
               within a document must have a unique value.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">xml:lang</span>, optional, xs:language 
            <span class="description">identifies the language of the word or text phrase
               marked. The values for this attribute are language 'tags' as defined in BCP
               47. All language tags that make use of private use subtags must be
               documented in a corresponding language element in the MEI header whose id
               attribute is the same as the language tag's value.
            </span></p></li></ul><h3>Module:</h3><p> text </p></div>