<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="tagDoc" id="tagDesc_when"><h2>&lt;when&gt; when</h2><h3>Description:</h3><p> Indicates a point in time either absolutely (using the absolute attribute), or relative
      to other elements in the same timeline element (using the interval and since
      attributes). The data attribute may be used to reference one or more features that occur
      at this point in time. This element is modelled on an element in the Text Encoding
      Initiative (TEI). 
   </p><h3>May contain:</h3><p> EMPTY </p><h3>May occur within:</h3><p><a title="Show description of timeline-element" href="/documentation/tagLibrary/timeline">timeline</a></p><h3>Attributes:</h3><ul><li><p><span class="attributeName">absolute</span>, optional, CDATA 
            <span class="description">provides an absolute value for the time associated with
               a point on a timeline. This attribute is required for the element designated
               as the origin by the parent timeline.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">data</span>, optional, xs:IDREFS 
            <span class="description">used to link metadata elements to one or more
               data-containing elements.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">interval</span>, optional, xs:decimal, 1 - ∞ 
            <span class="description">specifies the (positive) numeric portion of a time
               interval.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">n</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">provides a label (name or number) for an element. While
               its value need not be unique, it is required to be a single token.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">since</span>, optional, xs:IDREF 
            <span class="description">identifies the reference point for determining the time
               of the current when element, which is obtained by adding the interval to the
               time of the reference point. The value should be the ID of another when
               element in the same timeline. If the since attribute is omitted and the
               absolute attribute is not specified, then the reference point is understood
               to be the preceding when element.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">unit</span>, optional, xs:NMTOKEN 
            <span class="description">indicates the units used for a measurement, usually
               using the standard symbol for the desired unit.
            </span></p></li><li><p><span class="attributeName">xml:id</span>, optional, xs:ID 
            <span class="description">regularizes the naming of an element and thus
               facilitates building links between it and other resources. Each id attribute
               within a document must have a unique value.
            </span></p></li></ul><h3>Module:</h3><p> linkalign </p></div>